[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "The Mohr’s theory of failure can be symbolically expressed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) τmax=F(σn) and σmax–σmin = f(σmax +σmin)",
            "b) τmax = σmax– σmin",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mohr’s theory of failure can be symbolically expressed as:\nσmax–σmin = f (σmax +σmin) or τmax=f (σn)."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "The concept of a three dimension yield envelope was presented by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) D.C. Drucker and Prager",
            "b) Mohr",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effect of intermediate principal was studied by D.C. Drucker and W. Prager in 1952, who proposed the concept of a three dimensional yield envelope."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "A major drawback of Mohr criterion is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape of the envelope",
            "b) Principal stress",
            "c) Shape of the plane",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The major drawback of Mohr criterion is that the curved shape of the envelope, hence the functional form of the equation τmax=F (σn) is not amendable to mathematical computation."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "The yield or failure criterion can be expressed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) f(I1,I2)=0",
            "b) f(I1,I2,I3)=0",
            "c) f(σ1,σ2,σ3)=0",
            "d) f(σmax +σmin)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The yield criterion may be expressed as f (I1, I2, I3) = 0\nWhere I1, I2, I3 are the invariant of stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "If the auxiliary plane in hydrostatic axis passes through the origin, then its equation is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ1+σ2+σ3=0",
            "b) σ1+σ2+σ3=constant",
            "c) I1+ I2+I3 =0",
            "d) f(σ1,σ2,σ3)=0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the auxiliary plane passes through the origin its equation is σ1+σ2+σ3=0 and equation will be σ1+σ2+σ3=constant if the plane is perpendicular to the hydrostatic axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "The intersection of the yield surface or envelope with octahedral plane is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yield point",
            "b) Deviation point",
            "c) Failure locus",
            "d) Space diagonal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The intersection of yield surface with octahedral plane is called the failure locus. A point on the failure locus represents the stress state at incipient failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "The hydrostatic pressure’s inability to produce failure under normal pressure was first demonstrated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cross land",
            "b) W. Pager",
            "c) D.C. Drucker",
            "d) Mohr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Experiments conducted by Cross land in 1965 have demonstrated that a pure state of hydrostatic pressure is unable to produce failure even under enormous pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Which of the following equation represent hydrostatic pressure in its purest form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ1+σ2+σ3=0",
            "b) σ1+σ2+σ3=constant",
            "c) σ1=σ2=σ3",
            "d) σmax+ σmin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to cross land σ1=σ2=σ3 represent hydrostatic pressure in its purest form."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "The Mohr-Coulomb criterion assumes that the strength of the soil is independent of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ1",
            "b) σ2",
            "c) σ3",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Mohr-Coulomb criterion implicitly assumes that the strength is independent of the intermediate principal stress σ2."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "The auxiliary plane in the hydrostatic axis can also be called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Failure plane",
            "b) Octahedral plane",
            "c) Deviatoric plane",
            "d) Principal plane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since all the points in the auxiliary plane represent deviatorial state of stress, the plane is also called the deviatoric plane. "
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "The plastic state of stress when the failure is imminent was investigated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rankine",
            "b) Darcy",
            "c) Skempton",
            "d) Terzaghi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The plastic state of stress failure of the soil samples was studied by Rankine in the year 1860. Darcy is known for his works in the field of soil permeability.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "___________ is used for maintaining the ground surface at different elevations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Floor",
            "b) Retaining wall",
            "c) Ceiling",
            "d) Roof"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The retaining wall is used to resist the lateral earth pressure due to the backfill soil. It prevents the landslides by maintaining the ground surface at different elevations in hilly regions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "The material retained by the retaining wall is known as_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) roof",
            "b) slab",
            "c) backfill",
            "d) footing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The material retained by the retaining wall is known as backfill. The surface of the backfill can be both horizontal as well as inclined. It should be noted that the angle does not exceed the angle of repose of the soil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "The backfill has its top surface ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal only",
            "b) inclined only",
            "c) both horizontal and inclined",
            "d) vertical only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The backfill can have its top surface as a horizontal surface or as an inclined surface. It should be noted that the angle does not exceed the angle of repose of the soil or else it will fail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "The portion of backfill lying above a horizontal plane of wall is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) surcharge",
            "b) base",
            "c) foot",
            "d) truss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The portion of backfill lying above a horizontal plane of wall is called as the surcharge. The surcharge is a load which is imposed upon the surface of the soil close enough to the excavation to cause a lateral pressure to act on the system in addition to the basic earth pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Surcharge angle β is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) inclination of surcharge to the vertical",
            "b) inclination of surcharge to the normal of the wall",
            "c) inclination of surcharge to the horizontal",
            "d) inclination of surcharge to the tangent to the wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The surcharge is a load which is imposed upon the surface of the soil close enough to the excavation to cause a lateral pressure to act on the system in addition to the basic earth pressure. Its inclination to the horizontal is known as Surcharge angle β.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "A body is said to be in plastic equilibrium, if every point of it is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) in the verge of failure",
            "b) in equilibrium",
            "c) in stable state",
            "d) elastic state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A body is said to be in plastic equilibrium, if every point of it is in the verge of failure. The transition from the state of plastic equilibrium to the state of plastic flow represents the failure of the soil mass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "The stress condition during plastic equilibrium can be represented by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{σ_1-σ_3}{2}\\frac{σ_1+σ_3}{2} sinφ=cosφ \\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{σ_1-σ_3}{2}+\\frac{σ_1+σ_3}{2} sinφ=c cosφ\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{σ_1*σ_3}{2}-\\frac{σ_1+σ_3}{2} sinφ=c cosφ\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{σ_1-σ_3}{2}-\\frac{σ_1+σ_3}{2} sinφ=c cosφ\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The stress condition during plastic equilibrium can be represented by the equation of Mohr-Coulomb,\n\\(\\frac{σ_1-σ_3}{2}-\\frac{σ_1+σ_3}{2} sinφ=c cosφ,\\) \nWhere, σ1=major principal stress\nσ3=minor principal stress\nφ=angle of internal friction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "The stress condition during plastic equilibrium in terms of tangent of angle is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(σ_1=tan⁡(45°+\\frac{φ}{2})+σ_3 tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}) \\) ",
            "b) \\(σ_1=2c+σ_3 tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "c) \\(σ_1=2c \\,tan⁡(45°+\\frac{φ}{2})+σ_3\\) ",
            "d) \\(σ_1=2c \\,tan⁡(45°+\\frac{φ}{2})+σ_3 tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The stress condition during plastic equilibrium can be represented by the equation of Mohr-Coulomb,\n\\(\\frac{σ_1-σ_3}{2}-\\frac{σ_1+σ_3}{2} sinφ=c cosφ,\\) \nsince tan⁡φ=sinφ/cosφ\n∴ \\(σ_1=2c \\,tan⁡(45°+\\frac{φ}{2})+σ_3 tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}).\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "The flow value is given by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(N_φ=cot^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "b) \\(N_φ=cos^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "c) \\(N_φ=tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "d) \\(N_φ=sin^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The flow value is given by,\n\\(N_φ= tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}),\\) \nwhere, Nφ=flow value\nφ=angle of internal friction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "The plastic equilibrium stress equation in terms of flow valve is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ1=2c∛Nφ+σ3 Nφ",
            "b) σ1=2c√Nφ+σ3 Nφ",
            "c) σ1=2cNφ-σ3 Nφ",
            "d) σ1=Nφ+σ3 Nφ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The stress condition during plastic equilibrium is given by,\n\\(σ_1=2c \\,tan⁡(45°+\\frac{φ}{2})+σ_3 tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}),\\) \nsince, \\(N_φ= tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}),\\) \n∴ σ1=2c√Nφ+σ3 Nφ.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "The Mohr Coulomb equation in terms of stress components in x-z plane is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sqrt{((\\frac{σ_z-σ_x}{2})^2+τ_{xz}^2))} -\\frac{σ_z+σ_x}{2} sinφ=c cosφ\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sqrt{((\\frac{σ_z-σ_x}{2})^2+τ_{xz}^2))} \\frac{σ_z+σ_x}{2} sinφ=c cosφ\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\sqrt{((\\frac{σ_z-σ_x}{2})^2+τ_{xz}^2))} = c cosφ\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\sqrt{((\\frac{σ_z-σ_x}{2})^2+τ_{xz}^2))} -\\frac{σ_z+σ_x}{2} sinφ=cosφ\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Mohr Coulomb equation is given by,\n\\(\\frac{σ_1-σ_3}{2}-\\frac{σ_1+σ_3}{2} sinφ=c cosφ,\\) \nWhere, σ_1=major principal stress and σ3=minor principal stress.\n∴ in terms of stress components in x-z plane it is,\n\\(\\sqrt{((\\frac{σ_z-σ_x}{2})^2+τ_{xz}^2))} -\\frac{σ_z+σ_x}{2} sinφ=c cosφ,\\) \nwhere, σz=stress in z-direction\nσx= stress in x-direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Combing the three equations, \\(\\sqrt{((\\frac{σ_z-σ_x}{2})^2+τ_{xz}^2))} -\\frac{σ_z+σ_x}{2} sinφ=c cosφ\\), \\(\\frac{∂σ_x}{∂x}+\\frac{∂τ_{xz}}{∂z}=0\\), and \\(\\frac{∂τ_{xz}}{∂x}+\\frac{∂σ_x}{∂z}+γ=0\\), lead to the equation called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kolter’s equation",
            "b) Terzaghi’s equation",
            "c) Darcy’s equation",
            "d) Skempton’s equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The material just in the verge of flowing plastically is still in static equilibrium and will satisfy the equations of, \\(\\frac{∂σ_x}{∂x}+\\frac{∂τ_{xz}}{∂z}=0, \\,and\\, \\frac{∂τ_{xz}}{∂x}+\\frac{∂σ_x}{∂z}+γ=0.\\)  These equations with the Mohr Coulomb equation give the Kolter’s equation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "The solution of Kolter’s equation gives ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) permeability of soil",
            "b) orientation of slip lines",
            "c) specific gravity of grains",
            "d) seepage pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The solution of Kolter’s equation for a given boundary condition gives the orientation of slip planes together with the stress at each point at the failure zone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "In active state, the major principal stress σ1  is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal direction",
            "b) vertical direction",
            "c) can be both vertical and horizontal direction",
            "d) in no direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In active state, the major principal stress denoted by σ1  is in vertical direction. While in the passive state, the major principal stress σ1  is in horizontal direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "In active state, the minor principal stress σ3 is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal direction",
            "b) vertical direction",
            "c) can be both vertical and horizontal direction",
            "d) in no direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In active state, the minor principal stress denoted by σ3    is in horizontal direction. While in the passive state, the minor principal stress σ3     is in vertical direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "In passive state, the major principal stress σ1 ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal direction",
            "b) vertical direction",
            "c) can be both vertical and horizontal direction",
            "d) in no direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In passive state, the minor principal stress denoted by σ3  is in vertical direction. While in the passive state, the major principal stress σ1 is in horizontal direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "In passive state, the minor principal stress σ3   is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal direction",
            "b) vertical direction",
            "c) can be both vertical and horizontal direction",
            "d) in no direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In active state, the minor principal stress denoted by σ3 is in horizontal direction. While in the passive state, the minor principal stress σ3 is in vertical direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "For cohesion-less soil, the ratio of major to minor principal stress is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{σ_1}{σ_3} = cos^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{σ_1}{σ_3} = sin^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{σ_1}{σ_3} = tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{σ_1}{σ_3} = tan^2 (45°-\\frac{φ}{2})\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stress condition during plastic equilibrium is given by,\n\\(σ_1=2c \\,tan⁡(45°+\\frac{φ}{2})+σ_3 tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}),\\)  and for cohesion-less soil, c=0,\n∴ \\(\\frac{σ_1}{{σ_3}} = tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}).\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "The ratio of horizontal stress σh to vertical stress σv  is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) coefficient of earth pressure",
            "b) coefficient of volume change",
            "c) coefficient of compressibility",
            "d) coefficient of consolidation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient of earth pressure is defined as the ratio of The ratio of horizontal stress σh to vertical stress σv.\n∴ \\(K=\\frac{σ_h}{σ_v}.\\) Where, K = coefficient of earth pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "The coefficient of earth pressure for active state of plastic equilibrium is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(K_a=\\frac{1}{tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})} \\) ",
            "b) \\(K_a=tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}) \\) ",
            "c) \\(K_a=sin^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}) \\) ",
            "d) \\(K_a=\\frac{1}{cot^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})} \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the case of active state, the major principal stress denoted by σ1  is in vertical direction and the minor principal stress σ3  is in horizontal direction.\n∴ \\(\\frac{σ_1}{σ_3} =\\frac{σ_v}{σ_h} =K_a=\\frac{1}{tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})}. \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "The coefficient of earth pressure for passive state of plastic equilibrium is given by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(K_p=\\frac{1}{tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})} \\) ",
            "b) \\(K_p=tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "c) \\(K_p=sin^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "d) \\(K_p=\\frac{1}{cot^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})} \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the case of passive state, the major principal stress denoted by σ1 is in horizontal direction and the minor principal stress σ3  is in vertical direction.\n∴ \\(\\frac{σ_1}{σ_3} =\\frac{σ_h}{σ_v} =K_p=tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}). \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "The coefficient of earth pressure for active state of plastic equilibrium in terms of sine function is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(K_a=1-sinφ\\) ",
            "b) \\(K_a=\\frac{1-sinφ}{1+sinφ} \\) ",
            "c) \\(K_a=\\frac{1+sinφ}{1-sinφ} \\) ",
            "d) Ka=1+sinφ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The coefficient of earth pressure for active state of plastic equilibrium is,\n\\(K_a=\\frac{1}{tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})},\\) \n∴ therefore in terms of sine function,\n\\(K_a=\\frac{1}{tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})}=\\frac{1-sinφ}{1+sinφ}. \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "The coefficient of earth pressure for passive state of plastic equilibrium in terms of sine function is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(K_a=1-sinφ\\) ",
            "b) \\(K_a=\\frac{1-sinφ}{1+sinφ} \\) ",
            "c) \\(K_a=\\frac{1+sinφ}{1-sinφ} \\) ",
            "d) Ka=1+sinφ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The coefficient of earth pressure for active state of plastic equilibrium is,\n\\(K_p=tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}), \\) \n∴ therefore in terms of sine function,\n\\(K_p=tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})=\\frac{1+sinφ}{1-sinφ}. \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": " During the active state of plastic equilibrium, the retaining wall moves _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) towards the fill",
            "b) away from the fill",
            "c) does not change its position",
            "d) remains in equilibrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the active state of plastic equilibrium, the major principal stress denoted by σ1 is in vertical direction and the minor principal stress σ3  is in horizontal direction. Therefore, the movement of the wall will be away from the back fill.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "During the passive state of plastic equilibrium, the retaining wall moves _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) towards the fill",
            "b) away from the fill",
            "c) does not change its position",
            "d) remains in equilibrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During the passive state of plastic equilibrium, the major principal stress denoted by σ1  is in horizontal direction and the minor principal stress σ3  is in vertical direction. Therefore, the movement of the wall will be towards the back fill.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "In active state of plastic equilibrium, the earth pressure on the wall ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) is zero",
            "d) is constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the wall moves away from the backfill, mobilization of the internal resistance of the soil takes place in the direction away from the wall. Hence the earth pressure on the wall decreases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "In passive state of plastic equilibrium, the earth pressure on the wall ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)  increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) is zero",
            "d) is constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In passive state of plastic equilibrium, when the wall moves towards the fill, the earth pressure increases because the shearing resistance builds up in the direction of the wall.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "In active state, the failure wedge shows ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) downward movement",
            "b) upward movement",
            "c) left side movement",
            "d) right side movement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the active state of plastic equilibrium, the wall moves away from the fill because of the mobilization of the internal resistance of the soil taking place in the direction away from the wall. Due to this the failure wedge shows downward movement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "In passive state, the failure wedge shows ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) downward movement",
            "b) upward movement",
            "c) left side movement",
            "d) right side movement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In passive state of plastic equilibrium, the wall moves towards the fill because of the shearing resistance that builds up in the direction of the wall. Due to this the failure wedge shows upward movement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "The theory of plasticity pertaining to soils is based on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mohr’s theory",
            "b) Rankine’s method",
            "c) Mohr-coulomb theory",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The theory of plasticity pertaining to soils is based on Mohr’s theory of rupture."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "On designing retaining walls it is necessary to take care of __________ exerted by soil mass.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erosion",
            "b) Lateral pressure",
            "c) Surcharge",
            "d) Lateral stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the designing of retaining walls; sheet piles or other earth-retaining structures, it is necessary to compute the lateral pressure exerted by the retained mass of soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "The material retained or supported by the retaining structure is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surcharge",
            "b) Support wall",
            "c) Back fill",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The material retained or supported by the structure is called backfill which may have its top surface horizontal or inclined."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "The coefficient of earth pressure when the soil is at equilibrium is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) σv /σh",
            "b) σh /σv",
            "c) σv × σh",
            "d) σ1 / σ3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the soil is at elastic equilibrium(i.e. at rest) the ratio of horizontal to vertical stress is called the co-efficient of earth pressure of rest.\nσh /σv = K0."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "The computation of stress in plastic equilibrium is based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Theory of plasticity",
            "b) Mohr’s theory of rupture",
            "c) Rankine’s theory",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The theory on which the computation of the stress in a state of plastic equilibrium is based is called the theory of plasticity."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "The wedge-shaped portion of the backfill tending to move with the wall is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wedge fall",
            "b) Active fall",
            "c) Failure wedge",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During the active state, the wall moves away from backfill and a certain portion of the backfill in wedged-shaped tend to move which is called a failure wedge."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "In active stress, the major principal stress σ1 acting on the wall will be in __________ plane.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical",
            "b) Horizontal",
            "c) Inclined",
            "d) Zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In an active state, the major principal stress σ1 is vertical and the minor principal stress σ3 is horizontal."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "The plastic state of stress was proposed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mohr",
            "b) Rankine",
            "c) Coulomb",
            "d) Darcy"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The plastic state of stress when the failure is imminent was investigated by Rankine in 1860."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "The position of the backfill lying above the horizontal plane at the top of wall is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Active state",
            "b) Plasticity",
            "c) Surcharge",
            "d) Slip lines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The position of the backfill lying above a horizontal plane at the elevation of the top of a wall is called the surcharge, and its inclination to the horizontal is called surcharge angle β."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "What will be the co-efficient of passive earth pressure, at a depth of 8m in cohesion less soil sand with an angle of internal friction of 30° when the water rises to the ground level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given φ = 30°\nCo-efficient of passive earth pressure, Kp = (1 + sin φ) / (1 – sin φ)\nKp = (1 + sin 30)/ (1 – sin 30°)\nKP = 3. "
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "The coefficient of active earth pressure is_______ than the coefficient of passive pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than",
            "b) greater than",
            "c) equal to",
            "d) insufficient data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient of active earth pressure is less than that of the coefficient of passive earth pressure. The coefficient of active earth pressure is also less than that of the coefficient of earth pressure at rest.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "The coefficient earth pressure at rest is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than coefficient of active pressure",
            "b) greater than coefficient of active pressure",
            "c) equal to coefficient of active pressure",
            "d) one"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The coefficient earth pressure at rest is greater than that of the coefficient of active earth pressure. But, he coefficient earth pressure at rest is less than the coefficient of passive earth pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "For earth pressure at rest, there will be no ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertical stress",
            "b) shear stress",
            "c) horizontal stress",
            "d) both vertical and horizontal stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For earth pressure at rest, there is horizontal stress as well as the vertical stress. For earth pressure at rest, there will be no shear stresses.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "The lateral strain in the horizontal direction is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(∈_h=\\frac{1}{E} [σ_h-μ(σ_v)] \\) ",
            "b) \\(∈_h=\\frac{1}{E} [σ_h-μ(σ_h-σ_v)]\\) ",
            "c) \\(∈_h=\\frac{1}{E} [σ_h-μ(σ_h+σ_v)]\\) ",
            "d) \\(∈_h=\\frac{1}{E} [σ_h-(σ_h-σ_v)]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lateral strain ∈h in the horizontal direction is given by,\n\\(∈_h=\\frac{1}{E} [σ_h-μ(σ_h-σ_v )],\\) \nwhere, σh =horizontal stress\nσv =vertical stress\nE=elastic modulus\nμ= Poisson’s ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "The lateral earth pressure at rest with respect to Poisson’s ratio is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) σh=μ(σh-σv)",
            "b) σh=μ(σh-σv)",
            "c) σh=μ(σh+σv)",
            "d) σh=-μ(σh-σv)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The earth pressure at rest has the condition corresponding to ∈h=0.\nSince, \\(∈_h=\\frac{1}{E} [σ_h-μ(σ_h-σ_v)],\\) \n∴ σh=μ(σh+σv).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "The coefficient of earth pressure at rest is given by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(K_0=\\frac{μ}{1-μ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(K_0=\\frac{μ}{1+μ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(K_0=\\frac{2μ}{1-μ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(K_0=\\frac{1}{1-μ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient of earth pressure at rest is the ratio of the horizontal stress to the vertical stress.\nsince, σh=μ(σh+σv),\n∴ \\(\\frac{σ_h}{σ_v} = \\frac{μ}{1-μ}.\\) \n∴ \\(K_0 = \\frac{μ}{1-μ}.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "If γ is the unit weight of soil, then the lateral earth pressure at depth z of soil mass is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(σ_h=\\frac{3}{2} K_0 z\\) ",
            "b) σh=γz",
            "c) σh=-K0 γz",
            "d) σh=K0 γz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since the lateral earth pressure is given by,\nσh=μ(σh+σv )=K0 σv,\nsubstituting σv=γz,\n∴ σh=K0 γz.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "The pressure distribution diagram for earth pressure at rest is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) circular",
            "b) triangular",
            "c) rectangular",
            "d) square"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pressure distribution diagram for earth pressure at rest is triangular. If the retaining wall has a height of H, then the pressure at the base of wall is K0γH. At the top of wall, the pressure is zero.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "The total earth pressure P0 at rest per unit length for vertical height H is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(P_0=\\frac{1}{2}K_0γH^2\\) ",
            "b) P0=γH2",
            "c) P0=K0 γH2",
            "d) \\(P_0=\\frac{1}{2}K_0H^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pressure intensity P0 is given by,\nP0=K0 γz,\nThe total earth pressure P0 at rest per unit length is,\n\\(P_0=\\int_0^H K_0 γz.dz \\) \n∴ \\(P_0=\\frac{1}{2}K_0γH^2.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "The coefficient of earth pressure at rest is represented as _________ expression given by Jaky.",
        "Options": [
            "a) K0=1-sinφ",
            "b) K0=sinφ",
            "c) K0=1-cosφ",
            "d) K0=cosφ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient of earth pressure at rest is also computed from the expression given by Jaky in 1944 as,\nK0=1-sinφ,\nwhere, φ=angle of internal friction of the soil specimen.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "For cohesion-less soil, the angle of internal friction is 45°, find the K0.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.429",
            "b) 0.784",
            "c) 0.293",
            "d) 0.334"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nφ=450\nK0=1-sinφ=1-sin45=0.293.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "A backfill of a retaining wall consists of γ=19 kN/m3 which is 6 m high. Find the total earth pressure per meter length. Given coefficient of earth pressure at rest is 0.5.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 165 kN/m",
            "b) 178 kN/m",
            "c) 171 kN/m",
            "d) 345 kN/m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nγ=19 kN/m3\nH=6 m\n\\(P_0=\\frac{1}{2}K_0γH^2\\) \n\\(P_0=\\frac{1}{2}(0.5)(19)6^2 = 171 kN/m.\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "If K0=0.4, then find the value of µ.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.438",
            "b) 0.286",
            "c) 0.472",
            "d) 0.592"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given,\nK0=0.4\n\\(K_0=\\frac{μ}{1-μ}\\) \n\\(μ=\\frac{K_0}{1-K_0}\\) \n\\(μ=\\frac{0.4}{1-0.4}\\) \nμ=0.286.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "For μ=0.3, find K0.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.429",
            "b) 0.289",
            "c) 0.536",
            "d) 0.375"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Given,\nμ=0.3\n\\(K_0=\\frac{μ}{1-μ}=\\frac{0.3}{1-0.3} \\) \nK0=0.429.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "A backfill of a retaining wall consists of γ=19 kN/m3 which is 6 m high. Find the lateral earth pressure per meter length. Given coefficient of earth pressure at rest is 0.5.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 43 kN/m2",
            "b) 57 kN/m2",
            "c) 48 kN/m2",
            "d) 76 kN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:\nGiven,\nγ = 19 kN/m2\nz = 6 m\nK0 = 0.5\nP0 = K0 γz = 0.5×19×6\nP0 = 57 kN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Originally, Rankine’s theory of lateral earth pressure can be applied to only _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesion less soil",
            "b) Cohesive soil",
            "c) Fine grained soil",
            "d) Coarse grained soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As originally proposed, Rankine’ s theory of lateral pressure is applied to uniform cohesion less soils only. Later, it was extended to include cohesive soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Rankine’s theory of lateral pressure was extended to other soil by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resal and Bell",
            "b) Mohr",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The theory of lateral pressure was extended to cohesive, stratified, partially immersed and submerged soil was by Resal in 1910 and by Bell in 1915."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Based on the assumptions of Rankine’s theory, the soil mass is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stratified",
            "b) Submerged",
            "c) Homogeneous",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to the assumption of Rankine’s theory, the soil mass is semi-infinite, homogeneous, dry and cohesion less."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Which of the following cases for cohesion less backfill in Rankine’s theory is considered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Submerged backfill",
            "b) Moist backfill with no surcharge",
            "c) Backfill with sloping surface",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Rankine’s theory the following cases of cohesionless backfill are considered\ni) Dry or moist backfill with no surcharge\nii) Submerged backfill\niii) Backfill with a sloping surface and inclined back and surcharge."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "The factor that is responsible for inclination of resultant pressure to the retaining wall is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frictional force",
            "b) Surcharge",
            "c) Earth pressure",
            "d) Weight of the wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The retaining walls are constructed of masonry or concrete, due to this the frictional force develops. The existence of the friction makes the resultant pressure inclined to the wall at an angle that approaches the frictional angle between the soil and the wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "If the sand filled behind the retaining wall with saturated water with water, then the possible lateral pressure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lateral pressure due to submerged weight and Lateral pressure due to water",
            "b) Lateral pressure due to retaining wall",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lateral pressure is made up of two components for wetted soil in back of the retaining wall:\ni) Lateral pressure due to submerged weight ‘γ’ of the soil, and\nii) Lateral pressure due to water."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "The earth pressure at rest exerted on a retaining structure can be calculated using __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Theory of plasticity",
            "b) Theory of elasticity",
            "c) Mohr’s theory of rupture",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The earth pressure at rest, exerted on the back of the rigid, unyielding retaining structure, can be calculated using theory of elasticity."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "The value of K0(coefficient of earth pressure at rest) for loose sand is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.6",
            "b) 0.5",
            "c) 0.4",
            "d) 0.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of K0 for different soils is:\ni) Loose sand – 0.4\nii) Dense sand – 0.6\niii) Soft clay – 0.6\niv) Hard clay – 0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "The expression for K0 as given by Jacky is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) K0 = 1 – sin φ",
            "b) K0 = sin φ",
            "c) K0 = 1 – cos φ",
            "d) K0 = 1 + sin φ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: K0 can be calculated by using the following equation as computed by Jacky in 1944:\nK0 = 1 – sin φ."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "What will be the coefficient of earth pressure at rest for a rigid retaining wall, If the backfill consists of cohesion less soil having φ = 26°?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1295",
            "b) 0.6552",
            "c) 0.5616",
            "d) 0.7383"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Coefficient of earth pressure, K0 can be calculated using Jacky’s formula:\nGiven: φ = 26°\nFormula: K0=1 – sin φ\nK0 = 1 – sin 26°\nK0 = 1 – 0.4383\nK0 = 0.561628."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "For a dry backfill with no surcharge, the active earth pressure intensity is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pa=Ka γH",
            "b) pa=γH",
            "c) pa=Ka H",
            "d) pa=Ka γ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The active earth pressure intensity is given by,\npa=Ka γH,\nwhere, \\(\\frac{σ_1}{σ_3} = \\frac{σ_v}{σ_h} = K_a=\\frac{1}{tan^2(45°+\\frac{φ}{2})},\\) \nγ=unit weight of the back fill\nH= height of the retaining wall.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "The resultant active pressure per unit length of wall for dry backfill with no surcharge is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(P_a=\\frac{1}{2}K_aγH^2\\) ",
            "b) Pa=γH2",
            "c) Pa=Ka γH2",
            "d) Pa=Ka H2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pressure intensity p0 is given by,\npa=Ka γz,\nThe total earth pressure P0 at rest per unit length is,\n\\(P_a=\\int_0^HK_a γz.dz\\) \n∴  \\(P_a=\\frac{1}{2}K_aγH^2\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "The resultant active pressure per unit length of wall for dry backfill with no surcharge acting  at _________ above the base of wall.",
        "Options": [
            "a) H/2",
            "b) H",
            "c) H/6",
            "d) H/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pressure distribution of the stresses in the retaining wall due to the backfill is triangular one. Since the pressure distribution is triangular, the resultant active pressure per unit length of wall will act at the centroid of the wall, which is at a distance of H/3 from the base of the wall.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "For a submerged backfill, the active earth pressure is given by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pa=Kaγ’z",
            "b) pa=Kaγ’z-γwz",
            "c) pa=Kaγ’z+γwz",
            "d) pa=Kaγ’z*γwz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a submerged backfill, the lateral pressure is made up of two components,\n\nlateral pressure due to submerged weight of backfill\nlateral pressure due to water\n\n∴ pa=Kaγ’z+γwz.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "If free water stands on both side of a retaining wall, the lateral earth pressure is given by ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) pa=Ka γ’ z",
            "b) pa=Ka γ’ z-γw z",
            "c) pa=Ka γ’ z+γw z",
            "d) pa=Ka γ’ z*γw z"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the free water stands on both side of a retaining wall, the water pressure is not considered and the net pressure is given by,\npa=Ka γ’ z.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "If the angle of internal friction decreases, then Ka  ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) decreases",
            "b) increases",
            "c) equal to zero",
            "d) does not change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the coefficient of earth pressure for active state of plastic equilibrium is given by,\n\\(K_a=\\frac{1-sinφ}{1+sinφ}.\\) Therefore, from the equation it is clear that as the angle of internal friction decreases, then Ka increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "For the same value of φ, the backfill is partly submerged to height H2 and the backfill is moist to a depth H1. Find the lateral pressure intensity at the base of wall.",
        "Options": [
            "a) pa=Ka γH1-Ka γ’ H2+γw H2",
            "b) pa=Ka γH1+Ka γ’ H2+γw H2",
            "c) pa=Ka γH1+γw H2",
            "d) pa=Ka γH1+Ka γ’ H2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the backfill is partly submerged to height H2 and the backfill is moist to a depth H1, lateral pressure intensity is due to:\n\nlateral pressure due to moist weight of backfill\n\tlateral pressure due to saturated weight of backfill\n\tlateral pressure due to water\n\n∴ pa=Ka γH1+Ka γ’ H2+γw H2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "For the different value of φ, the backfill is partly submerged to height H2 and the backfill is moist to a depth H1. Find the lateral pressure intensity at the base of wall for φ1>φ2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) pa=Ka2 γH1-Ka2 γ’ H2+γw H2",
            "b) pa=Ka2 γH1+Ka2 γ’ H2+γw H2",
            "c) pa=Ka2 γH1+γw H2",
            "d) pa=Ka2 γH1+Ka2 γ’ H2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the different value of φ, the coefficient of active earth pressure is different. Since, the lateral pressure intensity is due to:\n\n\tlateral pressure due to moist weight of backfill\n\tlateral pressure due to saturated weight of backfill\n\tlateral pressure due to water\n\n∴ pa=Ka2 γH1+Ka2 γ’ H2+γw H2. We have to consider Ka2 over Ka1 as the φ1>φ2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "If the backfill carries a uniform surcharge q, then the lateral pressure at the depth of wall H is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pa=Ka γz+Ka q",
            "b) pa=Ka γz-Ka q",
            "c) pa=Ka γz*Ka q",
            "d) pa=Ka γz/Ka q"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the backfill is horizontal and carries a surcharge q, then the vertical pressure increment will be by q. Due to this, the lateral pressure will increase by Ka q. Hence, lateral pressure at the depth of wall H is pa=Ka γz+Ka q.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "The height of fill Ze, equivalent to uniform surcharge intensity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) q/γ",
            "b) q-γ",
            "c) q+γ",
            "d) q*γ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The height of fill Ze, equivalent to uniform surcharge intensity is given by,\nKa γze=Ka q,\n∴ \\(z_e=\\frac{q}{γ}.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "For finding out the active earth pressure for a backfill with sloping surface, the Rankine’s theory makes as additional assumption of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertical and lateral stresses are normal to surcharge",
            "b) vertical and lateral stresses are tangential to surcharge",
            "c) vertical and lateral stresses are conjugate",
            "d) vertical and lateral stresses are negligible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The additional assumption of vertical and lateral stresses are conjugate is made as, it can be shown that stresses on a given plane at a given point is parallel to another plane, the stresses on the latter plane at the same point must be parallel to the first plane.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "The Rankine’s lateral pressure ratio is given by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(K=\\frac{\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\) ",
            "b) \\(K=\\frac{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\) ",
            "c) \\(K=\\frac{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\) ",
            "d) \\(K=cosβ\\frac{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Rankine’s theory, the additional assumption of the vertical and lateral stresses are conjugate is made. Being conjugate, both the vertical and the lateral pressures have the same angle of obliquity β.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "For backfill with sloping surface, the coefficient of active earth pressure is given by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(K_a=\\frac{\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\) ",
            "b) \\(K_a=\\frac{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\) ",
            "c) \\(K_a=\\frac{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\) ",
            "d) \\(K_a=cosβ\\frac{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ratio K is the conjugate ratio or the Rankine’s lateral pressure ratio, which is given by,\n\\(K=\\frac{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}, \\) \nwhere, β=surcharge angle\nφ=angle of internal friction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "When the surcharge angle reduces to zero, the coefficient of active earth pressure is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ka=1",
            "b) \\(K_a=\\frac{1-sinφ}{1+sinφ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(K_a=\\frac{1+sinφ}{1-sinφ}\\) ",
            "d) Ka=0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The vertical pressure in case of backfill with surcharge,\nσ= γzcosβ,\nTherefore, from the assumption of stresses being conjugate,\n\\(K_a=cosβ\\frac{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}. \\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "The principal stress relationship on a failure plane is given by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ1=σ3 tan2 α",
            "b) σ1=2c tan⁡α-σ3 tan2 α",
            "c) σ1=2c tan⁡α+σ3",
            "d) σ1=2c tan⁡α+σ3 tan2 α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The principal stress relationship on a failure plane is given by,\nσ1=2c tan⁡α+σ3 tan2 α,\nWhere, σ1=major principal stress\nσ3=minor principal stress\n\\(α=(45°+\\frac{φ}{2}), \\) \nφ=angle of internal friction\nc=cohesion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "The Belli equation of lateral pressure of cohesive soil is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pa=γzcot2 α-2c cot⁡α",
            "b) pa=γzcot2 α+2c cot⁡α",
            "c) pa=-2c cot⁡α",
            "d) pa=γzcot2 α/2c cot⁡α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the principal stress relationship on a failure plane is given by,\nσ1=2c tan⁡α+σ3 tan2 α,\n σ1=γz and σ3=pa,\n∴ γz=2c tan⁡α+pa tan2 α\n∴ pa=γzcot2 α-2c cot⁡α.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "The Belli equation at the ground surface is given by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pa=γzcot2 α-2c cot⁡α",
            "b) pa=γzcot2 α+2c cot⁡α",
            "c) pa=-2c cot⁡α",
            "d) pa=γzcot2 α/2c cot⁡α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since the Belli equation of lateral pressure of cohesive soil is given by,\npa=γzcot2 α-2c cot⁡α,\nat the ground surface, z=0,\n∴ pa=-2c cot⁡α.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "The tension at the top level of retaining wall reduces to zero at a depth ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(z_0=\\frac{q-2c cot⁡α}{γ} \\) ",
            "b) \\(z_0=\\frac{2c tan⁡α}{γ} \\) ",
            "c) \\(z_0=\\frac{2 cot⁡α}{γ} \\) ",
            "d) \\(z_0=\\frac{cot⁡α}{γ} \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the Belli equation of lateral pressure of cohesive soil is given by,\npa=γzcot2 α-2c cot⁡α,\nWhen  pa=0,\n∴ \\(z_0=\\frac{2c tan⁡α}{γ} \\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "The depth at which the tension is zero for cohesive soils with retaining wall in terms Ka is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(z_0=\\frac{2cK_a}{γ} \\) ",
            "b) \\(z_0=\\frac{2c}{γ} \\frac{1}{√K_a } \\) ",
            "c) \\(z_0=\\frac{2cK_a}{γ} \\) ",
            "d) \\(z_0=\\frac{2c}{γ}(\\frac{1}{K_a}) \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tension at the top level of retaining wall reduces to zero at a depth,\n\\(z_0=\\frac{2c tan⁡α}{γ}, \\) \nSince, \\(K_a=\\frac{1}{tan^2 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2})}, \\) \n∴ \\(z_0=\\frac{2c}{γ} \\frac{1}{√K_a}. \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "The effect of cohesion in the soil is to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reduce pressure intensity",
            "b) increase pressure intensity by 3",
            "c) double the pressure intensity",
            "d) increase pressure intensity by 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cohesion is the component of shear strength of a rock or soil that is independent of inter-particle friction. Due to the cohesion, the particles of the soil are in close contact by which they distribute the load evenly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "For a cohesive soil, the pressure intensity is reduced by a factor of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2c cot⁡α",
            "b) 2c tan⁡α",
            "c) 2c sin⁡α",
            "d) 2c cos⁡α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The equation of pressure intensity due to cohesion is given by,\npa=γzcot2 α-2c cot⁡α.\nThus, the effect of cohesion is to reduce the pressure intensity by a factor of ” 2c cot⁡α”.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "The total net pressure for a cohesive soil is given by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pa=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) Ka γH2 cot2 α-2c cot⁡α",
            "b) Pa=γH2-2c cot⁡α",
            "c) Pa=Ka γH2-2c cot⁡α",
            "d) Pa=Ka H2-2c cot⁡α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total net pressure is given by,\n\\(P_a=\\int_0^H p_a.dz = \\int_0^H(γzcot^2 α-2c cot⁡α).dz\\) \n∴ Pa=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) Ka γH2 cot2 α-2c cot⁡α.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "If a tension crack is developed at the top of wall to a depth Zo in cohesive soils, then the total net pressure is zero for a depth of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2Zo",
            "b) 3Zo",
            "c) 4Zo",
            "d) 5Zo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A negative pressure develops and because of it, a crack is developed in the soil upto a depth Zo. The sum of negative pressure and the positive pressure will be compensated at a depth of 2Zo. Hence, the total net pressure is zero for a depth of 2Zo.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "The critical height for an unsupported vertical cut in cohesive soil is given by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(H_c=\\frac{q-2c cot⁡α}{γ} \\) ",
            "b) \\(H_c=\\frac{4c tan⁡α}{γ} \\) ",
            "c) \\(H_c=\\frac{4 cot⁡α}{γ} \\) ",
            "d) \\(H_c=\\frac{cot⁡α}{γ} \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a tension crack is developed at the top of wall to a depth Zo in cohesive soils, then the total net pressure is zero for a depth of 2Zo. This means that the soil will be able to stand with a vertical face up to a depth of 2Zo.\n∴ The critical height  \\(H_c=\\frac{4c tan⁡α}{γ}. \\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "For an inclined back and surcharge, if P1, is horizontal pressure and W is weight of soil wedge, then the total pressure is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) P=P1+W",
            "b) \\(P=\\sqrt{P_1^2+W^2}\\) ",
            "c) P=(P1+W)2",
            "d) P=P1-W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For an inclined back and surcharge, if P1, is horizontal pressure and W is weight of soil wedge, then the total pressure is given by,\n\\(P=\\sqrt{P_1^2+W^2},\\) \nThis is due to the fact that the total pressure P is the resultant of the horizontal pressure and the weight of the wedge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "When the top tension portion of the wall in cohesive soil is neglected, the total lateral thrust is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pa=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)Ka γH2 cot2 α-2c cot⁡α",
            "b) Pa=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)Ka γH2 cot2 α-2c cot⁡α+\\(\\frac{2c^2}{γ}\\) ",
            "c) Pa=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)Ka γH2 cot2 α-2c cot⁡α-\\(\\frac{2c^2}{γ}\\) ",
            "d) Pa=Ka H2-2c cot⁡α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the negative tensile portion is neglected, the total lateral thrust is given by,\n\\(P_a=\\int_{z_0}^H p_a.dz = \\int_{z_0}^H(γzcot^2 α-2c cot⁡α).dz\\) \nsubstituting for  \\(z_0=\\frac{2c tan⁡α}{γ},\\) \n∴ Pa=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)Ka γH2 cot2 α-2c cot⁡α+\\(\\frac{2c^2}{γ}.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "If the cohesive backfill carries a surcharge of q per unit area, then the lateral pressure is increased by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ka q",
            "b) q",
            "c) Ka",
            "d) Ka/q"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the surcharge is the additional load, when the backfill is horizontal and carries a surcharge q, then the vertical pressure increment will be by q. Due to this, the lateral pressure will increase by Ka q.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "The lateral pressure for cohesive backfill with surcharge q is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pa=γzcot2 α-2c cot⁡α+qcot2 α",
            "b) pa=γzcot2 α+2c cot⁡α+cot2α",
            "c) pa=-2c cot⁡α-cot2 α",
            "d) pa=γzcot2 α/2c cot⁡α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the cohesive backfill carries a surcharge of q per unit area, then the lateral pressure is increased by Ka q. Since, Ka=cot2α,\n∴ pa=γzcot2 α-2c cot⁡α+qcot2 α.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "For a cohesive backfill with surcharge q, when at depth z0, pa=0, then the depth z0 is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(z_0=\\frac{q-2c cot⁡α}{γ} \\) ",
            "b) \\(z_0=\\frac{2c tan⁡α}{γ}-\\frac{q}{γ} \\) ",
            "c) \\(z_0=\\frac{2 cot⁡α}{γ}+\\frac{q}{γ} \\) ",
            "d) \\(z_0=\\frac{cot⁡α}{γ}-\\frac{q}{γ} \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the lateral pressure for cohesive backfill with surcharge q is given by,\npa=γzcot2 α-2c cot⁡α+qcot2 α,\nwhen pa=0,\n∴ \\(z=z_0=\\frac{2c tan⁡α}{γ}-\\frac{q}{γ}. \\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "In case of passive state of plastic state of equilibrium, the lateral pressure is the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) minor principal stress",
            "b) major principal stress",
            "c) major principal plane",
            "d) minor principal plane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of passive state of plastic state of equilibrium, the lateral pressure is the major principal stress while the vertical pressure is the minor principal stress.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "The passive earth pressure intensity is given by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) pp=γz cot2 α",
            "b) pp=γz tan2 α",
            "c) pp=γz sin2 α",
            "d) pp=γz cos2 α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of passive state of plastic state of equilibrium,\npp=σh=σ1, and σ3=σv=γz,\n∴ for non-cohesive soils, σ1=σ3 tan2 α,\n∴ pp=γz tan2 α.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "The passive earth pressure intensity in terms of coefficient of passive earth pressure is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pp=Kp γH",
            "b) pp=γH",
            "c) pp=Kp H",
            "d) pp=Kp γ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The passive earth pressure intensity is given by,\npp=γz tan2 α,\nsince, Kp= tan2 α,\n∴ pp=Kp γH.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "The ratio between coefficients of passive and active earth pressure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cot2 \\((45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "b) cos2 \\((45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "c) tan4 \\((45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) ",
            "d) sin2 \\((45°+\\frac{φ}{2})\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The coefficient of passive earth pressure is Kp= tan2 α and that of the coefficient of active earth pressure is \\(K_a=\\frac{1}{tan^2(45°+\\frac{φ}{2})},\\) \n∴ \\(\\frac{K_p}{K_a}\\) = tan2 α* tan2 α\n\\(\\frac{K_p}{K_a} =tan^4 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}).\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "For angle of internal friction of 250, the ratio of coefficient of passive and active earth pressure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nangle of internal friction φ=250,\n∴ \\(\\frac{K_p}{K_a} =tan^4 (45°+\\frac{φ}{2}) = tan^4 (45°+\\frac{25}{2}),\\) \nKp/Ka =6.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "The relation between Kp and Ka  is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kp=Ka",
            "b) Kp=1+Ka",
            "c) Kp=1-Ka",
            "d) Kp=1/Ka"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The coefficient of passive earth pressure is,\nKp= tan2 α,\nthe coefficient of active earth pressure is,\n\\(K_a=\\frac{1}{tan^2(45°+\\frac{φ}{2})},\\) \n∴ Kp=1/Ka.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "For a cohesion less soil, the total passive pressure Pp at a depth H is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pp=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) Kp γH2",
            "b) Pp=γH2",
            "c) Pp=Kp γH2",
            "d) Pp=Kp H2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pressure intensity pp is given by,\npp=Kp γz,\nThe total earth pressure P0 at rest per unit length is,\nPp=\\(\\int_0^H\\)Kp γz.dz\n∴ Pp=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) Kp γH2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "For a cohesion less soil with surcharge Q, the passive pressure intensity is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pp=Kp γz+Kp q",
            "b) pp=Kp γz-Kp q",
            "c) pp=Kp γz*Kp q",
            "d) pp=Kp γz/Kp q"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the backfill is horizontal and carries a surcharge q, then the vertical pressure increment will be by q. Due to this, the lateral pressure will increase by Kp q. Hence, lateral pressure at the depth of wall H is pp=Kp γz+Kp q.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "For a surcharge angle β, the passive earth pressure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(p_p=γz \\frac{\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\) ",
            "b) \\(p_p=γz \\frac{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(p_p=γz \\frac{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(p_p=γzcosβ \\frac{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the backfill is having its top surface inclined to the horizontal at an angle β, then the passive earth pressure is given by,\n\\(p_p=γzcosβ \\frac{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}},\\) \nwhere, β= surcharge angle\nγ=unit weight of the soil\nφ= angle of internal friction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "For a surcharge angle β the coefficient of passive earth pressure is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kp=\\(\\frac{\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}} \\) ",
            "b) Kp=\\(cosβ \\frac{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}\\) ",
            "c) Kp=\\(\\frac{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}\\) ",
            "d) Kp=\\(cosβ \\frac{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The vertical pressure in case of backfill with surcharge,\nσ= γzcosβ,\nTherefore, from the assumption of stresses being conjugate,\nKp=\\(cosβ \\frac{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "When the surcharge angle β is reduced to zero, then the coefficient of passive earth pressure is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) \\(\\frac{1-sinφ}{1+sinφ} \\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{1+sinφ}{1-sinφ} \\) ",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For backfill with sloping surface, the coefficient of passive earth pressure is given by,\nKp=\\(cosβ \\frac{cosβ+\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}}{cosβ-\\sqrt{cos^2 β-cos^2 φ}},\\) \nWhen the surcharge angle reduces to zero, β=0,\nsubstituting this in the equation, we get,\nKa=\\(\\frac{1+sinφ}{1-sinφ}.\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "In case of cohesive backfill, the passive pressure intensity is given by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) pp=γz tan2 α-2c tan⁡α",
            "b) pp=γz tan2 α+2c tan⁡α",
            "c) pp=-2c tan⁡α",
            "d) pp=γz tan2 α/2c tan⁡α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the principal stress relationship on a failure plane is given by,\nσ1=2c tan⁡α+σ3 tan2 α,\n σ1=pp and σ3=γz,\n∴ pp=2c tan⁡α+γztan2 α\n∴ pp=γz tan2 α+2c tan⁡α.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "In case of cohesive backfill, the total passive pressure is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pp=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) Kp γH2+2cH tanα",
            "b) Pp=γH2+2c tanα",
            "c) Pp=Kp γH2-2c tanα",
            "d) Pp=Kp H2-2c tanα"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pressure intensity pp for a cohesive soil is given by,\npp=Kp γz+2c tanα,\nThe total earth pressure P0 at rest per unit length is,\nPp=\\(\\int_0^H\\)Kp γz+2c tanα.dz\n∴ Pp=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) Kp γH2+2cH tanα.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "With respect to the flow value, the total passive pressure for cohesive backfill is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pp=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) Nφ γH2+2cH √Nφ",
            "b) Pp=γH2+2c √Nφ",
            "c) Pp=Nφ γH2-2c √Nφ",
            "d) Pp=Nφ H2-2c √Nφ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flow value is given by,\nNφ= tan2 α=Kp,\nsince the the total passive pressure for cohesive backfill is given by,\nPp=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) Kp γH2+2cH tanα,\ntherefore on substituting the value of Nφ in the equation, we get,\nPp=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) Nφ γH2+2cH √Nφ.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "For an angle of internal friction of 300, the values of coefficients of active and passive earth pressures are given by a _____ and ____ respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{1}{3}\\), 3",
            "b) \\(\\frac{1}{5}\\), 5",
            "c) 3, \\(\\frac{1}{3}\\) ",
            "d) 5, \\(\\frac{1}{5}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Given,\nΦ=300,\nTherefore \\(K_a=\\frac{1-sin⁡φ}{1+sin⁡φ}=\\frac{1+sin⁡30}{1+sin⁡30}=\\frac{1}{3}\\) \n\\(K_p=\\frac{1}{K_a} =3.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Compute the active pressure intensity when the backfill has unit weight of 18 KN/m3 and height of wall is 6 m. The angle of internal friction is 30°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 KN/m2",
            "b) 36 KN/m3",
            "c) 87 KN/m2",
            "d) 27 KN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given,\nγ= 18 kN/m3\nH=6m\nΦ=30°\nTherefore  \\(K_a=\\frac{1-sin⁡φ}{1+sin⁡φ}=\\frac{1+sin⁡30}{1+sin⁡30}=\\frac{1}{3}\\) \nPp= KaγH = \\((\\frac{1}{3})\\)×18×6 = 36 kN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Compute the passive pressure intensity when the backfill has unit weight of Ka=\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\) and height of wall is 6 m. The coefficient of active earth pressure Ka=\\(\\frac{1}{3}.\\) ",
        "Options": [
            "a) 176 KN/m3",
            "b) 154 KN/m3",
            "c) 324 KN/m3",
            "d) 476 KN/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nγ= 18 kN/m3\nH=6m\nKa=\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\) \nKp=\\(\\frac{1}{K_a}=3 \\) \nTherefore Pp = KpγH =3×18×6=324 KN/m3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "The water table is at the ground   level and backfill has saturated unit weight as 22KN/m3. The height of wall is 6m and Ka=\\(\\frac{1}{3}.\\) Find the pressure intensity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45.22 KN/m2",
            "b) 18.45 KN/m2",
            "c) 83.24 KN/m2",
            "d) 67.83 KN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nγsat=22 KN/m3\nγ’=γsat-γω=22-9.81= 12.19\nKa = \\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)\nH = 6m\nWe know that, Pa=Ka γ’ H+ γω H\nPa = \\((\\frac{1}{3})\\)×12.19×6 + 9.81×6 = 83.24 kN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "The water table is at the ground   level and backfill has saturated unit weight as 22KN/m3. The height of wall is 6m and Ka=1/3. Find the pressure intensity, if free water stands on other face of wall.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45.82 KN/m2",
            "b) 78.28 KN/m2",
            "c) 24.38 KN/m2",
            "d) 56.27 KN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nFree water stands on both sides of wall, so the effect of water pressure is not considered\nPa=Ka γ’ H=\\((\\frac{1}{3})\\) ×12.19×6\nPa= 24.38 kN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Compute the active pressure intensity when the backfill has unit weight of 18 KN/m3 and height of wall is 6 m. The angle of internal friction is 300. The backfill has surcharge of 36 KN/m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 KN/m2",
            "b) 75 KN/m2",
            "c) 48 KN/m2",
            "d) 78 KN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nq = 36 KN/m2\nPa=Ka γH+ Ka q= \\((\\frac{1}{3})\\) ×18×6 + \\((\\frac{1}{3})\\) ×36\nPa= 48 KN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Compute the passive pressure intensity when the backfill has unit weight of 18 KN/m3 and height of wall is 6 m. The angle of internal friction is 300. The backfill has surcharge of 36 KN/m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 378 KN/m2",
            "b) 432 KN/m2",
            "c) 875 KN/m2",
            "d) 972 KN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given,\nq = 36 KN/m2\nPa=Ka γH+ Ka q= 3×18×6 + 3×36\nPp= 432 kN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": " If the backfill has unit weight of 18 KN/m2 and surcharge of 36 KN/m2, then find the equivalent height of surcharge.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4m",
            "b) 56m",
            "c) 2m",
            "d) 86m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nq= 36 kN/m3\nγ= 18 kN/m3\n\\(Z_e = \\frac{q}{γ} = \\frac{36}{18}=2m.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": " If a backfill has unit weight of 12 KN/m3 and the equivalent height of surcharge as 3m, then find the surcharge.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12 KN/m2",
            "b) 25 KN/m2",
            "c) 36 KN/m2",
            "d) 75 KN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nγ = 12 kN/m3\nZe = 3m\nTherefore q = Ze γ= 3×12= 36 kN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "When the height of retaining wall is 6m, then the distance of point of application of the resultant pressure from the base is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10m",
            "b) 2m",
            "c) 3m",
            "d) 7m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given,\nH = 6m\nThe point of application is \\(\\frac{H}{3}= \\frac{6}{3} = 2m.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Find the critical height of an unsupported vertical cut in cohesive soil of C= 10KN/m2 and γ=20KN/m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5m",
            "b) 2m",
            "c) 8m",
            "d) 9m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given,\nc= 10 KN/m2\nγ=20KN/m2\nHc= 4c/γ  tan⁡∝\nSince φ=0, tan⁡∝=1\n\\(H_c= 4×\\frac{10}{20}×1= 2m.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "For a soil deposit, C=20 KN/m2 and is found be to a purely cohesive soil. It has a critical height of an unsupported vertical cut as 4m. Find the unit weight of soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13 kN/m3",
            "b) 20 kN/m3",
            "c) 56 kN/m3",
            "d) 77 kN/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given,\nC= 20 kN/m2\nΦ=0,this makes tan⁡∝=1\nHc= 4 m\nTherefore \\(H_c=\\frac{4c}{γ}  tan⁡∝\\) \nγ = 4×\\(\\frac{20}{4}×1\\)= 20 kN/m3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "For a saturated clay of 20KN/m3 and cu=24 kN/m2, find the height of tension cracks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.4 m",
            "b) 6.9 m",
            "c) 3.5 m",
            "d) 1.7 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Given,\ncu=24 KN/m2\nγsat=20 KN/m3\nTherefore height of the tension cracks is,\n\\(Z_0=\\frac{2c_u}{γ_{sat}} = \\frac{2×24}{20}=2.4 m. \\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "For a saturated clay cu=18KN/m2, find the height of tension cracks is 7m. Find the saturated unit weight.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 43 KN/m3",
            "b) 98 KN/m3",
            "c) 18 KN/m3",
            "d) 86 KN/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\ncu=18 KN/m2\nzo= 2m\nwe know that, \\(Z_0=\\frac{2c_u}{γ_{sat}} \\) \n\\(γ_{sat}=\\frac{2c_u}{Z_0}=\\frac{2×18}{2}=18\\)KN/m3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "For an angle of internal friction of 30°, find the flow value Nφ",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given,\nφ=30°\nTherefore flow value \\(N_φ=tan^2⁡ (45+\\frac{φ}{2})\\) \n\\(N_φ=tan^2⁡(45+\\frac{30}{2})\\) \nNφ=3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "The wedge theory of earth pressure is based on the concept of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Active earth pressure",
            "b) Sliding wedge",
            "c) Wall friction",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The wedge theory of earth pressure is based on the concept of a sliding wedge which is torn off from the rest of the backfill on a movement of the wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a basic assumption of the wedge theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The slip surface is plane",
            "b) The backfill is dry",
            "c) The backfill is homogeneous",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Based on the assumptions of the wedge theory:\ni. The backfill is dry, cohesion less, homogeneous, isotropic, and elastically undeformable.\nii. The slip surface is a plane which passes through the heel of the wall\niii. The sliding wedge itself acts as a rigid body."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "The force acting on a wedge of soil are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frictional force",
            "b) Weight of the wedge and Active thrust",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to wedge theory, the forces acting on a wedge of soil are its weight W, the reaction R along the plane of sliding and the active thrust against the retaining wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "The active lateral pressure of intact saturated clays is calculated by assuming __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) φ=0 and φc=0",
            "b) φ=90",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The active lateral pressure of intact saturated clays for temporary works or immediately after construction of a retaining wall is calculated by assuming φ=φc=0."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "The forces acting on the trial wedge which is used for finding Rankine’s active earth pressure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight W of the wedge",
            "b) Resultant force",
            "c) Resultant reaction between wedge and sol",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The three forces acting on a trial wedge are: i) the resultant force that exist between the free body and the wall ii) the weight W of the wedge iii) the resultant reaction between the wedges and the rest of the soil along the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "The Rankine’s active earth pressure can also be found out by method of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trial wedges",
            "b) Graphical method",
            "c) Sliding wedge",
            "d) Theoretical calculation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Rankine’s active earth pressure (assuming the wall to be smooth) can be found out by method of trial wedges."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Based on the assumptions of the wedge theory, pressure distribution is assumed to be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Planar",
            "b) Hydrostatic",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) Distributed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The assumption is based on that, the total pressure distribution is hydrostatic,i.e., triangular"
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "In Coulomb’s wedge theory, the angle λ is referred as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angle of wall friction",
            "b) Surcharge angle",
            "c) Critical slip angle",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In wedge theory, the angle between the slip plane and the ground is called the critical angle λ."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "The φ-line in wedge theory can also be called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surcharge line",
            "b) Natural slope line and Repose line",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The φ-line shows a plane inclined at an angle φ to the horizontal at which the soil is expected to stay in the absence of any lateral support. The line therefore is called the natural slope line or repose line."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "In coulomb’s wedge theory, the criterion for maximum active pressure is present at ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slip-plane",
            "b) Repose line",
            "c) Surcharge line",
            "d) Ground line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1971, Professor Rebhann presented that the criterion for maximum active pressure is present at the slip–plane of the assumed triangle."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Culmann’s solution can be conveniently used for _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Various type of surcharge loads",
            "b) Ground surface of any shape",
            "c) Backfill of different densities",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Culmann’s graphical method can be conveniently used for the ground surface of any shape, for various types of surcharge loads, and for a layered backfill of different densities."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Culmann’s solution is based on ___________ theory.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coulomb’s",
            "b) Rebhann’s",
            "c) Mohr",
            "d) Rankine’s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1886, Culmann gave a graphical solution to evaluate the active earth pressure by coulomb’s theory."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Which of the following effect of line load can be taken into account by Culmann’s graphical method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Railway track and Long wall of a building",
            "b) Road alignment",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Culmann’s graphical method can be used to take into account the effect of line of load, such as railway track or a long wall of a building etc., running parallel to the retaining wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Rebhann’s graphical method can be used for the location of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slip plane and Total active earth pressure",
            "b) Passive earth pressure",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1871, Rebhann presented a graphical method for the location of the slip plane and the total active earth pressure according to Coulomb’s wedge theory."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Earth pressure for retaining walls, of less than 6m are obtained by _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analytical method",
            "b) Graphical method",
            "c) Considering approximate value",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In practice, earth pressures for retaining walls of less than 6m height are obtained from graphs or tables."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "All available graphs and tables, used for finding earth pressure is based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rankine’s theory",
            "b) Coulomb’s theory",
            "c) Culmann’s theory",
            "d) Rebhann’s graphical method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Almost all graphs and tables available in the literature which are used for finding earth pressure are based on Rankine’s theory."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the criteria, for design of gravity dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The wall must be safe against sliding",
            "b) The wall must be safe against overturning",
            "c) The wall must be thinner in section",
            "d) No tension should be developed in the wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the gravity wall resists the earth lateral pressure by its weight, therefore it should be thicker in section."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "For the design of gravity dam, the minimum value of F(factor of safety) against sliding should be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.0",
            "b) 1.5",
            "c) 0.5",
            "d) 4.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the equation F = RV.μ / Rh\nThe minimum value of factor of safety is found out to be 1.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Positive projecting conduits are of ___________ types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Positive projecting conduits are of four types: i) complete ditch conditions ii) complete projection conduits iii) incomplete ditch conduit iv) incomplete projection conduits."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "The settlement ratio for a negative projecting conduit is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Always positive",
            "b) Always negative",
            "c) Negative in some cases",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The settlement ratio for negative projecting conduits is always negative since the settlement of the critical plane is more than the settlement of the natural ground."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "The magnitude and direction of relative movements between the interior and exterior prisms of the conduits are dependent upon the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Settlement ratio",
            "b) Projection ratio",
            "c) Settlement of conduits",
            "d) Compressive strain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnitude and direction of relative movements are dependent upon the settlement ration rsd defined by the equation:\nrsd = (sm + sg) – (sf + dc)/sm."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Critical plane in conduit is located at ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tangential to the top of the conduit",
            "b) Tangential to the bottom of the conduit",
            "c) Centre of the conduit",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The critical plane is a horizontal plane, located tangential to the top of the conduit."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "If the critical plane settles more than the top of the conduit, the settlement ratio is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Negative",
            "c) Positive",
            "d) Unity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the critical plane settles more than the top of the conduit i.e. if (sm + sg) is more than (sf + dc) the settlement ratio is positive."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Both the projection condition and the ditch conditions of a positive projecting conduit may be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complete",
            "b) Incomplete",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Depending upon the position of plane of equal settlement, both the projection conditions and the ditch conditions of a positive projecting conduit may be complete or incomplete."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "If the plane of settlement does not fall within the embankment, then such a condition is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complete ditch condition and Complete project condition",
            "b) Incomplete ditch condition",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the embankment is not of sufficient height, the plane of equal settlement does not fall within the embankment (i.e., He > H); such a condition is called complete projection condition or complete ditch condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "The sign used for complete projection is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) +",
            "b) –",
            "c) No sign is used",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since + is used for positive settlement ratio, (+) sign is used for complete projection and (–) sign used for complete ditch condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "The recommended value of settlement ratio for embankment, to use in design is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) +0.5",
            "b) +1.0",
            "c) – 0.3",
            "d) – 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of rsd for embankment of rigid conduit type is +1.0, which can be used for any ordinary rock hard, hard or unyielding soil as foundation soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "The load on a negative conduit is given by the equation __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wc = Cn γ Bd",
            "b) Wc = Cn γ Bd2",
            "c) Wc = γ Bd",
            "d) Wc = Cn Bd2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The load on the conduit is given as WC = Cn γ Bd2, where Cn= load coefficient for negative projecting conduit."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "A soil engineers usually encounter problems of stress distribution in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vicinity of vertical shafts and Vicinity of inclined shafts",
            "b) Vicinity of horizontal shafts",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A soil engineer is commonly encountered with the problem of stress distribution in the vicinity of vertical or inclined shafts in an elastic semi-infinite solid with a horizontal or inclined surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "The problem of stress distribution in the vicinity of shafts was first solved by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Westergaard",
            "b) Terzaghi",
            "c) Darcy",
            "d) Biot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1940, Westergaard solved the problem of stress distribution by using the theory of plasticity using a suitable stress function."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "The method given by Biot for solving the problem of stress distribution was based on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Theory of elasticity",
            "b) Method of superposition",
            "c) Westerngaard method",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The method suggested by Biot was based on the method of superposition as proposed by Terzaghi in 1943."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "The stress component which acts on any point in the surrounding material before the excavation of the shaft can be resolved into __________ parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: i) Stresses due to the weight of material and ii) stress due to pressure exerted by the equivalent liquid are the two stress component that acts at any point on the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Stress due to equivalent fluid pressure can be found out using __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biot method",
            "b) Theory of elasticity",
            "c) Lame’s formula",
            "d) Method of superposition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stress due to equivalent fluid pressure can be found out by using the Lame’s formula for the state of stress in thick walled cylinder subjected to internal pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "After excavating the shaft, the shearing stresses along the walls of the shaft will be equal to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Normal stress",
            "c) Circumferential stress",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: After the shaft has been excavated the shearing stresses along the walls of the shaft are equal to zero and the radial normal stresses are also equal to zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "When the high value of σϴ in the vicinity of the walls of a shaft exceeds the compressive strength it results in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plastic flow of soil",
            "b) Non uniform stress distribution",
            "c) Increase fluid pressure",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The high value of σϴ in the vicinity of walls of a shaft may exceed the compressive strength of the soil, resulting in a plastic flow of the soil which continues until a state of plastic equilibrium."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "The stress component at any point, after the excavation of the shaft, will be equal to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) σR = (σZ)1-(σZ)2",
            "b) σZ = (σZ)1-(σZ)2",
            "c) σϴ = (σϴ)1-(σϴ)2",
            "d) σR = (σR)1-(σR)2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The stress component at any point, after the excavation of the shaft will be equal to the difference between the initial stresses i.e., σZ = (σZ) 1-(σZ) 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Underground conduits are commonly used for, which of the following purpose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sewers",
            "b) Gas lines",
            "c) Culverts",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Underground conduits are commonly used as sewers, drains, and water mains, gas lines, culverts etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "A ditch conduits can be installed in a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shallow bedding",
            "b) Shallow ditch",
            "c) Narrow ditch",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A ditch conduit is the one which is installed in a narrow ditch, excavated in undistributed soil below ground level, which is then covered with earth backfill."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Underground conduits can be classified into ___________ types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Based on the type of installations, conduits can be classified into 3 types:\ni) Ditch conduits\nii) Projecting conduits\niii) Special conduits."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Ditch conduits are more commonly used in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sewers",
            "b) High way",
            "c) Railway culverts",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since narrow ditch can be installed in a narrow ditch below ground level, it is more commonly used as sewers, water mains etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "The problem of computing the stress in the vicinity of a cylindrical tunnel was solved by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Terzaghi",
            "b) Mindlin",
            "c) Biot",
            "d) Rankine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The problem of computing the stress in the vicinity of a cylindrical tunnel corresponding to the state of elastic equilibrium has been solved more rigorously by Mindlin (1939), using the values of K0."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "The transfer of pressure from a yielding part of soil mass to the less yielding part is defined by the term __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arching",
            "b) Projecting conduits",
            "c) Stress transfer",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Arching is defined as the phenomenon of the transfer of pressure from a yielding part of the soil mass to an adjoining less yielding or restrained part of the mass."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Which of the following conduit is installed in shallow bedding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ditch conduits",
            "b) Positive projecting conduits",
            "c) Special conduits",
            "d) Negative projecting conduits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A passive projecting conduit is the one which is installed in shallow bedding, with its top projecting above the natural ground and which is then covered with an embankment."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Which of the following values of K0 is used to compute the stress in the vicinity of a cylindrical tunnel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) K0 = 1",
            "b) K0 = μ / 1-μ",
            "c) K0 = 0",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The problem of computing the stress in the vicinity of a cylindrical tunnel corresponding to the state of elastic equilibrium has been solved by Mindlin using the following valued of K0:\ni) K0 = 1 ii) K0 = μ / 1-μ iii) K0 = 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Terzaghi’s experiment show that the value of K (empirical constant) varies from about ________ above the Centre of strip.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unity",
            "b) Zero",
            "c) Less than unity",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Terzaghi’s experiments show that the value of K varies from about unity (i.e., 1) immediately above the Centre of strip to a maximum of 1.5 at an approximate height above the strip."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following conduits are commonly used in highway or railway culverts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive/Negative projecting conduits",
            "b) Negative projecting conduits",
            "c) Ditch conduits",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Negative and positive projective conduits are used in highway or railway culverts as both can be covered with an embankment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Earth embankments or slopes are commonly required for which of the following purpose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Railways",
            "b) Earth dams",
            "c) Road ways",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Earth embankments are commonly required for railways, roadways, earth dams, levees and river training works."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "The failure of slopes may take place due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forces between the soil particle and High water content",
            "b) Action of gravitational force",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The failure of slopes takes place mainly due to the action of a gravitational force which tends to pull the upper portions of the soil mass downwards to a nearly more level surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Slopes is classified into ____________ types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slopes may be of two types: i) infinite slopes and ii) finite slopes."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of slopes extending to infinity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inclined face of Earth dams",
            "b) Embankments",
            "c) Cuts",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Slopes extending to infinity do not exist in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Analysis of stability of slopes is used for determining ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shearing strength and Stressed internal surface",
            "b) Properties of the soil",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An analysis of stability of slopes consist of determining the most severely stressed internal surface and the magnitude of the shearing stress to which it is subjected and determining the shearing stress along the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "If the soil properties for all identical depths below the surface are constant, it is a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Finite slope",
            "b) Infinite slope",
            "c) Planar failure surface",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a slope represents the boundary surface of a semi-infinite soil mass, and the soil properties for all identical depths below the surface are constant, it is called an infinite slope."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "A long natural slope of cohesion-less soil is inclined at 12° to the horizontal. What will be the factor of safety of the slope if φ = 30°?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.6",
            "b) 2.7",
            "c) 0.13",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given φ = 30° and i = 12°\nFormula, F = tan φ /tan i\nF = tan 30° / tan 12°\nF = 2.72."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Factor of safety with respect to height is given by ______________ equation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) FC = HC / H",
            "b) FC = C / Cm",
            "c) FC = τf / τ",
            "d) FC = τC / τ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the factor of safety FC with respect to cohesion, also represent the factor of safety with respect to height\nFC = C / Cm = HC / H\nWhere, Cm is the mobilized cohesion at a depth H."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "In the limiting case of stability, the angle of slope is referred to as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angle of deviation",
            "b) Angle of repose",
            "c) Angle of unstable slope",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the limiting case of stability, the angle of slope is known as the angle of repose φ."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "The factor of safety against safety is given by ________ equation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) F = HC / H",
            "b) F = τf / τ and F = tan φ / tan i",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The factor of safety against sliding is given by equation:\nF = τf /τ = tan φ / tan i."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "A basic type of failure at a finite slope may occur due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slope failure and Base failure",
            "b) Toe failure",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two basic types of failure of a finite slope may occur: (i) slope failure (ii) base failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "If the failure occurs along a surface of sliding that intersect the slope at its toe, the slide is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base failure",
            "b) Slope failure",
            "c) Face failure",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the failure occurs along a sliding that intersects the slopes at or above its toe, the slide is known as slope failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "The types of slip surface or failure surfaces are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The types of failure surface are: i) Planar failure surface ii) circular failure surface iii) Non-circular failure surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "The ratio of total depth to depth H is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth factor",
            "b) Slope depth",
            "c) Depth failure",
            "d) Base failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ratio of the total depth (H + D) to depth H is called the depth factor Df."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "The depth factor Df for toe failure is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Df > 1",
            "b) Df < 1",
            "c) Df = 1",
            "d) Df = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For toe failure, Df = 1; for base failure, Df > 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Planar surface commonly occur in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Embankment with specific plane of weakness",
            "b) All embankments",
            "c) Soil deposit",
            "d) Foundation of infinite depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Planar failure surface may commonly occur in a soil deposit or embankment with a specific plane of weakness."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "The stability of a finite slope can be investigated by which of the following method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bishop’s method",
            "b) Swedish circle method",
            "c) Friction circle method",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The stability of a finite slope can be investigated by the following methods:\ni) Culmann’s method of planar failure surface\nii) The Swedish circle method\niii) Friction circle method\niv) Bishop’s method."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "According to Bennet, non-circular slip surface may arise in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non homogeneous dam",
            "b) Embankment dams",
            "c) Homogeneous dam",
            "d) Soil deposit with a specific plane of weakness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Bennet (1951), non-circular or composite slip surface may arise in homogeneous dam have foundation of infinite depth, rigid boundary planes of maximum and presence of stronger or weaker layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "The rupture mass sliding down a surface in a definite pattern resembles __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curve",
            "b) Cycloid",
            "c) Ellipse",
            "d) Circle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Collin observed that the rupture mass slide down a sliding surface, in a definite pattern resembling that of a cycloid."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "In stability computation, the curve representing the real surface of sliding is usually replaced by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arc of circle and Logarithmic failure",
            "b) Cycloid",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Failure of finite slopes occurs along a curved surface. In stability computation, the curve is represented by an arc of a circle or logarithmic scale."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Rectangular plot method has been suggested by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Culmann",
            "b) Bishop",
            "c) Singh",
            "d) Terzaghi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A simplified rectangular plot method for finding the stability of slopes was suggested by Singh in 1962."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "The slip circle having the minimum factor of safety is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Critical circle",
            "b) Failure slip circle",
            "c) Critical slip circle",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A number of trial critical slip circle are chosen against sliding and factor of safety of each is computed. The circle having the minimum factor of safety is the critical slip circle."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "In Swedish circle method ___________ analysis cases are considered.",
        "Options": [
            "a) φC = 0",
            "b) C – φ and φu = 0",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Swedish slip circle method two cases are considered: i) analysis of purely cohesive soil (φu = 0) and ii) analysis of a soil possessing both cohesion and friction (C-φ analysis)."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "When does the critical condition of d/s slope, occur in reservoir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reservoir is full",
            "b) Pore pressure is high",
            "c) Steady seepage does not occur",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Critical condition of d/s slope occurs when the reservoir is full and percolation is at its maximum rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "In the rectangular plot method if there are n-slices, the total number of ordinates will be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) n – 1",
            "b) n",
            "c) n – 2",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the rectangular plot method if there are n-slices, the total number of ordinates will be (n-1), the ordinates at the end of the last strip being zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Stability of slopes of an earth dam is tested under, which of the following condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stability of downstream slope during steady seepage and Stability of upstream slope during a sudden drawdown",
            "b) Stability of upstream slope during sudden seepage",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stability of slopes of an earth dam is tested under the following conditions:\ni) Stability of downstream slope during steady seepage\nii) Stability of upstream slope during a sudden drawdown\niii) Stability of upstream and downstream slopes during and immediately after construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "When a dam is built of impervious compressible soil, water is entrapped in the pore space due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excessive pore pressure",
            "b) Volume change in the soil mass",
            "c) Low shear strength of soil",
            "d) Unstable soil mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a dam is built of relatively impervious compressible soil, excess pore pressure develops in the air and water entrapped in the pore pressure. This is because the soil mass undergoes a change in the soil due to compaction of the dam construction and also due to a down weight."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "The area of U-diagram in finding stability of D/S slope during steady seepage, can be measured by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Planimeter and Rectangular plot method",
            "b) Fellinious method",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The area of U-diagram can be measured with the help of a planimeter, or else the rectangular plot method can be utilized."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "The magnitude and distribution of pore water pressure on a slip surface can be calculated from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure net",
            "b) Test data",
            "c) Graphical method",
            "d) Rectangular plot method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnitude and distribution of pore water pressure on a likely slip surface is estimated from pressure net which are developed from the flow net. "
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "The pore water pressure at any point on the slip surface is represented by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Piezometric head",
            "b) Pore pressure",
            "c) Factor of safety",
            "d) Failure plane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pore water pressure at any point is represented by the piezometric head hw at that point."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "The estimation of construction pore pressure can be made with the help of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Swedish circle method",
            "b) Bishop’s method",
            "c) Hilf’s equation",
            "d) Rectangular plot method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The estimation of the construction pore pressure is made with the help of Hilf’s equation:\nu = pa Δ / (va + hc γw – Δ)."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "In Hilf’s equation ‘u = pa Δ / (va + hc γw – Δ)’, hc refers to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Induced pore pressure",
            "b) Henry’s constant",
            "c) Volume of pore water",
            "d) Volume of air voids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Hilf’s equation hc refers to Henry’s constant of solubility of air in water by volume (= 0.02 at 68°F)."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "In the friction circle method, it is assumed that the resultant reaction is ___________ to the friction circle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perpendicular",
            "b) Tangential",
            "c) Parallel",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the friction circle method, it is assumed that the resultant reaction is tangential in the friction circle, since the error involved in this assumption is of small magnitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "The friction circle may be also referred as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) φ-circle",
            "b) Plane circle",
            "c) Cohesion circle",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The friction circle having radius r sin φ is also called as φ-circle."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "A circle is considered to be a critical slip circle, if it has ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum factor of safety",
            "b) Minimum factor of safety",
            "c) Maximum radius",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The circle giving minimum factor of safety Fc is considered as a critical slip circle."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "The factor of safety with respect to cohesion is given by the equation ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) FC = HC / H",
            "b) FC = C / Cm",
            "c) FC = τf / τ",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The factor of safety Fc with respect to cohesive strength, based on the assumption that the frictional strength has been fully mobilized, is given by\nFC = C / Cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "The friction circle method assumes the failure surface as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cycloid",
            "b) Curve",
            "c) Arc of circle",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Similar to Culmann’s method, the friction circle method also assumes the failure surface as the arc of circle."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "The forces acting on a sliding wedge are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight of the wedge",
            "b) Total frictional force",
            "c) Total cohesive resistance",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The forces acting on a sliding wedge are i) the weight of the wedge ii) the total frictional resistance or resultant, and iii) total cohesive resistance along the slip circle."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "The factor of safety Fc with respect to cohesive strength is based on the assumption that ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frictional force is fully mobilized",
            "b) Frictional force is zero",
            "c) Total cohesive resistance is zero",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The factor of safety with respect to cohesive strength, based on the assumption that frictional force has been fully mobilized, and the equation is given by FC = C / Cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "The factor K, in the radius of the friction circle(Kr sin φ) depends on ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radius of the frictional circle",
            "b) Frictional resistances offered",
            "c) Cohesive resistance",
            "d) Central angle of the slip arc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the frictional circle radius of Kr sin φ, the factor K depends on the central angle δ of the slip arc."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "The total cohesion force which resists the slipping along the slip arc at critical equilibrium is proportional to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesion and Height of the slope",
            "b) Taylor’s stability number",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total cohesive force c L̑, which resist the slipping along the slip arc at critical equilibrium, is proportional to the cohesion c and the height H of the slope."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "The Taylor’s stability number is based on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Height of the slope and Pore pressure",
            "b) Factor of safety",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Taylor’s stability number is based on the factor of safety Fc with respect to cohesion assuming that the frictional resistance assuming that frictional force has been fully mobilized."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "The factor of safety with respect to friction is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unity",
            "b) Zero",
            "c) Greater than one",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The friction of safety Fφ with respect to friction is a unity which means that the frictional force has been fully mobilized."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "According to Taylor, the force causing instability in the sliding wedge is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesive resistance and Weight of the wedge",
            "b) Total frictional resistance",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The force causing instability is the weight of the wedge which is equal to unit weight γ."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Taylor’s stability number is represented by the term __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SC",
            "b) Sn",
            "c) Cm",
            "d) HC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Taylor’s stability is represented as Sn."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Which of the following quantity is called as Taylor’s stability number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) c/Fc γ H",
            "b) c/γ H",
            "c) cm/ Fc γ",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If Fc is the factor of safety with respect to cohesion,\nWe have c × H / Fc × γH2\n= c / Fc γ H = Sn\nThe dimensional quantity c / Fc γ H is called as Taylor’s stability number Sn."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "For purely frictional soil, the Taylor’s stability number is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unity",
            "b) Zero",
            "c) >1",
            "d) <1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For purely frictional soil (c = 0), the stability number is zero, and Taylor’s stability curves do not apply."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "The stability of a slope for a pure frictional soil, depends upon __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slope angle",
            "b) Factor of safety",
            "c) Frictional resistance",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stability of slope for a frictional soil entirely depends upon the slope angle i, irrespective of height of the slope."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "What will be the factor of safety with respect to cohesion of a clay slope laid at 1 in 2 to a height of 10 m, if the angle of internal friction φ=10° ; c=25 k N/m2 and γ = 19 k N/m3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.34",
            "b) 2.06",
            "c) 1.02",
            "d) 20.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: i = tan-1(1/2) = 26.5°\nFor i = 26.5° and φ = 10°, Sn = 0.064\nBut, Sn = c / Fc γ H\nTherefore, Fc = c / Sn γ H\nFc = 25 / (0.064×19×10) = 2.06. "
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "A slope is to be constructed at an inclination of 30° with the horizontal. What will be the safe height of the slope at factor of safety of 1.5? The soil has the properties: c = 15 k N/m2, φ=22.5° and γ = 19 k N/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11.5",
            "b) 20.5",
            "c) 12",
            "d) 18.64"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mobilized frictional angle φm is given by\nφm = φ/F = 22.5/1.5 = 15°\nFor, i = 30° and φm = 15°, Sn =0.046\nNow H = c/F γ Sn = 15/(0.0046×1.5×19) = 11.5 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "When the slope is fully submerged, which of the following has to be used for finding stability number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Submerged density",
            "b) Shearing resistance",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the slope is fully submerged, the submerged density γ’, and weighted frictional angle φw should be used for computing stability number Sn."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "The gross pressure intensity (q) of a structure is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total pressure at base of the footing",
            "b) Excess pressure after the construction of the structure",
            "c) Minimum pressure intensity at the base",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gross pressure intensity q is the total pressure at the base of the footing due to the weight of the superstructure."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "The ultimate bearing capacity and the net ultimate capacity are connected by the relation ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) qf = qnf +/- σ̅ and qf = qf – σ̅",
            "b) qf = qnf – σ̅",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ultimate bearing capacity qf and the net ultimate capacity are connected by the following relation:\nqf = qnf + σ̅ (or) qf = qf – σ̅\nwhere σ̅ is the effective surcharge at the base level of the foundation."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "The net safe bearing capacity is defined by which of the following equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) qns=qnf / F",
            "b) qns = qnf + σ̅",
            "c) qns = qf – σ̅",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The net safe bearing capacity is the net ultimate bearing capacity divided by a factor of safety F i.e., qns = qnf/F."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "The safe bearing capacity can also be referred as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Net safe bearing capacity",
            "b) Ultimate bearing capacity",
            "c) Safe bearing pressure",
            "d) Net soil pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sometimes, the safe bearing capacity is also referred to as the ultimate bearing capacity qf divided by a factor of safety F."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Rankine considered the first soil element (element 1) at ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base of the structure",
            "b) Below the foundation",
            "c) Edge of the footing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rankine considered the equilibrium of two soil elements, The first one immediately below the foundation (element 1)."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "The bearing capacity of cohesion-less soil at the ground surface is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unity",
            "b) Less than one",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) Greater than one"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Rankine’s equation bearing capacity of cohesion less soil is zero at the ground surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "When a state of equilibrium is reached under the footing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Load on footing increase",
            "b) Load on footing decreases",
            "c) Safe bearing capacity of the soil is reached",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the load on footing increases, and approaches a value qf, a state of plastic equilibrium is reached under the footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Rankine considered the equilibrium of second soil element at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base of the structure",
            "b) Below the foundation",
            "c) Edge of the footing",
            "d) Top of the foundation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rankine considered the equilibrium of the other soil element (element 2) beyond the edge of the footing, but adjacent to element 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "During the state of shear failure, which of the following principal stress relationship exist?",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ1 = σ tan α + 2c tan α",
            "b) σ1 = σ3 tan2 α + 2c tan α",
            "c) σ1 = 2c tan α",
            "d) σ1 = σ3 tan α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the state of shear failure (plastic equilibrium), the following principal stress relationship exists σ1 = σ3 tan2 α + 2c tan α\nfor cohesion-less soil,σ1 = σ3 tan2 α."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "The symbol σ̅, represent which of the following term?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultimate bearing capacity",
            "b) Effective surcharge",
            "c) Gross pressure intensity",
            "d) Bearing capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: σ̅ represents the effective surcharge at the base level of the foundation, assuming total unit weight for the portion of the soil above the water table and submerged unit weight for the portion below the water table."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "When a footing fails due to insufficient bearing capacity, distinct failure patterns are developed depending upon _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Failure mechanism",
            "b) Plastic equilibrium",
            "c) Shear strength",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Experimental investigations have indicated that when a footing fails due to insufficient bearing capacity, distinct failure patterns are developed, depending upon the type of failure mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Vesic observed _____________ types of bearing capacity failures.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In 1963, Vesic observed three types of bearing capacity failures:\ni) General shear failure\nii) Local shear failure\niii) Punching shear failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "In general shear failure, continuous failure is developed between ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ground surface and footing",
            "b) Edge of the footing and ground surface",
            "c) Foundation and the ground surface",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of general shear failure, continuous failure surface develops between the edges of the footing and the ground surface. "
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of general shear failure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Failure is accompanied by compressibility of soil",
            "b) Failure is sudden",
            "c) Bulging of shearing mass of soil",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A typical characteristic of general shear failure is\na) Failure is sudden with pronounced peak resistance\nb) There is considerable bulging of sheared mass of soil adjacent to the footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "In local shear failure, the development of plastic equilibrium is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Full",
            "b) Partial",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In local shear failure there is only partial development of state of plastic equilibrium and there is a significant compression of the soil under the footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Punching shear may occur in loose sand with density less than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 %",
            "b) 50 %",
            "c) 35 %",
            "d) 20 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Punching shear may occur in relatively loose sand with relative density less than 35 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Local shear failure is associated with soils having _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High compressibility",
            "b) High pore pressure",
            "c) Low porosity",
            "d) Low compressibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Local shear failure occurs in soil having high compressibility and in sands having relative density lying between 35 and 70 percent."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the characteristics of a local shear failure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Failure is defined by large settlements",
            "b) Failure surface do not reach the ground surface",
            "c) Failure is sudden",
            "d) Ultimate bearing capacity is not well defined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In local shear stress there is no tilting of footing and therefore the failure is not sudden."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "In local shear failure, the failure surface do not reach the ground surface because ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compression of soil under the footing",
            "b) Ultimate bearing capacity is not well defined",
            "c) Failure is defined by large settlements",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In local shear failure there is a significant compression of the soil under the footing and only partial development of state of plastic equilibrium. Due to this reason, the failure surface does not reach the ground."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "State of equilibrium is fully developed in which of the following bearing capacity failures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Local shear failure",
            "b) General shear failure",
            "c) Punching shear failure",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In general shear failure, when the pressure approaches the value of qf, the state of equilibrium is reached initially in the soil around the soil and gradually spreads, ultimately the state of plastic equilibrium is fully developed throughout the soil above the failure surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "An analysis of the condition of complete bearing capacity failure is usually termed as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) General shear failure",
            "b) Terzaghi’s analysis",
            "c) Bearing failure",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An analysis of the condition of complete bearing capacity failure is termed as a general shear failure, can be made by assuming that the soil behaves like an ideally plastic failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "The concept of analysis of bearing capacity failure was first developed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Terzaghi",
            "b) Meyerhof",
            "c) Prandtl",
            "d) Darcy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The concept of failure analysis was first developed by Prandtl, and later extended by Terzaghi, Meyerhof and others."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "For purely cohesive soil, the bearing capacity is given by which of the following equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) qf = 5.7 c + σ̅",
            "b) qf = c + σ̅",
            "c) qf = 5.7 c",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For purely cohesive soil the bearing capacity is\nqf = c Nc + σ̅ Nq = 5.7 c + σ̅\nWhere σ̅ = γ D if the water table is below the base of the footing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "The parameters Nc, Nq, Nγ in the equations of bearing capacity failure are known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant head",
            "b) Bearing capacity factors",
            "c) Effective pressure",
            "d) Load intensity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The parameters Nc, Nq, Nγ are the dimensionless numbers, known as bearing capacity factors depending only on the angle of shearing resistance of the soil. "
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "For purely cohesive soil, local shear failure may be assumed to occur when the soil is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Medium to soft",
            "b) Soft to medium",
            "c) Hard",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For purely cohesive soil, local shear failure may be assumed to occur when the soil is soft to medium, with an unconfined compressive strength qu ≤ 100 kN/m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a limitation, of assumption in Terzaghi’s analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) φ changes when the soil is compressed and strip footing has a rough base",
            "b) Soil is homogeneous",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the soil compress, φ changes; slight downward movement of footing may not develop fully the plastic planes."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Which of the following are original Terzaghi values for Nγ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 34° and 48°",
            "b) 60°",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The values of Nγ for φ of 34° and 48° are the original Terzaghi values which were used by Bowles to back compute Kpγ."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "According to the assumptions in Terzaghi’s analysis, the soil is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homogeneous and Isotropic",
            "b) Non Homogeneous",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Terzaghi’s analysis the soil is homogeneous and isotropic and its shear strength is represented by Coulomb’s equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "The Terzaghi’s general bearing capacity equation is represented as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) qf = 5.7 c + σ̅",
            "b) qf = c Nc + σ̅. Nq + 0.5γBNγ",
            "c) qf = c Nc + σ̅. Nq",
            "d) qf = c Nc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: “qf = c Nc + σ̅. Nq + 0.5γBNγ” is known as Terzaghi’s general bearing capacity equation for a continuous footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Local shear failure generally occurs in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dense sand",
            "b) Non-cohesive soil",
            "c) Loose sand",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Local shear failure generally occurs in loose sand while general shear failure occurs in dense sand."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "The curve for Nq and Nγ for the transition state from φ = 28° and φ = 38° was given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peck",
            "b) Hanson",
            "c) Thorn burn",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Peck, Hansen, and Thorn burn gave curves for Nq and Nγ for the transition state from φ = 28° and φ = 38°, in which they assumed general shear failure when φ > 28°."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Terzaghi’s bearing capacity equation is not applicable for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth effect and Inclination factor",
            "b) Narrow slope",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Terzaghi assumed the value of angle ψ = φ, which is not true. Since footings are normally rough, ψ has been found close to 45° + φ/2 than to φ, thus Terzaghi’s bearing capacity equations do not have provision for including depth effects, inclination factors, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "For purely cohesive soil, Nc has a maximum value of ___________ for square footing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 7.5",
            "c) 9",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Skempton’s observation, for purely cohesive soil (φ = 0) Nc has a maximum value of 9 for square or circular footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "The Brinch Hansen shape factor can be applied to ___________ for the case of rectangular footing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Skempton value of Nc",
            "b) Terzaghi’s equation",
            "c) Meyerhof’s equation",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Brinch Hansen shape factor can be applied to the Nc values from Skempton for the rectangular footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Hansen considered the bearing capacity as a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tri axial problem",
            "b) Base factor",
            "c) Plane-strain problem",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Brinch Hansen considered the bearing capacity as a plane-strain problem. If φ is found by tri axial test, its corresponding value for the plane strain case can be computed."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Bowel suggested that the increase in φ in plane-strain case can be computed only for φ greater than ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 25",
            "c) 60",
            "d) 90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bowel suggests that the increase of φ in the equation φ plain strain = 1.1 φ tri axial can be computed only for φ greater than 25°."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Skempton observed that the factor Nc increases with the ratio ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) D/B",
            "b) B/D",
            "c) H/Hc",
            "d) c/cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Based partly on theory and partly on the laboratory test, Skempton observed that the factor Nc increases with the ratio D/B."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "When D=0, the value of Nc for strip footing will be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.20",
            "b) 2.5",
            "c) 5.14",
            "d) 7.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to Skempton recommendation, the value of Nc = 5.14 for strip footing when D=0 and Nc = 6.20 for square or circular footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Which of the following value can be taken [Nc] surface for surface footing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 2.1",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Value of [Nc] surface may be roughly taken as 5 for surface strip footing and as 6 for square or circular footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "The term ‘i’ in Hansen equation represents ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth factor",
            "b) Shape factor",
            "c) Ground factor",
            "d) Inclination factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Brinch Hansen’s equation, i represent the inclination factor to account for both horizontal and vertical components of foundation loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "When the water table is above the base of the footing, the submerged weight ‘γ’ can be used to compute __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective pressure and Surcharge",
            "b) Pore pressure",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the water table is above the base of the footing, the submerged weight ‘γ’ should be used for the soil below the water table for computing the effective pressure or the surcharge."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an essential difference between Vesic’s and Hansen’s procedure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Different values of Nγ and Variation on some of Hansen inclination",
            "b) Different value of Nq and Nc",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The essential difference in Vesic’s and Hansen’s procedure are i) use of slightly different values of Ny and ii) a variation on some of Hansen’s inclination, base and ground factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "The equation Nc = (Nq – 1) cot φ, have been adopted by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Terzaghi and Peck",
            "b) Hansen",
            "c) Vesic",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The two equations Nc = (Nq – 1) cot φ and Nq = tan2 (45 + φ/2) ex tan φ have been adopted by i) Terzaghi and Peck ii) Hansen iii) Vesic iv) Meyerhof and Bureau of Indian standards."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Which of the following N factors has the widest range of values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nc",
            "b) Nq",
            "c) Nγ",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Nγ factor has the widest suggested range of any value of N factors. A literature value reveals that for φ = 40°, 38≤ Nγ≤192."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Which of the following term does not contribute to q f?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nc",
            "b) Nγ",
            "c) Nq",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Nγ term does not contribute significantly to qf so that almost any reasonable value can be used. Bureau of Indian standards (BIS) recommends using the value of Nγ, given by Vesic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Meyerhof’s extended the analysis of plastic equilibrium of a surface footing to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shallow foundation and Deep foundation",
            "b) Inclined foundation",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: M Meyerhof’s extended the analysis of plastic equilibrium of a surface footing to Shallow and Deep foundation according to both Terzaghi and Meyerhof analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "In the Bowl’s method for finding the effect of water table, which of the following factor is used for soil in the wedge zone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water reduction factor",
            "b) Effective unit weight",
            "c) Overburden pressure",
            "d) Average unit weight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the third method (Bowles, 1988), no water reduction factor is used, but effective unit weight (γe) is used for the soil in the wedge zone. "
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Which of the following equation has been recommended by Indian standard for finding reduction factor in water table?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R w = 0.5 (1 + z w2/B)",
            "b) R w = (1 + z w2/B)",
            "c) R w = c Nc + σ̅. Nq + 0.5γBNγ",
            "d) R w = z w2 / B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rw =Rw2 = 5 (1 + z w2 / B) has been recommended by Indian standard at a depth D1 below the ground level."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "The value of Nc and Nq are same for, which of the following methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meyerhof",
            "b) Hansen",
            "c) Vesic",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of Nc and Nq are same for Meyerhof, Hansen and Vesic method, while subscripts for Nγ identify the author, i.e. N γ(H) = valued by Hansen etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "The factor N γ(M) identifies which of the following author?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vesic",
            "b) Meyerhof",
            "c) Hansen",
            "d) Terzaghi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The factor N γ(M) gives values by Meyerhof, as it has the subscript (M) in it."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "IS code recommends a bearing capacity equation, which is similar to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vesic",
            "b) Meyerhof and Brinch Hansen",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS code (IS : 6403-1981) recommends a bearing capacity equation which is similar in nature to those given by Meyerhof and Brinch Hasen."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "According to IS code, there are __________ types of failures of soil support beneath the foundation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The code recognizes, depending upon the deformation associated with the load and the extent of development of failure surface, three types of failures of soil support beneath the foundations which are general, local and punching shear failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "The bearing capacity equation for strip footing as given IS standard, can be modified on the basis of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape of the footing",
            "b) Type of soil",
            "c) Bearing capacity",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bearing equations applicable for strip footing shall be modified to take into account, the shape of the footings, and inclination of loading, depth of embankment and effect of water table."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "The value of shape factor S c, S q and S γ for circular base is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.3, 1.2, 0.8",
            "b) 1.3, 1.2, 0.6",
            "c) 1.0, 1.0, 1.0",
            "d) 1.2, 1.0 and 1.3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to IS (6403 -1981) standards, the shape factor for circle base is 1.3, 1.2 and 0.6 for S c, S q and S γ respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "The depth factor can be applied to footing only when ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Back filling is compacted",
            "b) Shape factors are not used",
            "c) The base of the footing is circular",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The depth factor can be applied only the back filling is done with proper compaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "The effect of the water table is taken into account for bearing capacity in the form of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth factor",
            "b) Inclination factor",
            "c) Correction factor",
            "d) Shape factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The effect of the water table is taken into account in the form of correction factor W’ applied to the wedge term."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "If the water table is located at the depth D, then the value of W’ is taken as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0.5",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the water table is located at the depth D or likely to rise at the base of the footing or above, then the value of W’ shall be taken as 0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "For cohesion less soils, having c=0 Indian standard code recommends that the bearing capacity can be calculated based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relative density",
            "b) Standard penetration resistance value",
            "c) Static cone penetration",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For cohesionless soils (c=0), Indian standard code recommends that the bearing capacity can be calculated i) based on relative density or ii) based on standard penetration resistance value, and iii) based on static cone penetration test."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "The standard penetration resistance is determined at a number of selected points at intervals of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80 cm",
            "b) 75 cm",
            "c) 100 cm",
            "d) 10 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Indian standard recommends that the standard penetration resistance is determined at a number of selected points at intervals of 75 cm in the vertical direction or change of strata if it takes place earlier."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "The ultimate bearing capacity for cohesive soil can be calculated using the equation __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) q nf = c Nc.sc",
            "b) q nf = c Nc.sc.dc.ic",
            "c) q nf = Nc.sc.dc",
            "d) q nf = sc.dc.ic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The net ultimate bearing capacity after construction on fairly saturated homogeneous cohesive soils can be calculated from the expression:\nq nf = c Nc.sc.dc.ic\nwhere, Nc = 5.14."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "The value of c in the equation, q nf = c Nc.sc.dc.ic used for finding bearing capacity of cohesive soil can be calculated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unconfined compression strength test",
            "b) Static cone penetration test",
            "c) Relative density test",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of cohesion c can be obtained from unconfined compression strength test. Alternatively, cohesion c may be determined by static cone resistance q c using the empirical relation between q c and c."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "The plate load test is essentially a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laboratory test",
            "b) Field test",
            "c) Graphical method analysis",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plate load test is a field test to determine the ultimate bearing capacity of the soil, and the probable settlement under a given loading."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "The plate load test consists in loading a rigid plate at the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base of the footing",
            "b) Bottom of the construction",
            "c) Foundation level",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The plate load test essentially consists in loading a rigid plate at the foundation level, and determining the corresponding to each load increment."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "The bearing plate used in plate load test is in the shape of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square",
            "b) Rectangular and Circular",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bearing plate is either circular or square, made of mild steel of not less than 25 mm in thickness."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "The size of bearing plate, which used in plate load test varies from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300 to 750 mm",
            "b) 25 to 100 mm",
            "c) 100 to 300 mm",
            "d) 25 to 300 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bearing plate used varies in size from 300 to 750 mm with a chequered or grooved bottom. "
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "The loading to the test plate is applied with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluid tube",
            "b) Hydraulic jack",
            "c) Sand bags",
            "d) Cross-joists"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The loading to the test plate may be applied with the help of a hydraulic jack. The reaction of the hydraulic jack may be borne by either any of gravity loading methodor reaction truss method."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "For clayey and silty soils, which of the following bearing plate can be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square plate and Concrete block",
            "b) Circular plate",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For clayey and silty soils and for loose medium dense sandy soils with N < 15, a 450 mm square plate or concrete block shall be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "The settlement of the plate in a load test is measured with the help of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sensitive dial gauges",
            "b) Test plate",
            "c) Measuring unit",
            "d) Datum bar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The settlement of the plate is measured with the help of sensitive dial gauges. For square plate, two dial gauges are used. The dial gauges are mounted on independently supported datum bar."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "According to Indian standard method, the loading of the plate should be borne with either by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity loading platform and Reaction truss",
            "b) Concrete blocks",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Indian standards (IS: 1888: 1982) recommend that the loading of the plate should invariably be borne either by gravity loading platform or by the reaction truss."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "A seating pressure of ___________ is applied on the plate before starting the load test.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70 g/cm2",
            "b) 30 g/cm2",
            "c) 50 g/cm2",
            "d) 100 g/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A minimum seating pressure of 70 g/cm2 (0.7 t/m2), shall be applied and removed before starting the load test."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of loading method is popular now-a-days?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity loading platform",
            "b) Reaction truss",
            "c) Concrete blocks",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The use of reaction truss is more popular now-a-days since this is simple, quick and less clumsy."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "The value of factor of safety used, for finding safe bearing capacity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In order to determine the safe bearing capacity, it would be normally sufficient to use a factor of safety of 2 or 2.5 on the ultimate bearing capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Which of the following pose a limitation to plate load test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effect of size of foundation and Test on cohesive soil",
            "b) Load increment",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A limitation of plate load test is\ni) Effect of the size of foundation. For clayey soils the ultimate pressure for a large foundation is the same as that of the test plate. But in dense sandy soils, the bearing capacity increases, with the size of the foundation\nii) Plate load test is essentially a short duration test, and hence the test does not give the ultimate settlement, particularly in the case of cohesive soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "For a c-φ soil, Housel suggested which of the following expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q = A .q + P .s",
            "b) Q = A .q",
            "c) q f = M + N( BF/B p )",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1929, Housel suggested the following expression for a c-φ soil:\nQ = A .q + P .s\nWhere, Q = total load on bearing area;\nP = perimeter of footing;\nS = perimeter shear;\nA = contact area of footing or plate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "For clay soil the value of n can be taken as _____________ in the absence of test data.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0. 4 to 0.5",
            "b) 0.20 to 0.25",
            "c) 0.003 to 0.05",
            "d) 0.08 to 0.10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of index n can be determined by carrying out two or more plate load tests on different size plate. In absence of test data, the following values of n can be adopted:\nDense sand : 0.4 to 0.5\nLoose sand : 0.20 to 0.25\nClay : 0.003 to 0.05\nSand clay : 0.08 to 0.10."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "The two commonly used penetration tests are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard penetration test",
            "b) Cone penetration test",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Indian standard, the two commonly used penetration tests are static cone penetration test and standard penetration test."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "The values derived from penetration tests can be used for finding ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth of hard stratum and Strength of soil",
            "b) Soil saturation",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The penetration test are useful for general exploration of erratic soil profiles, for finding depth to bed rock or hard stratum, and to have an approximation indication of the strength and other properties of soils."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "The observed value of N in static cone penetration test is corrected by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overburden and Dilatancy /submergence",
            "b) Effective pressure",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The N-value for cohesion less soil shall be corrected for overburden and the values N0 obtained after overburden correction is corrected further for dilatancy. "
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Correction for increasing effective overburden pressure have been proposed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gibbs and Holtz",
            "b) Peck",
            "c) Thornburn",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a constant density index, the N value increase with increasing effective overburden pressure for which correction have been proposed by Gibbs and Holtz, peck, Thornburn, Whitman and others."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "The split tube used in static cone penetration test, is commonly known as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Split spoon sampler",
            "b) Split tube sampler",
            "c) Tube sampler",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The split tube sampler, used in a test for standard penetration is commonly known as split spoon sampler resting on the bottom of the bore hole which is allowed to sink under its own weight."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "The total blow required for the second and third 15 cm of penetration in standard penetration test is taken as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seating drive",
            "b) Penetration resistance",
            "c) Overburden pressure",
            "d) Dilatancy/submergence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In standard penetration test, the first 15 cm of drive may be considered to be a seating drive. The total blows required for the second and third 15 cm of penetration is termed as the penetration resistance N."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "The expression for C n as given by Lio and Whitman is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) C n = √(σ’)",
            "b) C n = √(100/σ’)",
            "c) C n = 0.77log10(2000/σ’)",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In 1986, Lio and Whitman gave the following expression for\nNormalizing factor C n:\nC n = √ (100/σ’)."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "The cone test is useful in determining the bearing capacity of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesion less soil and Fine sand",
            "b) Clay soil",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cone test is considered very useful in determining the bearing capacity of pits in cohesion less soils, particularly in fine sands of varying density."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "The cone resistance qc, for sandy silt type of soil is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.5",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For silts, sandy silts, slightly cohesive silt sand mixture type of soil, the cone resistance q c is 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "The analytical methods used for finding bearing capacity of footing is based on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear failure",
            "b) Effective pressure",
            "c) Overburden pressure",
            "d) Size of the footing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The analytical methods for the determination of bearing capacity of footings are based essentially on shear failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "The effect of settlement on structure depends upon its ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnitude and Uniformity",
            "b) Size",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effect of settlement upon the structure depends on its magnitude, the length of the time over which it takes place, its magnitude and the nature of the structure itself."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "The vertical downward movement of the base of the structure is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penetration resistance",
            "b) Settlement",
            "c) Effective pressure",
            "d) Shear failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The vertical downward movement of the base of the structure is called settlement and its effect depends upon its magnitude and uniformity etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "The allowable pressure, that should be selected for a maximum settlement is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 mm",
            "b) 25 mm",
            "c) 30 mm",
            "d) 10 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is suggested that allowable pressure should be selected such that maximum settlement of any individual foundation is 25 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "The maximum allowable settlement for warehouses are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 38",
            "c) 50",
            "d) Less than 0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The allowable maximum settlement for warehouse type of structure is 50 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "According to National building code of India, the differential settlement can be kept within limits by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Suitably designing the foundation",
            "b) Decreasing the total settlements",
            "c) Increasing the allowable pressure.",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to National Building Code of India (SP: 7-1970) the differential settlement shall be kept within limits to which the super-structure can accommodate itself without the distortion, by suitably designing the foundation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "For simple spread footing on clayey soil, the differential settlement should not exceed __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/ 400",
            "b) 1/300",
            "c) 1/100",
            "d) 1/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For simple spread footing on clayey soils, the allowable pressure should be such that the differential settlement does not exceed 1/300."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "According to Polish and Tokar brick masonry will crack, when the unit elongation amounts to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.005",
            "c) 1.0",
            "d) 0.05"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Polishin and Tokar (1957), brick masonry will crack due to differential settlement when the unit elongation amount to 0.005."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "The recommendation of American code, for a differential settlement depends upon __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of structure and Pattern of loading",
            "b) Settlement depth",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The recommendation of American code are based upon that if the maximum total settlement is kept within a reasonable limit, the differential settlement will only be a fraction depending upon the type of structure and pattern of loading."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "The rate of differential settlement is defined by which of the following equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H/L",
            "b) L/H",
            "c) H/H c",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate of settlement is defined as the slope or the relative settlement between two points divided by the horizontal distance.\nRate of differential settlement = L/H."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "Foundations can be broadly classified under __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shallow foundation and Deep foundation",
            "b) Pile foundation",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Foundations may be broadly classified under two heads: shallow foundations and deep foundations."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "A foundation is said to be shallow if its depth is ________ than its width.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal to and Less than",
            "b) Greater than",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to Terzaghi, a foundation is shallow if its depth is equal to or less than its width. In the case of deep foundations, the depth is equal to or greater than the width."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "which of the following, is a type of shallow footing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spread footing",
            "b) Pile foundation",
            "c) Pier foundation",
            "d) Well foundation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The shallow foundations are of the following types: spread footing (or simple footing), strap footing, combined footing, and mat footing or raft footing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Which of the below is the most commonly used shallow foundation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strap footing",
            "b) Spread footing",
            "c) Combined footing",
            "d) Raft footing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In spread footing, load is transmitted through an isolated column or wall to the subsoil; hence this is most common type of foundation."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "The pressure intensity beneath the footing depends upon ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rigidity of the footing",
            "b) Soil type",
            "c) Condition of soil",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Both from observations as well as the analytical studies from elasticity, it is known that the pressure distribution beneath footing is not uniform and it depends on the rigidity of footing, the soil type, and the condition of the soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Once the pressure distribution is known ___________ in the reinforced concrete footing can be calculated.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bending moment and Shear force",
            "b) Bearing pressure",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Knowing the pressure distribution is known, the bending moment and shear force can be calculated, and the thickness of the structural member of the member can be calculated using properties of reinforced concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "In conventional design, allowable bearing capacity should be taken smaller than which of the following value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Safe bearing capacity and Allowable bearing pressure",
            "b) The pressure intensities beneath the footing",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In conventional design, the allowable bearing capacity should be taken as the smaller of the following two values: i) the safe bearing capacity based on ultimate capacity, and ii) the allowable bearing pressure on tolerable settlement."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "In cohesive soil, the pressure distribution beneath the footing is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Non linear",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a footing rests on cohesive soil, the edge stresses may be very large, but the pressure distribution may be considered to be linear."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "When do strap footings are used in foundation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To transfer load of an isolated column",
            "b) Distance between the columns are long",
            "c) Two column loads are unequal",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A strap footing may be used where the distance between the columns is so great that the combined trapezoidal footing becomes quite narrow, with a high bending moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "When two column loads are unequal, which of the possible footing can be provided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strap footing",
            "b) Raft footing",
            "c) Trapezoidal combined footing",
            "d) Mat footing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the two columns load are unequal, with the outer column carrying a heavier load, and when there is space limitation beyond the outer column, a trapezoidal footing is provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "The total settlement of a footing in clay is considered to be consisting of ___________ components.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Three",
            "c) Two",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Skempton and Bjerrum, the total settlement of a footing in clay may be considered to consist of three components\nS = Si + Sc + Ss."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "The component Sc, used in the total settlement of clay refers to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total settlement",
            "b) Consolidation settlement",
            "c) Immediate plastic settlement",
            "d) Settlement due to secondary consolidation of clay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The three components used in total settlement of clay are given below:\nSc = consolidation settlement\nSi = immediate elastic settlement\nSs = settlement due to secondary consolidation of clay."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "The immediate settlement can be computed from the expression, based on ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Theory of plasticity",
            "b) Theory of elasticity",
            "c) Terzaghi’s analysis",
            "d) Pressure distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The immediate settlement is the elastic settlement and can be computed from the following expression based on the theory of elasticity,\nSi = q B (1-μ2/E s) I w. "
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "The influence factor for rigid square footing is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.88",
            "b) 0.82",
            "c) 1.06",
            "d) 1.70"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As suggested by BIS Code IS: 8009 Part 1, 1976 the value of influence factor Iw for rigid footing is 0.82."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "The equation for computing immediate settlement “Si = μ0μ1 q B ( 1-μ2/Es )” was proposed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Janbu",
            "b) Bjerrum",
            "c) Kjaernsli",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In 1966, Janbu, Bjerrum, and Kjaernsli have proposed the following equation for computing the immediate settlement:\nSi = μ0μ1 q B (1-μ2/Es)."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "The value of Es used in the immediate settlement equation, can be found out using _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triaxial test",
            "b) Compression test",
            "c) Direct shear test",
            "d) Rankine’s theory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The modulus of elasticity Es used in the equation Si = μ0μ1 q B (1-μ2/Es) is computed from triaxial test data, where\nEs = (σ1-σ3)/ΔL / L."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "A combined footing may be rectangular in shape if both the columns carry ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unequal loads",
            "b) Equal loads",
            "c) No load",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The combined footing may be rectangular in shape if both the columns carry equal loads, or may be trapezoidal if they carry unequal loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "The influence factor Iw for rigid rectangular footing with L/B = 1.5 is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.88",
            "b) 0.82",
            "c) 1.70",
            "d) 1.06"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Iw = influence factor = 1.06 for rigid rectangular footing, with L/B = 1.5 = 1.70 for rigid rectangular footing, with L/B = 5."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "The design of rigid rectangular combined footing consist in determining the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure distribution",
            "b) Location of center of gravity of column",
            "c) Shear force",
            "d) Safe bearing pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design of rigid rectangular footing consists in determining the location of center of gravity of the column loads and using length and width dimension such that centroid of footing and the center of gravity of columns loads coincide."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "If the independent spread footing of two columns are connected by a beam, it is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Combined footing",
            "b) Trapezoidal combined footing",
            "c) Strap footing",
            "d) Raft footing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In strap footing, two independent columns are supported by as trap or beam at the bottom. "
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition is true regarding the transfer of load from strap to soil, used in strap footing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transfer load to soil",
            "b) Does not transfer load to soil",
            "c) Partially transfer to load",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The strap used does not remain in contact with soil, and thus does not transfer any pressure to the soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "When the allowable soil is low or the building loads are heavy, the footing used is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Raft footing",
            "b) Strap footing",
            "c) Trapezoidal combined footing",
            "d) Rectangular combined footing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the allowable soil pressure is low, or the building loads are heavy, the use of spread footings would cover more than one-half of the area and it may prove more economical to use mat or raft foundation."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "If the resultant of the soil pressure coincides with the resultant of the loads, the soil is pressure is assumed to be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-uniformly",
            "b) Uniformly distributed",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the resultant of the soil pressure coincides with the resultant of the loads and the center of gravity of the footing, the soil pressure is assumed to be uniformly distributed."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "In designing rectangular combined footing _________ should be adopted as the design value.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stress distribution",
            "b) Compression index",
            "c) Maximum bending moment",
            "d) Safe bearing pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum bending moment should be adopted as the design value for the reinforced concrete rectangular footing, which should also be checked for maximum shear and bond etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "For a rectangular combined footing, x̅ is given as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) x̅ = L/2",
            "b) L/3 < x̅ < L/2",
            "c) x̅ = L/3",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a rectangular combined footing, x̅ = L/2 and for a trapezoidal combined footing solutions lies between the limits L/3 < x̅ < L/2."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Generally combined footing is assumed to rest on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesive soil",
            "b) Homogeneous soil",
            "c) Cohesion-less soil",
            "d) Non homogeneous soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is assumed that the combined footings are rigid and rests on a homogeneous soil, so as to give rise to a linear stress distribution on the bottom of the footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "The design procedure of strap footing is essentially that of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct method",
            "b) Trial and error method",
            "c) Graphical method",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The designing of strap or cantilever footing is based on trial and error method, it begins with a trial value of e so that the length L1 is known. The calculations are repeated with another value of e till values of the reactions R1 and R2 calculated by both the procedure, coincide."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "What will be the shape of footing if a=0, is substituted in the pressure intensity equation “q2 = a. qs”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular",
            "b) Triangular",
            "c) Trapezoidal",
            "d) Circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the pressure intensity equation q2 = a. qs, if a= 0 we have a triangle with x̅ = L/3."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "The foundation that is used when the soil mass is sufficiently erratic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strap footing",
            "b) Combined footing",
            "c) Mat footing",
            "d) Rectangular combined footing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mat footing is used where the soil contains compressible lenses or the soil is sufficiently erratic so that the differential settlement would be difficult to control."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Usually, rafts are designed as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reinforced slabs",
            "b) Reinforced concrete flat slabs",
            "c) Ordinary concrete slab",
            "d) Inverted flat slabs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ordinarily, rafts are designed as reinforced concrete flat slabs using heavy beams."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "The weight of the raft is not considered in the structural design, because ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight is carried by subsoil",
            "b) Raft does not remain contact with soil",
            "c) The weight is transferred to column",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The weight of the raft is not considered in the structural design because it is assumed to be carried by directly by the subsoil."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "If a maximum settlement of 50 mm is permitted for a raft, the differential settlement must not exceed ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 mm",
            "b) 10 mm",
            "c) 20 mm",
            "d) 25 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A raft may undergo large settlement without causing harmful differential settlement. For this reason, almost double settlement of that permitted for footing is acceptable for raft. Therefore if a maximum settlement of 50 mm (2 in) is permitted for a raft, the differential settlement is not likely to exceed 20 mm (0.75 in)."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "The net ultimate bearing capacity for raft may be determined by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Skempton’s equation and Terzaghi’s equation",
            "b) Darcy’s equation",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The net ultimate bearing capacity may be determined from both Skempton and Terzaghi’s equation as given below:\ni) Skempton’s equation: q nf = 5 [1 + 0.2D/B ] [1 + 0.2B/L]c\nii) Terzaghi’s equation: q nf = 5.7[ 1 + 0.3B/L]c."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "In raft footing, if the C.G of the load coincide with the centroid of the raft, the upward load is considered as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non uniform pressure",
            "b) Uniform pressure",
            "c) Excess pressure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the Center of gravity of the load coincides with the centroid of the raft, the upward load is regarded as a uniform pressure, which will be equal to the downward load divided by the area of the raft."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Raft is subdivided in to series of beams to establish __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear failure and Moment diagrams",
            "b) Pressure distribution",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The raft is subdivided into a series of continuous beams (strips) centered on the appropriate column rows to establish shear failure and moment diagram."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "The penetration resistance N for designing of raft should be taken at ___________ intervals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 cm",
            "b) 60 cm",
            "c) 75 cm",
            "d) 20 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The penetration resistance N values should be taken at 75 cm intervals for a depth equal to width of the raft, below the base of the raft."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "If the penetration resistance N is less than 5, which of the following measures can be adopted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using piles and piers and Compacting sand",
            "b) Using inverted flat slab",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If N is less than 5, sand should be compacted by artificial means to rise N above 10, or else piles or piers should be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "The net pressure can be calculated for raft having width greater than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 m",
            "b) 20 cm",
            "c) 30 cm",
            "d) 4 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Based on the settlement criterion for raft, the net pressure can be calculated from the following equation having its width greater than 6m.\nqp = 20(N-3) Rw2 kN/m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "According to IS codes, the maximum differential settlements should not exceed ___________ in the foundation on clayey soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 mm",
            "b) 100 mm",
            "c) 25 mm",
            "d) 40 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to IS: 2950-1965 code of practice, the maximum settlement should not exceed 40 mm in the foundation on clayey soils and 25 mm in foundations on clayey soils."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "The possible method adopted for designing of raft foundation is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conventional method",
            "b) Elastic method",
            "c) Soil line method",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The behavior of a raft foundation being complicated, a number of simplifying assumption has to be made in design. There are two approaches for design-conventional method and the elastic method or the soil line method."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "The conventional method for designing raft foundation is based on which of the following assumptions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Foundation is infinitely rigid and Soil pressure is assumed to be planar",
            "b) Overburden pressure is assumed as zero",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conventional method is based on the following two basic assumptions:\ni) The foundation is infinitely rigid and therefore, the actual deflection of the raft does not influence the pressure distribution below the shaft.\nii) The soil pressure is assumed to be planar such that the centroid of the soil pressure coincides with the line of action of the resultant force of all the loads acting on the foundation."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "The actual reinforcement provided should be ___________ of that worked out theoretically by conventional method.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twice",
            "b) Thrice",
            "c) Lesser",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The actual reinforcement provided should be twice of that worked out theoretically in the case of design by conventional method."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "The method that can be used for designing raft, based on elastic method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simplified elastic foundation and Truly elastic foundation",
            "b) Conventional elastic foundation",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A number of methods have been proposed based primarily on two approaches of a simplified and truly elastic foundation, i) simplified elastic foundation ii) truly elastic foundation."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "In truly elastic foundation, the soil is assumed to be obey ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Terzaghi’s theory",
            "b) Hooke’s law",
            "c) Skempton’s theory",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The soil in a simplified elastic foundation is assumed to be continuous elastic medium obeying Hooke’s law."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Both conventional and flexible method can be used only in the case when _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Foundation is laid on cohesive soil",
            "b) Soil pressure is low",
            "c) Foundation is flexible",
            "d) Load is concentrated on larger area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conventional and flexible methods are to be used in case the foundation is comparatively flexible and the loads tend to concentrate over small areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "The modulus of subgrade reaction is applicable only when the load is applied through _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plate of size 30 ×30 cm and Beam 30 cm wide on soil area",
            "b) Plate size is 10 × 10 cm",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The modulus of subgrade reaction (Ks) is applicable to the case of load through a plate of size 30 × 30 cm or beam 30 cm wide on soil area."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "The value of Ks(modulus of subgrade reaction) can be found out, based on the effect of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size and Shape",
            "b) Properties",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of Ks can be found corresponding to a different size and shape for both cohesive and cohesionless soils."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "The effect of shape is based on ____________principal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Principal of superposition",
            "b) System of forces",
            "c) Hooke’s law",
            "d) Principal of center of gravity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effect of shape utilizes the principal of superposition."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "In effect of shape method, the columns loads and bearing pressure distribution are divided in to ___________ system of forces.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Four",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The columns loads and bearing pressure distribution are divided in three system of forces such that each system balance within itself so that the sum of forces is zero and the sum of moments of these forces about any point is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "The first system of forces consist of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference between actual column loads",
            "b) Varying distributed load acting downwards",
            "c) Column support reaction acting downwards",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first system of forces consists of i) uniformly distributed bearing pressure w acting upwards along the entire area of the raft ii) the column support reaction acting vertically downwards obtained by treating the raft as an inverted floor carrying the uniformly distributed load w with the reaction at the point of loading."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "The resultant earth pressure at any point of a raft is considered to be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) w + mw",
            "b) (1-m)w",
            "c) w-mw",
            "d) (1-w)m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The earth pressure varies from point to point of a raft, and hence the resultant pressure at any point is considered to be w + mw, where w is constant and m varies throughout the raft."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "The third system of forces is composed of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Varying upward pressure and Varying downward pressure",
            "b) Distributed load",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The varying distributed load pressure in raft, acting both upward and downward forms the third system of forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "The art of driving piles into the ground was first established by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greeks",
            "b) Romans",
            "c) Philippians",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The art of driving was first well-established in Roman times and the details of such foundation were recorded by Vitruvius in 59 A.D."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Based on the function, piles can be classified into ___________ types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Based on the function or the use, piles may be classified as 1) end bearing piles 2) friction piles 3) compaction piles 4) tension pile 5) anchor pile 6) fender pile 7) batter pile 8) sheet pile."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Which of the following piles is used to compact loose granular soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Friction piles",
            "b) End bearing piles",
            "c) Compaction piles",
            "d) Tension piles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Compaction piles are used to compact loose granular soil, thus increasing their bearing capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Sheet piles are commonly used as __________ in hydraulic structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bulk heads",
            "b) Bearing stratum",
            "c) Boulders",
            "d) Composite piles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sheet piles are commonly used as bulkheads, or as an impervious cutoff to reduce seepage and uplift under the hydraulic structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "The piles that are used for protecting structures from ships and floating object is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anchor piles",
            "b) Fender piles",
            "c) Compaction piles",
            "d) Batter piles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fender piles and dolphins are used to protect waterfront structures against the impact of ships or other floating objects."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Modern pile driving method was first invented by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Romans",
            "b) Nasmyth",
            "c) Terzaghi",
            "d) Vitruvious"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Modern pile driving started with the first steam pile drivers, invented by Nasmyth in 1845."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "The precast concrete piles are generally used for a maximum design load of about ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 tonnes",
            "b) 100 tonnes",
            "c) 75 tonnes",
            "d) 80 tonnes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The precast concrete piles are generally used for a maximum design load of about 80 tonnes, except for large pre-stressed piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Cast-in-situ piles may be classified in to ________ classes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Three",
            "b) Eight",
            "c) Two",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cast-in-situ piles can be classified in to two classes: driven piles(cased or uncased) and bored piles(pressure piles, pedestal piles and under reamed piles)."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Which of the following piles is a cast-in-situ type of concrete pile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Under-reamed pile",
            "b) Raymond standard pile",
            "c) Pressure pile",
            "d) Anchor pile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Raymond standard pile and Raymond step-taper pile are the common types of cast-in-situ piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Composite piles are suitable for ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum design load",
            "b) Project above the water table",
            "c) Compacting the soil",
            "d) Protect water front structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Composite piles are suitable where the upper part of a file is to project above the water table. Such a pile consists of a lower portion of untreated timber and the upper portion of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Piles are commonly driven in to ground by means of special device called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pile driver and Hammer",
            "b) Driller",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Piles are commonly driven by means of hammer supported by a crane or by a special device known as pile drivers."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "The types of hammer used for driving piles are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drop hammer",
            "b) Diesel hammer",
            "c) Vibratory hammer",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hammer of the following types: i) drop hammer ii) single acting hammer iii) double acting hammer iv) diesel hammer v)vibratory hammer."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "If a hammer is raised by steam and allowed to fall by gravity on top of the pile, it is called as________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diesel hammer",
            "b) Vibratory hammer",
            "c) Single acting hammer",
            "d) Drop hammer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If a hammer is raised by steam, compressed air or internal combustion, but is allowed to fall by gravity alone, it is called as single acting hammer. The energy of such hammer is equal to the weight of the ram times the height of the fall."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Single acting hammers provide an advantage in __________ type of soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compact soil and Hard soil",
            "b) Light weight soil",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Single acting hammers are advantageous when driving heavy piles in compact or hard piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "The maximum load which can be carried by a pile is defined as its __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultimate load carrying capacity",
            "b) Ultimate bearing resistance",
            "c) Ultimate bearing capacity",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ultimate load carrying capacity, or ultimate bearing resistance or ultimate bearing capacity Q up is defined as the maximum load which can be carried by a pile and at which the pile continues to sink without further increase of load."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "The allowable load which the pile can carry safely is determined on the basis of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Factor of safety",
            "b) Load test",
            "c) Stability of the pile foundation",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The allowable load Qa is the safe load which the pile can carry safely and is determined on the basis of: i) overall stability of the pile-foundation ii) the permissible settlement iii) ultimate bearing resistance divided by factor of safety."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "The load carrying capacity of a pile can be determined by which of the following methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic formulae",
            "b) Static formulae",
            "c) Plate load test",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The load carrying capacity of a pile can be determined by the following methods: i) Penetration tests ii) Dynamic formulae iii) Static formulae iv) Plate load test."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Which of the following are some of the commonly used dynamic formula?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engineers News formula and Hiley’s formula",
            "b) Static formula",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Engineers News formula as proposed by Wellington and Hiley’s formula given by the original expression of Hiley are the commonly used dynamic formula."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "When a pile hammer hits the pile, the total driving energy is equal to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight of hammer times the height of drop",
            "b) Weight of the ram time times the height of the stroke",
            "c) Sum of the impact of the ram",
            "d) Sum of the impact of ram plus the energy delivered by explosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a pile hammer hits the pile, the total driving energy is equal to the weight of hammer the height of drop or stroke."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Dynamic formulae are best suited for _________ type of soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fine grained soil",
            "b) Coarse grained soil",
            "c) Cohesive soil",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dynamic formulae are best suited to coarse grained soils for which the shear strength is independent of rate of loading."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Dynamic formula does not indicate about _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temporary change in soil structure and Future settlement",
            "b) Allowable load",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A disadvantage of a dynamic formula is that it gives no indication about the reduced bearing future settlement or temporary changes in soil structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "The dynamic formula is valueless for which of the following type of soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loose sand",
            "b) Saturated soil",
            "c) Clay soil",
            "d) Compacted soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For clays, the dynamic formulae are valueless because the skin friction developed in clay during driving is very much less than which occurs after a period of time."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "In dynamic formulae what are the energy losses, that is not accounted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Energy Loss due to vibration and Energy loss due to heat",
            "b) Frictional loss",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In dynamic formulae, the energy loss due to vibrations, heat and damage to dolly or packaging are not taken into account."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "The greater objection to any of the pile driving formulae is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uncertainty in relation between dynamic and static resistance",
            "b) Shear strength of the soil",
            "c) Uncertainty in the allowable pressure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The greater objection to any of the pile driving formulae is the uncertainty about the relationship between the dynamic and static resistance to soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "The static formula is based on the assumption that the ultimate bearing capacity Qup is equal to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rf + Qa",
            "b) Rf + Rp",
            "c) As + Ap",
            "d) Q up / F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The static formulae are based on the assumption that the ultimate bearing capacity Qup of a pile is the sum of the total ultimate skin friction Rf and total ultimate point or end bearing resistance Rp:\nQup = Rf + Rp."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "The pile load test should be performed on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Working pile",
            "b) Test pile",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pile load test can be performed on a working pile which forms the foundation of the structure or on a test pile."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "A Factor of safety that should be adopted for finding an allowable load for a pile is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5 and 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The IS code recommends that for working out allowable load, a minimum factor of safety 2.5 or 3 should be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "For pile in cohesive soil __________ is neglected for individual pile action.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frictional resistance",
            "b) Surface area of pile",
            "c) Shear strength of soil",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the pile in cohesive soil, point bearing is generally neglected for individual pile action, since it is negligible as compared to frictional resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "The allowable load for the pile is given by __________ equation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Qa = Qup/ F",
            "b) Qa = Qup× F",
            "c) Qa = WH /F(S+C)",
            "d) Qa = WH /6(S+2.5)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The allowable load Qp for a pile is given by dividing the ultimate bearing capacity Qup by a suitable factor of safety F.\nQa = Qup/ F."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "The separation of Q at any stage of loading into Rp and Rf in cyclic test is based on experimental value found out by________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hailey",
            "b) A.F. Van Weele",
            "c) A.M. Wellington",
            "d) MacArthur"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The separation of Q at any stage of loading into Rp and Rf in cyclic test is based on experimental found value of A.F. Van Weele (1957) that the load on the pile toes (1957) that the load on the pile toe (i.e. RP) increases linearly with the elastic compression of the soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "The test which can be used for separating load carried by the pile is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyclic load test",
            "b) Pile load test",
            "c) Penetration test",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cyclic load test is particularly useful in separating the load carried by the pile into the skin friction and point bearing resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "The result of Dutch cone penetration test can be applied to determine _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultimate skin fraction",
            "b) Total ultimate point",
            "c) Ultimate bearing capacity",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The result of Dutch cone penetration test can be applied with sufficient accuracy to determine the ultimate bearing capacity of piles in cohesion soils."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "The elastic compression Δ L of a pile can be calculated by the expression based on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Terzaghi’s theory",
            "b) Hooke’s law",
            "c) Meyerhof’s theory",
            "d) Hiley’s formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The elastic compression Δ L of the pile corresponding to any load Q (= Rf + Rp) can be calculated from the following expression based on Hooke’s law,\nΔ L = (Q – Rf/2) L / AE."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "The efficiency of pile group depends upon __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Characteristic of pile and Spacing of pile",
            "b) Bearing capacity of soil",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The efficiency of pile group depends upon the following factors: Characteristics of pile (i.e. length, diameter, material etc.), spacing of pile, total number of piles in a row and number of rows etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Which of the following formulae can be used for determining the efficiency of pile group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic formulae",
            "b) Static formulae",
            "c) Feld’s formulae",
            "d) Hiley’s formulae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Converse Labarre formulae, Seiler-kenney formulae, Feld’s rule are some of the common formulae available for determining the efficiency of pile group."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "In which of the following rule, the value of each pile is reduced by one-sixteenth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Converse Labarre formulae",
            "b) Feld’s formulae",
            "c) Seiler-Keeney formulae",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Feld’s rule, the value of each pile is reduced by one-sixteenth on account of the effect of the nearest pile in each diagonal or straight row of which the pile in question is a member."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "The bearing capacity of a single pile in clay is mainly due to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Friction",
            "b) Shear strength of soil",
            "c) Allowable load",
            "d) Ultimate load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bearing capacity of single pile in clay is mainly due to friction, and the friction and the point bearing resistance may be negligible."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "The downward drag acting on a pile due to the movement of the surrounding is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Skin friction",
            "b) Negative skin friction",
            "c) Frictional force",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Negative skin friction is downward drag acting on a pile due to the downward movement of the surrounding compressible soil relative to the pile."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "The area of the pile group along the failure surface is equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perimeter × Area of cross section",
            "b) Breadth × Length",
            "c) Perimeter × Length",
            "d) Perimeter/area of cross section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The area of the pile group, along failure surface is approximately equal to the perimeter P of the pile group multiplied by the length L of the pile."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "The pile spacing of each pile is taken as __________ diameter of the pile.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Four",
            "b) Five",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Ten"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A spacing of three times the diameter of piles is commonly selected as trial spacing between the piles and checked against the criterion that the resistance Qs obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "The settlement of a group of friction piles can be computed on the assumption that ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clay is incompressible",
            "b) Pile below the lower level is ignored",
            "c) Bearing resistance is zero",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As a rough approximation, the settlement of a group of friction piles can be computed on the assumptions that the clay contained between the top of piles is incompressible."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "The equation used for determining the bearing capacity of a group of friction piles is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Qup = Rf + Rp",
            "b) Qug = n Qup . ηg",
            "c) Qug = n Qup / ηg",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A method of estimating the bearing capacity of a group of friction piles is to multiply the quantity nQup by a reduction factor called the efficiency of pile group.\nQug = n Qup . ηg."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "When the under-reamed pile has only one bulb, it is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multi-under reamed pile",
            "b) Single-under reamed pile",
            "c) Unique-under reamed pile",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the pile has only one bulb, it is known as single-under reamed pile, while the pile with more than one bulb is known as multi-under reamed pile."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "The diameter of the under-reamed pile is kept equal to _______ times the diameter of pile steam.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 2.5",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally the diameter of the under-reamed pile bulb is kept equal to 2.5 times the diameter of pile steam. However, it may vary from 2 to 3 times the stem diameter of pile steam."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Under-reamed pile foundation is most suitable for ___________ type of condition.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seasonal moisture change",
            "b) Dry conditioned soil",
            "c) Cohesive type of soil",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The under-reamed pile foundation find application in widely varying situations in a type of soils where foundation are required to laid on undesirable effect of seasonal moisture change as in expansive soils. "
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "The load carrying capacity of a under-reamed pile may be determined by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Safe load test",
            "b) Penetration test",
            "c) Pile load test",
            "d) Cyclic load test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The load carrying capacity of an under-reamed pile may be determined from safe load test, in the absence of actual test."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "The under-reamed piles are connected by a beam known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capping beam and Grade beam",
            "b) Reamed beam",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The under-reamed piles are connected by a reinforced concrete beam, known as capping beam or grade beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "The maximum spacing of the under-reamed pile should not normally exceed __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 meters",
            "b) 2½ meters",
            "c) 1.5 meters",
            "d) 30 centimeters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum spacing of the under-reamed pile should not normally exceed 2½ m as to avoid heavy capping beams."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Under reamed piles are normally bored _________ piles.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cast-in-situ piles",
            "b) Pre-cast-piles",
            "c) Steel piles",
            "d) Composite piles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Under reamed piles are bored cast-in-situ concrete piles having one or more bulbs formed by enlarging the bore hole."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "The spacing of the piles in under-reamed pile foundation depends on which of the following factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nature of the ground and Type of pile",
            "b) Load acting on the pile",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The spacing of the piles shall be considered in relation to the nature of the ground, the types of pile and the manner in which the pile transfers the load to the ground."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "The grade beams are designed for a maximum bending moment of _________ if the beams are supported.",
        "Options": [
            "a) (wL2)/50",
            "b) (wL2)/30",
            "c) (wL2)",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The grade design are designed for a maximum bending moment of (wL2)/50 if the beam are supported during the construction, and for a bending moment of (wL2)/30 if the beams are not supported."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "The details of the depth of beam and reinforcement required for various loading is provided by_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indian standard code",
            "b) Central Building Research Institute, Roorkee",
            "c) M.I.T system",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Design of grade beam, depth of beam and reinforcement required for various loading is provided by Central Building Research Institute, Roorkee."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "The equipment required for construction of a under-reamed pile is________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auger boring guide",
            "b) Spiral auger",
            "c) Concreting funnel",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The equipment required for the construction of pile are i) Auger boring guide ii) spiral auger with extension rods iii) under-reamer with soil bucket and iv) concreting funnel."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "The use of bore guide in under-reamed pile foundation is essential for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To drill the bore hole",
            "b) To provide a support to the pile",
            "c) To keep the bore holes vertical",
            "d) To set the guide assembly in position"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The used of boring guide is essential in order to keep the bore holes vertical and also in its position."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Which of the following stages are involved in the construction of under reamed piles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concreting of piles and Boring by auger",
            "b) Concreting the funnel",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The various stage involved in the construction of under reamed pile foundation are i) boring by auger ii) under-reaming by under-reamer iii) placing reinforcement cage in position iv) concreting of pile caps, plinth beams and curtain walls."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "The depth of the bore hole is checked at _________ before insertion of the under-reamer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) At the start and At the end",
            "b) Each time",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The depth of the bore hole is checked each time before insertion of the under-reamer so that any loose earth spilled from the bucket is removed."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Routine tests are usually carried out on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test piles",
            "b) Working piles",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Routine test should be carried out on test piles while initial test are preferably carried on test piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "In the process of pile foundation, boring is done with the help of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boring guide",
            "b) Under-reamer",
            "c) Spiral auger",
            "d) Pile beams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Boring is done with the help of spiral auger, present at the circular collar of the guide assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Enlarging the stem of bore hole at the depth is done by using________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spiral auger",
            "b) Under-reamer",
            "c) Boring guide",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Under-reaming or enlarging the stem of bore hole at the required depths is achieved by means of the under-reamer consisting of a set of two collapsible blade assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "For completion of one under-ream, how many buckets of earth are required for removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Five",
            "b) Ten",
            "c) Eight",
            "d) Three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally, removal of eight buckets full of earth is required for completion of one under-ream."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Pile groups in under-reamed pile foundation can be tested by means of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Free standing piles and Pile foundation",
            "b) Cannot be tested",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pile groups may be tested as both free standing piles or piled foundation by applying series of load. "
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "The dimension of the bulb in an under-reamed pile can be checked by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meter scale",
            "b) G.I pipe assembly",
            "c) Auger",
            "d) Under-reamer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dimensions of the bulb can be checked by means of a graduated G.I. pipe assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Cased cast-in-situ piles are suitable for _________ conditions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seasonal moisture change",
            "b) Dry condition",
            "c) All ground conditions",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cased cast-in-situ piles are suitable in practically all ground conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Bored compaction piles are the modification of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Composite piles",
            "b) End bearing piles",
            "c) Compaction piles",
            "d) Under-reamed piles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bored compaction piles are the modification of under-reamed piles. These piles are also cast-in-situ piles, same as under-reamed piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "The types of Raymond concrete piles in use are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Raymond standard concrete pile and Raymond step-taper pile",
            "b) Raymond cased pile",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At present, two types of Raymond piles are in use i) Raymond standard concrete pile and ii) Raymond step-taper concrete pile."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "The Raymond standard pile is used primarily as a________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compaction pile",
            "b) Tension pile",
            "c) Friction pile",
            "d) End bearing pile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Raymond standard pile is used primarily as a friction pile since its uniform heavy taper of 1 in 30 usually results in shorter piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "One of the main advantages of using cased piles are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) On-the-job-length flexibility and Internal inspection after being driven",
            "b) Protect concrete fillings",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The advantages of using cased piles are the on-the-job length flexibility, internal inspection after it is driven."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Who was the first to develop a method for placing cast-in-situ concrete piles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) McArthur",
            "b) A.M. Wellington",
            "c) Raymond",
            "d) Hiley"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In 1897, A.A. Raymond patented the Raymond pile system and was first develop a practical, economical way of placing cast-in-situ concrete piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Raymond concrete pile is reinforced with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corrugated steel shell",
            "b) Steel mandrel",
            "c) Steel bars",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Raymond standard concrete pile consists of thin corrugated sheet steel closed at the bottom that acts as a reinforcement."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "The type of cased piles used in soil, where the driving is very hard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) McArthur cased pile",
            "b) Raymond standard pile",
            "c) Western button bottom piles",
            "d) Swage pile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Swage piles are used with advantage in some soil where it is designed to leave watertight shell for some time before filling the concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Western button bottom piles uses ________ for driving.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concrete plug",
            "b) Auger",
            "c) Conical shoe",
            "d) Under-reamer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The western button pile uses a concrete plug, of the shape of a button to form an enlarged hole in the soil for driving."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "The piles that are suitable for end-bearing to friction friction-load carrying soils is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Swage piles",
            "b) Union metal monotone piles",
            "c) McArthur cased piles",
            "d) Western button pile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Monotube piles use tapered fluted steel without mandrel, so they are suitable for a wide variety of soil conditions, from end-bearing to friction-load-carrying soils."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an advantage of using uncased cast-in-situ piles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They need no storage place",
            "b) The concrete cannot be damaged by driving",
            "c) Special equipment is not required",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The uncased piles have the advantage that i) They need no storage place ii) they do not require cutting off excess length iii) do not require special equipment and iv) the concrete is not liable to damage from driving."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "The types of uncased piles used are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Swage pile",
            "b) McArthur cased pile",
            "c) Simplex pile",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The following are the common types of uncased cast-in-situ concrete piles:\ni) Simplex pile\nii) Vibro pile\niii) Franki pile\niv) Padestal pile."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "The uncased cast-in-situ piles can be used only in the condition, where _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water should not fall in the hole and Adjacent pile will not damage the concrete",
            "b) Seasonal condition change",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The uncased piles are used only where it is certain that neither soil nor water will fall in to the hole after withdrawing a driven mandrel or shell and also where adjacent pile will not damage the green concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "In Franki pile foundation, the bottom of the pile is provided in the shape of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spherical",
            "b) Mush-room",
            "c) Cone",
            "d) Rectangular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Franki pile has an enlarged base of mush-room shape, which gives the effect of a spread footing."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Which of the following pile is used, when the ground is soft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Franki pile",
            "b) Simplex pile",
            "c) Vibro-piles",
            "d) Pedestal piles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vibro-piles are used where the ground is shaft, thus offering little frictional resistance to the flow of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "The bearing capacity of vibro-pile can be increased by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing its diameter",
            "b) Elongation of the pile",
            "c) By using cone-shape base at the bottom",
            "d) By adding more load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bearing capacity of vibro-expanded piles is increased by enlarging its diameter at the bottom."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "If tamping of concrete is provided at regular intervals in a simplex pile, it is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simplex standard pile",
            "b) Simplex tamped pile",
            "c) Tamped standard pie",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a simplex tamped pile, tamping of green concrete is done after the casing is withdrawn, at regular intervals."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "The base of an vibro-pile should be in the shape of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conical shoe",
            "b) Mushroom",
            "c) Sphere",
            "d) Rectangle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bottom of a vibro-pile is provided with a conical shoe so that it can be easily driven up to the desired depth."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "In which of the following piles, alligator jaw point can be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vibro-pile",
            "b) Pedestal pile",
            "c) Franki pile",
            "d) Simplex pile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In simplex pile if the soil is firm enough to stand, the cast iron shoe at the base is provided with alligator jaw point."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Franki piles are best suited for _________ type of soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesive soil",
            "b) Clay",
            "c) Granular soil",
            "d) Cohesion less soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Franki pile is more useful where a bearing stratum of limited thickness can be reached at a reasonable depth, so they are best suited for the granular type of soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "There are __________ types of bored piles.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bored piles are of three types: i) Pressure piles, ii) under-reamed piles, and iii) Bored compaction piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "In bored pile, concreting is done by using ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auger",
            "b) Casing tube",
            "c) Under-reamer",
            "d) Concrete plug"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bored piles are done by forming a bore hole in the ground and then concreting it, either with the help of a casing tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "A major difference between the procedure of construction in bored piles and cast-in-situ driving piles is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Driving equipment",
            "b) Method of driving",
            "c) Concrete filling",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The procedure of construction in bored piles is different than the cast-in-situ driven pile where heavy pile driving equipment is required. "
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "The type of bored pile that is suitable for congestion sites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Under-reamed piles",
            "b) Bored compaction piles",
            "c) Pressure piles",
            "d) Simplex piles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pressure piles are most suitable where heavy pile driving machinery cannot be used and in congested sites because of its compact structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "In pressure piles, the soil is excavated by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Casing tube",
            "b) Under-reamer",
            "c) Concrete plug",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Boring tool such as auger working inside the steel tube excavates the soil in pressure piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "An advantage of preferring bored piles is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) The concrete is not liable to damage",
            "b) Vibration caused by driving can be avoided",
            "c) They need no storage space",
            "d) No requirement of special handling equipment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bored piles have an advantage of avoiding vibrations and noise caused by driving of piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "In pressure pile, the frictional resistance is increased by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compression of soil and Rough irregular surface",
            "b) Bearing capacity",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The diameter of the pile exceeds that of the tube, owing to the compression of soil, and rough irregular surface is formed which increases the frictional resistance of piles."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "The bearing value of the pressure pile can be increased by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cement grout",
            "b) Increasing diameter",
            "c) Changing the shape of base",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If it is required to increase the bearing value of the pile, an enlarged base is formed by introducing cement grout after the tube is sunk and forced it by air pressure into the adjacent soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "The common types of well shape are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular",
            "b) Dumb bell",
            "c) Single circular",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The common types of well shapes are: i) single circular ii) Twin circular iii) Dumb-well iv) Double-D v) Twin-hexagonal vi) Twin-octagonal vii) Rectangular."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Well are also called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open caissons",
            "b) Shell sunk",
            "c) Caisse",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Open caissons (“caisson” a French word) are called as wells."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "___________ forms the most common type of deep foundation for bridges.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pile foundation",
            "b) Well foundation",
            "c) Shallow foundation",
            "d) Pier foundation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In India, well foundation forms the most common type of deep foundation for bridges."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "The choice of a particular shape for a well depends on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dimension of the base and Cost of sinking",
            "b) Type of soil condition",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The choice of a particular shape of well depends upon the dimension of the pier or abutment, the care and cost of sinking, the considerations of the tilt and shift during the sinking."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "What are the types of caissons that can be used as a foundation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Box caissons and Open caissons",
            "b) Closed caissons",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The caissons are of three types: i) Box caissons ii) open caissons iii) pneumatic caissons."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Which of the following caissons, permits excavation in dry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pneumatic caissons",
            "b) Box caissons",
            "c) Open caissons",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A pneumatic caisson has its lower end designed as a working chamber in which compressed air is forced to prevent the entry of water and thus permit excavation in dry."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "The sinking of the dredge is uniform in which of the following, shapes of well?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double-D",
            "b) Rectangular",
            "c) Circular",
            "d) Dumb-well"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the perimeter of the circle is equidistant at all points from the center of the dredge hole, the sinking is more uniform than other shapes."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "The components that are needed to be considered in designing of a well foundation is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape of the well",
            "b) Sand filing",
            "c) Bottom plug",
            "d) Dredge hole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The following components of a well have to be considered in the design of a well foundation: well curb cutting edge, steining, Bottom plug and well cap."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "A disadvantage in using circular shape of well foundation is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum perimeter",
            "b) Skin friction is maximum",
            "c) Diameter of well is more than required",
            "d) Sinking is more uniform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The disadvantage of a circular well is that in the direction parallel to the span of the bridge, the diameter of the well is much more than the minimum size required."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "The most economical shape, of a well for the construction of large pier is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twin circular",
            "b) Double-D",
            "c) Rectangular",
            "d) Single circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dredge area for a double-D shape is smaller when compared to others; hence it can be more economical than a singular circular well."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "The selection of the depth of a well is based on which of the following criteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adequate embedded length should be provided and The well should rest on strata of adequate bearing capacity",
            "b) The perimeter of the well should be minimum",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The selection of the depth of a well is based on the following two criteria:\ni) There should be the adequate embedded length of well, called the grip length below the lowest scour level.\nii) The well should be taken deep enough to rest on strata of adequate bearing capacity in relation to the load transmitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "For alluvial soil, the normal scour depth can be calculated by ___________ formula.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rankine’s formula",
            "b) Lacey’s formula",
            "c) Converse Labarre formula",
            "d) Terzaghi’s formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For alluvial soil mostly met with in North Indian Rivers, the normal scour depth can be calculated by Lacey’s formula:\nRL = 1.35(q2/f)1/3."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "The grip length of well is taken as _________ below the scour level in roads.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ½ R",
            "b) 1½ R",
            "c) 1/3 R",
            "d) 1 R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to the code of practice of the Indian Road Congress, the grip length is taken as 1/3 R below the scour level."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "For piers and abutment, the minimum depth of embedment below the scour level should be taken as _________ m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.0",
            "b) 1.2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to IRC code, it is recommended that the minimum depth of embankment below the scour level should not be less than 2.0 m for piers and abutment with arches and 1.2 m for other types of structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "What are the horizontal forces that are prone to act on a well foundation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wind force",
            "b) Earth pressure",
            "c) Seismic force",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A well foundation is liable to the following horizontal forces: i) force on account of water current ii) wind forces iii) seismic forces iv) earth pressure v) centrifugal forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "The analysis of well foundation is done based on the assumptions of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Banerjee and Gangopadhyay",
            "b) Lacey",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Based on the assumptions done by Banerjee and Gangopadhyay in 1960, the analysis of well foundation can be done."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "The maximum depth of scour at the nose of pier is _______ Lacey’s value.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twice",
            "b) Thrice",
            "c) Half",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum depth of scour at the nose of the pier, is found to be twice the Lacey’s value of normal scour depth: R = 2RL."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Coefficient of horizontal soil reaction m, depends on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape of the area carrying load and Nature of soil",
            "b) Skin friction",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Factor m, called the coefficient of horizontal soil reaction depends on the nature of soil, size and shape of the area which carries the load."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "When a rigid well starts moving parallel, it transforms the soil in to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Active and passive states",
            "b) Rigid state",
            "c) Loose sand",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a rigid soil, embedded in sand, starts moving parallel to its original position under the action of a horizontal force, it transforms the soil on one side to passive state and the other side in to active state."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "According to Terzaghi and Peck, the ultimate bearing capacity can be determined by which of the following expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q f = Q p + 2πRfs Df",
            "b) Q p = πR2(Q p + 2πRfs Df)",
            "c) Q p = 2πRfs Df",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to Terzaghi and Peck, the ultimate bearing capacity can be determined from the following expression:\nQ f = Q p + 2 π R fs Df\nWhere R = radius of well, Df = depth of well, fs = average skin friction."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "The well curb is designed for which of the following purpose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For avoiding skin friction",
            "b) Supporting the weight of well",
            "c) For designing the well",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The well curb is designed for supporting the weight of the well with well partial support at the bottom of the cutting edge."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be assumed for design purpose of well curb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Three point support of cutting edge",
            "b) Boulders",
            "c) Skin friction",
            "d) Steining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A three-point support of the cutting edge resting on a log may be assumed for design purposes of well curb."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "An effective well curb should withstand ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum stress",
            "b) Stress due to sand blows",
            "c) Its own weight",
            "d) Blasting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The well curb has to withstand stress due to sand blows, as well as due to light blasting required when boulder obstructs the sinking of well."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "The cutting edge should be provided with an angle of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45°",
            "b) 60°",
            "c) 90°",
            "d) 30°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cutting edge should have as sharp an angle of 30° practicable for knifing into the soil without making it too weak to resist the various stresses induced."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "A sharp vertical edge for the well is provided at _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inner Face of the well",
            "b) Out of the well",
            "c) Outside face of the caisson",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A sharp vertical edge or cutting edge should be provided along the outside face of the caisson or open well."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "At a given depth, the skin friction of the well is equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diameter of well",
            "b) μ times the lateral earth pressure",
            "c) Stress condition",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The unit skin friction increases with depth, and at a given depth, the skin friction is equal to the coefficient of friction μ times the lateral earth pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "For loose sand, the value of skin friction is between ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.73-2.93",
            "b) 4.9-19.5",
            "c) 1.22-3.42",
            "d) 3.42-6.84"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the purpose of design, the values of skin friction given by Terazaghi and peck may be used:\nSilt and soft clay: 0.73-2.93 t/m2\nVery stiff clay: 4.9-19.5 t/m2\nLoose sand: 1.22-3.42 t/m2\nDense sand: 3.42-6.84 t/m2\nDense gravel: 4.9 -9.4 t/m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Frictional resistance developed during the sinking the well depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roughness of the surface of contact",
            "b) Diameter of the well",
            "c) Type of soil",
            "d) Lateral earth pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frictional resistance depends on the roughness of the surface of contact. For example, a smoothly plastered well steining surface is said to reduce frictional resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "The skin friction developed in San Francisco Oakland Bay Bridge, was reduced by, which of the following methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By introducing special equipment",
            "b) By coating smooth oil surface",
            "c) By decreasing the stress developed",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In order to reduce the skin friction on the in San Francisco Oakland Bay Bridge, a coating which gave a smooth oily surface that was estimated to reduce the friction between the concrete and fairly clay by 40 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "The bottom plug is designed in _________ shape.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular",
            "b) Mushroom",
            "c) Bowl-shaped",
            "d) Circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bottom-plug is made in bowl-shaped so as to have inverted arch actions."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Laying of the well curb in river bed having water, is done by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Draining out the water",
            "b) Diverting the water",
            "c) Constructing cofferdams",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If water is present in the river, suitable cofferdams are constructed around the site of the well and islands are made."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "To avoid the setting of the cutting edge unevenly, ___________ can be introduced.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wooden sleepers",
            "b) Smooth oil surface",
            "c) Bottom plug",
            "d) Steining bars"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is desirable to insert wooden sleepers below the cutting edge at regular intervals so as to distribute the load and avoid setting of the cutting edge unevenly during concreting."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "The inside shuttering of the well curb is made up of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steel",
            "b) Wood",
            "c) Brick masonry",
            "d) Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inside shuttering of the well curb is generally made of brick masonry built to proper profile and plastered and the outer shuttering is made by wood or steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Excavation of soil inside the well in river beds can be done by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auger",
            "b) Sending in Workers",
            "c) Special equipment",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Excavation and scooping out of the soil inside the well can be done by sending down workers inside the well till the depth of water inside becomes about 1 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "When the well is sunk deeper, the skin friction is decreased by which of the following method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Use of phawrah jhams",
            "b) By tilting and shifting",
            "c) By applying kentledge",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To overcome the increased skin friction and the loss of weight due to buoyancy when the well is sunk deeper, additional load known as kentledge is applied on the well."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Unequal dredging of well causes _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collapsing of well",
            "b) Tilting",
            "c) Open excavation",
            "d) Maximum skin friction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the dredging is done unequally tilts and cannot be rectified if the well is sunk to a greater depth."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "The radius of the well curb should be kept _________ larger than the outside radius of well steining.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 cm and 4 cm",
            "b) 2 m",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As a precaution to avoid tilts and shifts, the radius of curb should be kept 2 to 4 cm larger than the outside radius of well steining."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "To counter act the tilts in the well during sinking operations, which of the following measures can be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regulation of grabbing",
            "b) Strutting the well",
            "c) Pushing by jack",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Any of the following measures can usefully be employed to counteract the tilts in the well during sinking operations: i) regulating of grabbing ii) water jetting iii) eccentric loading iv) pulling the well vi) pushing by jacks."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "In which of the following methods, hydraulic jack is used to counter attack the tilt in the well?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulling the well",
            "b) Eccentric loading",
            "c) Pushing by jack",
            "d) Pulling the well"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In pushing by jack method, the well may be pushed by force applied by hydraulic or mechanical jack on the tilted side of the wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "The method that is used to avoid the further increase in tilt is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pushing by jack",
            "b) Eccentric loading",
            "c) Strutting the well",
            "d) Pushing the well"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Strutting the well method is used to avoid any further increase in the tilt of the well rather than rectifying it."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "The essential feature of a pneumatic caissons are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tilting can be avoided and Removing water by Compressed air",
            "b) Skin fraction is zero",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The essential feature of a pneumatic caisson is that compressed air is used to exclude or remove water from the working chamber at the bottom."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "The method of construction of pneumatic caisson is similar to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Box caissons",
            "b) Open caissons",
            "c) Rectangular caissons",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The method of construction of pneumatic caisson is similar to that for open caissons (well) except that the working chamber is kept air tight."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "The working chamber of pneumatic caissons are kept airtight because ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To avoid tilting",
            "b) To remove the soil",
            "c) To prevent water from entering the chamber",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In order that sub-soil water may not enter the working chamber, the pressure of air in the shaft is kept airtight."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "The allowable pressure that is allowed inside the working chamber of pneumatic caissons is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 kg/cm2",
            "b) 4 kg/cm2",
            "c) 3.5 kg/cm2",
            "d) 7 kg/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Normally the tolerable air pressure under which a man can work is limited to 3.5 kg/cm2 in pneumatic caissons."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Advantage of using pneumatic caissons are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Affords easy inspection and Process is done under control conditions",
            "b) Sinking process is easy",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An advantage of pneumatic caisson is that the entire process of sinking well is carried out under controlled conditions and it affords easy inspection work."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Disadvantage of using pneumatic caissons are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process cannot be done under control conditions",
            "b) Sinking process is tedious",
            "c) Inspection process is time consuming",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In pneumatic caissons, the sinking of pneumatic caissons are tedious, time consuming and expensive."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "In order to prevent leakage of air in the working chamber ________ is provided.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arrangement of double gates",
            "b) Air compressor",
            "c) Air lock",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In order to prevent leakage of air, the arrangement of double gates is provided. The person enters the first gate, where pressure is atmospheric."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "The limiting head of water value in pneumatic caisson is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 m",
            "b) 25 m",
            "c) 35 m",
            "d) 50 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the maximum air pressure is limited to 3.5 kg /cm2. the limiting head of water is given by:\nhlim = 3.5/0.1 = 35 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "In order to assist sinking of well __________ method is used in pneumatic caissons.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air pressure is reduced and Using explosive",
            "b) Using airlocks",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In order to assist sinking process, air pressure may be reduced for a short while. Sometimes explosive may be employed in this case, it is essential to make arrangements for the immediate removal of fall fumes."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Pneumatic caissons are closed at _________ during construction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bottom",
            "b) Top",
            "c) Top and bottom",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pneumatic caissons are closed at the top and open at the bottom during construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Most of the motions encountered in soil dynamics are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plane linear motion",
            "b) Motion by impact",
            "c) Horizontal motion",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most of the motions encountered in soil dynamics work are those of vibration, plane linear motion, a motion brought about by impact, shock, elastic waves, and seismic action of geophysical forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "The theory of harmonic vibrations is applicable to _________ for designing of foundation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbines",
            "b) Motors",
            "c) Generators",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design of foundations of turbines, motors, generators, compressor, forge hammers and other machine having a rhythmic application of unbalanced forces requires special knowledge of the theory of harmonic vibrations."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "The constituent part of soil mechanics which deals with soil under dynamic condition is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass spring system",
            "b) Soil dynamics",
            "c) Soil system",
            "d) Mass system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Soil dynamics is defined as that constituent part of soil mechanics which deals with soil under dynamic conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "The factor responsible for additional dynamic load in rotating machines are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Static load and Inertial force",
            "b) Geophysical force",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inertial forces of rotating elements of machines contribute besides their static loads, additional dynamic loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "In soil dynamics problems, the analysis may be conveniently carried out by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spring mass system",
            "b) Inertial force",
            "c) Free vibration",
            "d) Amplitude test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In soil dynamic problems, the analysis may be conveniently carried out by a single equivalent mass supported by a perfectly elastic system or spring mass system."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "The mass spring system has ________ degrees of freedom.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The elastic spring system has six natural frequencies and thus has six degrees of freedom."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "The time for one complete oscillation of the mass in the spring system is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Time period",
            "c) Free period",
            "d) Frequency interval"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The time for one complete oscillation of the mass is called the free period and the distance up or down from the equilibrium position is called the amplitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Which of the following expression is called the equation of motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fn = k / m",
            "b) z + ωn2 z = 0",
            "c) m z + ωn2 z = 0",
            "d) k z + k / m = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The equation of motion is given by the following formula\nz + ωn2 z = 0\nWhere, m = mass of the vibrating body\nZ = acceleration\nωn = natural frequency of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "For an oscillatory machine, the force can be expressed as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cosine function and Sine function",
            "b) Cosec function",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally for an oscillatory machine (where the machinery vibrates because an unbalanced rotational force exists), the force can be expressed as a sine or cosine function, such as F0sinωt."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "The equation for natural frequency of system as suggested by Barken is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ωn = √f(1 – r2)",
            "b) ωn = √cu A / m",
            "c) ωn = cu A / m",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Barken suggested the following equation for the natural frequency of the system\nωn = √cu A / m\nWhere cu = co-efficient of elastic uniform compression of soil\nA = contact area of foundation with soil\nm = mass of machine plus foundation."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "The co-efficient of elastic uniform compression of soil depends on which of the following factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size of area of foundation",
            "b) Mass of foundation",
            "c) Exciting force",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient of elastic uniform compression of soil depends not only on elastic constant E and μ but also on the size of the base contact area of foundation."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "On calculating the natural frequency of the system, Barken did not take into account of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contact area",
            "b) Frequency ratio",
            "c) Mass of the vibrating soil",
            "d) Mass of machine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The formula suggested by Barken for natural frequency does not take into account of the mass of soil vibrating with the foundations."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "What are the methods for determining the natural frequency of the foundation of soil system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barken’s method and Rankine’s method",
            "b) Pauw’s method",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The three methods of determining the natural frequency of the foundation soil system are: i) Barken’s method ii) Balakrishna Rao’s method iii) Pauw’s method."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "In a damped force vibratory system, the support is derived by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Co-vibrating body",
            "b) Spring mass system",
            "c) Transmitting force",
            "d) Soil mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a damped force vibratory system, the support is derived from the foundation by way of transmitting a force (FT) to the foundation."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "The size of co-vibrating body of soil depends on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil mass",
            "b) Apparent soil mass",
            "c) Transmitted force",
            "d) Size of the base area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The size of co-vibrating body of soil depends on frequency and is influenced by the size of the base area of the vibrator and by the elastic properties of the soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "The mass of co-vibrating soil is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight of vibrator",
            "b) Soil mass",
            "c) Apparent soil mass",
            "d) Certain soil mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mass of co-vibrating soil is called the apparent soil mass ms, participating in the vibrations."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Recommended design value for permissible load on soil under the action of static load, for rock type soil group is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than 10",
            "b) 5-10",
            "c) 3.5-5",
            "d) Greater than 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The recommended design value of the co-efficient of elastic uniform compression for permissible load on soil under action of static load only is greater than 5 kg/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "The bulb of pressure concept for calculating the apparent mass of soil was introduced by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Balakrishna and Nag raj",
            "b) Barken",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d)   All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1960, Balakrishna and Nag raj proposed the bulb of pressure concept of calculating the apparent mass of soil participating in the vibration."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "An aim of the foundation designer should be such that the frequency ratio f/fn is either less than _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 0.6",
            "c) 2.0",
            "d) 3.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The aim of the designer should be such that the frequency ratio f/fn is either less than 0.6 or more than 1.5 by suitably proportioning it."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "The method of Barken is based on the assumption of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equation of motion",
            "b) Linear spring theory",
            "c) Participation of soil in the vibration",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Barken’s method is based on linear spring theory. The method neglects the effect of damping and participating in the soil mass."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "The rotation of foundation about y axes is known as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yawning",
            "b) Pitching",
            "c) Rocking",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the general case, rotation about y, z and x-axes are respectively known as rocking, yawning and pitching."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Barken’s method is used in ___________ places.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Congested area",
            "b) Design offices",
            "c) Working area",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Barken’s method is very much used in design offices."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "If the combined C.G. of the machine and foundation lies in the same vertical line, then the twisting modes are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coupled",
            "b) Uncoupled",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the combined C.G. of the machine and foundation lies in the same vertical line as the centroid of the base plane, then the vertical and translation and twisting modes are uncoupled."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "The value of kx for the elastic support of soil is given by which of the following expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kx = Cu A",
            "b) Kx = Cϴ Iy",
            "c) Kx = Cx A",
            "d) Kx = Cu Iy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The values of Kx, Ky and Kϴy for the elastic support of soil are given by the following expressions:\nFor vertical motion: Kz = Cu A\nFor horizontal motion: Kx = Cx A\nFor rocking motion: Kϴy: Cϴ Iy."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "The permissible amplitude should not exceed ___________ for reciprocating machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probable amplitude",
            "b) Limiting amplitude",
            "c) Maximum amplitude",
            "d) Minimum amplitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The permissible amplitude should not exceed the limiting amplitude for the machine prescribed by the manufacturers."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "The methods of Pauw and Balakrishna Rao are based on ___________ assumptions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equation of motion",
            "b) Linear spring theory",
            "c) Participation of soil in the vibration",
            "d) Barken’s method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The method of Pauw and Balakrishna Rao are based on the assumption that a certain mass of soil participates in the vibration with the foundation."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "According to Barken, the value of the coefficient of elastic uniform shear is taken as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 2 Cu",
            "c) 3.0",
            "d) 0.5 Cu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Barken, the coefficient of elastic uniform shear Cτ for foundation resting on elastic support is taken as 0.5 Cu."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "If foundation block is supported by an elastic pad of contact area A and thickness t, the value of stiffness factor for vertical motion is given by which of the following expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kx = C A/t",
            "b) Kz = E A/t",
            "c) Kϴy = Ely / t",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of stiffness factors are given by the following expressions:\nFor vertical motion: Kz = E A /t\nFor horizontal (sliding motion): Kx = CA /t\nFor rocking motion: Kϴy = Ely/t."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "The two natural frequencies representing the couple motion, in sliding and rocking motion is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ωn1 and ωn2",
            "b) ωx and ωy",
            "c) ωϴ and ωn",
            "d) ωn1 and ωn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ωn1 and ωn2 are the two natural frequencies representing the coupled action (i.e., sliding along x-axis and rocking about the y-axis)."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a classification of pavements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Load pavement",
            "b) Sub-grade pavement",
            "c) Flexible pavement",
            "d) Rigidity pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pavements are classified in to Flexible, rigid and semi-flexible, based on distributing loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Pavements are classified, based on ________ factors.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earth surface",
            "b) Materials used",
            "c) Rigidity of the pavement",
            "d) Distributing loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Depending upon the mode of supporting and distributing loads, pavements are classified in to Flexible, rigid and semi-flexible."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "The thickness design of the flexible pavement is influenced by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distributing load",
            "b) Strength of sub-grade",
            "c) Sub-base",
            "d) Soil properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design of flexible pavement is based on the principal that a surface load is dissipated by carrying it deep in to the ground through the layer of sub-grade."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "The essential difference between rigid flexible pavements is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distribution of load over sub-grade",
            "b) Distribution of load over sub-base",
            "c) Materials used",
            "d) Thickness of layers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The essential difference between rigid flexible pavements is the manner in which they distribute the load over the sub-grade."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "Rigid pavement are commonly made of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bitumen",
            "b) Portland cement concrete",
            "c) Dry-lean concrete",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rigid pavements are made up of Portland cement concrete and may or may not have a base course between the pavement and the sub-grade."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Which of the following pavement is capable of resisting small tensile strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Semi-flexible pavement",
            "b) Rigid pavement",
            "c) Flexible pavement",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A flexible pavement consists of relatively then wearing surface and hence, can resist only very small tensile strength then the other pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "The wearing surface of pavement are made of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bituminous materials",
            "b) Portland cement concrete",
            "c) Dry-lean concrete",
            "d) Other materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The purpose of wearing course, made of bituminous materials is to provide a smooth riding surface that is re silent and to resist the pressure exerted by the tyres."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "The stability of sub-grade in a pavement is influenced by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compaction",
            "b) water contact",
            "c) Materials used",
            "d) Rigidity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stability of the sub-grade is influenced by soil texture, water content, density, frost action, shrinkage and swelling and other climatic factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "In pavements ___________ forms the foundation layer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base course",
            "b) Sub-base",
            "c) Sub-grade",
            "d) Wearing course"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sub-grade is the foundation layer, the structure which must eventually support all the loads which come on to the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Base course and sub-base course are used under flexible pavements for __________ purpose.",
        "Options": [
            "a) To provide foundation",
            "b) To increase durability",
            "c) To increase load supporting capacity",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Base course and sub-base course are used under flexible pavements primarily to increase the load supporting capacity of the pavement by distributing the load through a finite thickness of pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "The flexible pavement-thickness consists of __________ components.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Three",
            "c) Four",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally, the flexible pavement-thickness consists of three components: surfacing, base and sub-base course."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Which of the following pavement can be used, for construction on black cotton soils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible pavement",
            "b) Semi-flexible pavement",
            "c) Rigid pavement",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rigid pavements are used for heavier loads and can be constructed over relatively poor sub-grade such as black cotton or plastic soils, peat etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Which of the following layer of pavement should withstand a high level of deformation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base course",
            "b) Sub-base",
            "c) Sub-grade",
            "d) Surfacing course"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The base course lies close to the pavement surface, and hence it must possess high resistance to deformation in order to withstand high pressure imposed on it."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "____________is a relatively stable crust constructed over the natural soil for the purpose of supporting and distributing the wheel loads.",
        "Options": [
            "a) pavements",
            "b) wall",
            "c) beam",
            "d) column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A pavement is a floor constructed over the natural soil. Road is a form of pavement. The pavements are constructed for transportation purpose that is relatively safe and fast then the conventional compacted soil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "The pavements can be ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) flexible only",
            "b) semi flexible only",
            "c) rigid only",
            "d)  flexible, semi flexible and rigid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pavements are classified depending on the mode of supporting and distribution of loads as:\n\nFlexible\nSemi-flexible \nRigid.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "The flexible pavements consists of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) thin wearing surface",
            "b) thick wearing surface",
            "c) no wearing surface",
            "d) wearing surface present at only specific places"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flexible pavements consists of thin wearing surface which is built over a base and sub-base course, and they rest on compacted surface. The wearing surface is smooth in order for the vehicles to ride on it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "__________ can take appreciable tensile stress.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible pavement",
            "b) Semi-flexible pavement",
            "c) Rigid pavement",
            "d) Tar pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A rigid pavement can take appreciable tensile stress and is capable of bridging small weakness and depression in the sub-grade. The flexible pavements are able to resist only small tensile stresses.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "The flexible pavements resist ___________ tensile stresses.",
        "Options": [
            "a) only very small",
            "b) large",
            "c) negligible",
            "d) very large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flexible pavements consists of thin wearing surface which is built over a base and sub-base course and are able to resist only small tensile stresses. The semi flexible pavement can possess appreciable flexural strength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "A semi-flexible pavement is made of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tar only",
            "b) bitumen only",
            "c) dry-lean concrete",
            "d) aggregates only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A semi-flexible pavement is made of dry-lean concrete or soil cement. The semi-flexible pavement possesses qualities intermediate between the flexible and the rigid pavements.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "The modulus of electricity of a semi-flexible pavement is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) lower than concrete",
            "b) greater than concrete",
            "c) equal to concrete",
            "d) is always zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The semi flexible pavement possess appreciable flexural strength but its modulus of electricity is lower than concrete. This is due to the fact that the semi flexible pavement is made of dry-lean concrete or soil cement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "The design of flexible pavement is based on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) slab mechanism",
            "b) grain to grain transfer",
            "c) column mechanism",
            "d) footing mechanism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design of flexible pavement is based on the principle that the surface load is dissipated by carrying it deep into the ground through the successive layers of granular material. Thus it uses grain to grain transfer mechanism.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "The flexible pavement do not distribute the load by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) distributing through thick layers",
            "b) grain to grain transfer",
            "c) bending action",
            "d) layered system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wheel load acting on the pavement will be distributed to a wider area such that stress decreases with the depth. The flexible pavement uses grain to grain transfer mechanism. Hence, it uses the concept of layered system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "The thickness design of flexible pavement is dependent on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) uniformity of subgrade",
            "b) thickness of subgrade",
            "c) length of subgrade",
            "d) strength of subgrade"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The thickness design of flexible pavement is influenced by the strength of subgrade as the load transfer is based on grain-to-grain mechanism. It also depends upon the quality and the compactness of the subgrade.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "The rigid pavement tends to distribute the load by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) slab mechanism",
            "b) grain to grain transfer",
            "c) column mechanism",
            "d) footing mechanism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rigid pavement are usually made of RCC. Thus, the rigid pavements have more tensile strength. Therefore the rigid pavement tend to distribute the load by slab mechanism.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "The uniform sub grade support is most important in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) flexible pavement",
            "b) semi-flexible pavement",
            "c) rigid pavement",
            "d) tar pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rigid pavements can be constructed over a relatively poor sub-grade like black cotton or plastic soils or peat, etc. The load is taken by the bending action of the slab and thus the uniform sub-grade support is the most essential condition for the satisfactory performance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "The weaving course is also known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) base course",
            "b) surfacing",
            "c) sub-base",
            "d) subgrade"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The weaving course is the top most layer in the cross-section of the pavements. The weaving course is also known as surfacing and is the component of the pavement with which the wheels of the vehicles are in contact.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "In flexible pavement, _______ sub grade is more essential.",
        "Options": [
            "a) well – compacted",
            "b) poorly-compacted",
            "c) low quality",
            "d) uniform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design of flexible pavement is influenced by the strength of subgrade as the load transfer is based on grain-to-grain mechanism and due to this, the sub-grade must be well compacted in order to transfer the loads efficiently.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "The wearing course of flexible pavement is made of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bituminous materials",
            "b) R.C.C",
            "c) P.C.C",
            "d) OPC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The wearing course of flexible pavement is made of bitumen. Bitumen on being sticky and ductile, provides smooth surface for riding vehicles and on having tensile strength it is resilient to major deformations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "The base course contains __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) granular material",
            "b) bituminous material",
            "c) silt",
            "d) clay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The wearing course of flexible pavement is made of bitumen which is flexible. This also ensures safety by warning when the failure of the pavement occurs due to consolidation of the base, or sub-base, or the sub-grade takes place.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "The sub-base is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) below the base course",
            "b) above the base course",
            "c) below the sub-grade",
            "d) above the wearing course"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The base course contains granular material that is at least given a relative compaction of 95%.The base course is approximately 10 to 15 cm thick. The base course also contains a dry mix of cement and aggregates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "The strength of sub-grade is increased by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) compaction",
            "b) swelling",
            "c) bulking",
            "d) addition of excess of water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sub-base is below the base course and above the sub-grade. Sub-base is often the main load-bearing layer of the pavement. The sub-base spreads the load evenly over the subgrade. The materials used may be either unbound granular, or cement-bound.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "The maximum legal axle wheel load is _________ kg as specified by IRC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3473",
            "b) 5466",
            "c) 8170",
            "d) 4085"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compaction is a process by which the soil particles are compacted by loads into a closer state. This reduces the voids ratio which in turn increases the dry density of the soil sample. This increases the strength of the sub-grade.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "The maximum stress occurs on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertical plane passing through radial distance of one from the point of load application",
            "b) vertical plane passing through radial distance of two from the point of load application",
            "c) vertical plane passing through the point of load application",
            "d) vertical plane passing through radial distance of three from the point of load application"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stress equation is given by,\n \\(σ_z=\\frac{3Q}{2πz^2} \\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{r}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{5}{2},\\) \nif r=0, we get the maximum stress value. Hence, the maximum stress occurs on vertical plane passing through the point of load application.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "The stress σz at any point (r,z) below the pavement is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(σ_z=\\frac{3P}{2πz^2}\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{r}{z})^3}\\right]^\\frac{5}{2}\\) ",
            "b) \\(σ_z=\\frac{3P}{2πz^2}\\left[\\frac{1}{(\\frac{r}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{5}{2}\\) ",
            "c) \\(σ_z=\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{r}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{5}{2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(σ_z=\\frac{3P}{2πz^2}\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{r}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{5}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The stress σz at any point (r,z) below the pavement is given by,\n\\(σ_z=\\frac{3P}{2πz^2}\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{r}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{5}{2},\\) \nWhere, σz is the vertical stress\nP is the point load acting at the ground surface\nr is the radial horizontal distance\nz is the vertical distance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "For the loaded circular area of radius a, the vertical stress on a vertical line passing through the center of the loaded area is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(σ_z=p\\left[1-\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{a}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{3}{2}\\right]\\) ",
            "b) \\(σ_z=p\\left[1+\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{a}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{3}{2}\\right]\\) ",
            "c) \\(σ_z=p\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{a}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{3}{2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(σ_z=p\\left[1-\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{a}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{5}{2}\\right]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vertical pressure σz under a uniformly loaded circular area is given by,\n\\(σ_z=p\\left[1-\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{a}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{3}{2}\\right]\\) \nwhere, p=load intensity per unit area\na=radius of circle\nz= depth of point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "For a loaded circular area of radius ‘a’, μ=Poisson’s ratio, the horizontal radial stress is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(σ_r=\\frac{p}{2} \\left[1+2μ-\\frac{2(1+μ)z}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}\\right]\\) ",
            "b) \\(σ_r=\\frac{p}{2} \\left[\\frac{2(1+μ)z}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+\\frac{z^3}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{3}{2}}\\right]\\) ",
            "c) \\(σ_r=\\frac{p}{2} \\left[1-2μ-\\frac{2(1+μ)z}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+\\frac{z^3}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{3}{2}}\\right]\\) ",
            "d) \\(σ_r=\\frac{p}{2} \\left[1+2μ-\\frac{2(1+μ)z}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+\\frac{z^3}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{3}{2}}\\right]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a loaded circular area of radius ‘a’, the horizontal radial stress is given by,\n\\(σ_r=\\frac{p}{2} \\left[1+2μ-\\frac{2(1+μ)z}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+\\frac{z^3}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{3}{2}}\\right],\\) \nwhere, σr= horizontal radial stress\np=load intensity per unit area\nμ=Poisson’s ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "The vertical strain ∈z due to triaxial load (σz,σr,σt=σr) under the center of plate is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(∈_z=\\frac{1}{E}[σ_z-μ(σ_r)]\\) ",
            "b) \\(∈_z=\\frac{1}{E}[σ_z-2μ(σ_r)]\\) ",
            "c) \\(∈_z=\\frac{1}{E}[σ_z-23μ(σ_r)]\\) ",
            "d) \\(∈_z=\\frac{1}{E}[σ_z-0.43μ(σ_r)]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The vertical strain ∈z due to triaxial load (σz,σr,σt=σr) under the center of plate is given by,\n\\(∈_z=\\frac{1}{E}[σ_z-2μ(σ_r)],\\) \nwhere,\nσz=vertical stress\nE=elastic modulus\nμ= Poisson’s ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "The elastic strain ∆ of the subgrade is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(∆=\\frac{p}{E}\\left[(2-2μ^2)(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{(1+μ) z^2}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+(μ+2μ^2-1)z\\right]\\) ",
            "b) \\(∆=\\frac{p}{2}\\left[\\frac{2(1+μ)z}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+ \\frac{z^3}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{3}{2}}\\right]\\) ",
            "c) \\(∆=\\frac{p}{2}\\left[1-2μ-\\frac{2(1+μ)z}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+ \\frac{z^3}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{3}{2}}\\right]\\) ",
            "d) \\(∆=\\frac{p}{2}\\left[1+2μ-\\frac{2(1+μ)z}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+ \\frac{z^3}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{3}{2}}\\right]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vertical strain is given by,\n\\(∆=\\frac{1}{E}[σ_z-2μ(σ_r)],\\) also the vertical and horizontal stresses are given by,\n\\(σ_z=p\\left[1-\\left[\\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{a}{z})^2}\\right]^\\frac{3}{2}\\right]\\, and\\, σ_r=\\frac{p}{2}\\left[1+2μ-\\frac{2(1+μ)z}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+ \\frac{z^3}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{3}{2}}\\right],\\) \ntherefore from the three equations, we get,\n\\(∆=\\frac{p}{E}\\left[(2-2μ^2)(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{(1+μ) z^2)}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+(μ+2μ^2-1)z\\right]\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "For a Poisson’s ratio of 0.5, the elastic strain ∆ is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(∆=\\frac{3pa^2}{2E} \\) ",
            "b) \\(∆=\\frac{pa^2}{2E(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}} \\) ",
            "c) \\(∆=\\frac{3pa^2}{2E(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}} \\) ",
            "d) \\(∆=\\frac{a^2}{2E(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}} \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The elastic strain is given by,\n\\(∆=\\frac{p}{E}\\left[(2-2μ^2)(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{(1+μ) z^2)}{(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}+(μ+2μ^2-1)z\\right]\\)substituting μ=0.5,\n∴ \\(∆=\\frac{3pa^2}{2E(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}. \\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "For a Poisson’s ratio of 0.5, the elastic strain ∆ in terms of Boussinesq settlement factor is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} F_B\\) ",
            "b) \\(∆=\\frac{3pa^2}{2E} F_B\\) ",
            "c) \\(∆=\\frac{a^2}{2E} F_B\\) ",
            "d) \\(∆=\\frac{pa^2}{2E} F_B\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the Poisson’s ratio is 0.5, the elastic strain ∆ is given by,\n\\(∆=\\frac{3pa^2}{2E(a^2+z^2)^\\frac{1}{2}},\\) the Boussinesq settlement factor is \\(F_B=\\frac{3}{2}  \\frac{1}{(1+(\\frac{z}{a})^2)^\\frac{1}{2}},\\) \n∴ substituting in the equation,\n \\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} F_B.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "The Boussinesq settlement factor is given by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(F_B=\\frac{3}{2}  \\frac{1}{1+(\\frac{z}{a})^2}\\) ",
            "b) \\(F_B=\\frac{3}{2}  \\frac{1}{(1+(\\frac{z}{a})^2)^\\frac{5}{2}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(F_B=\\frac{3}{2}  \\frac{1}{(1+(\\frac{z}{a})^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(F_B=\\frac{1}{(1+(\\frac{z}{a})^2)^\\frac{1}{2}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Boussinesq settlement factor is given by equation,\n\\(F_B=\\frac{3}{2}  \\frac{1}{(1+(\\frac{z}{a})^2)^\\frac{1}{2}},\\) \nwhere, FB= Boussinesq settlement factor\nz=depth of point\na=radius of the loaded area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "If the load is at the surface of subgrade, the Boussinesq settlement factor is given by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 2.5",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the load is at the surface of subgrade, z=0,\n∴ \\(F_B=\\frac{3}{2}\\frac{1}{(1+(\\frac{z}{a})^2)^\\frac{1}{2}} =\\frac{3}{2}\\frac{1}{(1+(\\frac{0}{a})^2)^\\frac{1}{2}} \\) \n∴ FB=1.5.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "If the load is at the surface of subgrade, the elastic strain is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} 1.5\\) ",
            "b) \\(∆=\\frac{3pa^2}{2E} 2.5\\) ",
            "c) \\(∆=\\frac{a^2}{2E} 3\\) ",
            "d) \\(∆=\\frac{pa^2}{2E} 3.5\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the Poisson’s ratio is 0.5, the elastic strain ∆ is given by,\n\\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} F_B,\\) and at the surface, z=0,\n∴ FB=1.5\nHence, \\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} 1.5.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "The Burmister’s influence coefficient is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_B=\\frac{σ_z}{p}  \\) ",
            "b) CB=σz-p",
            "c) CB=σz*p",
            "d) CB=σz+p"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vertical stress at any depth z is,\nσz=CB p. Therefore, the Burmister’s influence coefficient is given by,\n\\(C_B=\\frac{σ_z}{p}.  \\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "If F is a dimensionless factor, the defection in rigid plate of radius a is__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} 1.5F\\) ",
            "b) \\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} 1.18F\\) ",
            "c) \\(∆=\\frac{a^2}{2E} 1.18F\\) ",
            "d) \\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} 2F\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The defections for a two layer system is obtained from,\n\\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} 1.5F,\\) for flexible pavement\n\\(∆=\\frac{pa}{E} 1.18F,\\) for rigid pavement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Maximum wheel load is the greatest load transmitted by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) a single wheel",
            "b) two wheels",
            "c) three wheels",
            "d) four wheels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum wheel load is the greatest load transmitted by a single wheel of the vehicle. The pavement is usually designed from the consideration of the greatest load transmitted by a single wheel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "The pressure transmitted to the surface of the pavement by the wheel is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) differential pressure",
            "b) absolute pressure",
            "c) contact pressure",
            "d) atmospheric pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The contact pressure is the pressure transmitted to the surface of the pavement by the contact of the wheel on the pavement surface. This contact pressure depends upon:\n\ntyre pressure \nstiffness of the tyre walls.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "The contact area of wheel is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) triangular",
            "b) square",
            "c) rectangular",
            "d) circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since, Area=Load/Pressure, the contact area shape for the wheel and the pavement is nearly an elliptical region. It is assumed to be circular for making the problems simple to proceed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Based on the equal deflection criterion, the expression for the equivalent wheel load Pe is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(F_e \\sqrt{P_e}=(F_1+F_2)\\sqrt{P} \\) ",
            "b) \\(F_e \\sqrt{P_e}=(F_1-F_2) \\sqrt{P}\\) ",
            "c) \\(F_e \\sqrt{P_e}=(F_1*F_2) \\sqrt{P}\\) ",
            "d) \\(F_e \\sqrt{P_e}=(F_1/F_2) \\sqrt{P}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The equivalent wheel load Pe is given by,\n\\(F_e \\sqrt{P_e}=(F_1+F_2)\\sqrt{P},\\) \nWhere, Pe=equivalent wheel load\nP=wheel load of each of the dual tyres\nFe=settlement factor for equivalent wheel load\nF1= settlement factor contributed by one tyre of the\nF2= settlement factor contributed by other tyre.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "_________is an empirical method based on soil classification and other factor like climate and moisture.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Group index method",
            "b) Plate bearing test mathod",
            "c) CBR",
            "d) North Dakota cone method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The group index method and the Federal aviation agency method are the empirical methods based on soil classification and other factor like climate and moisture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "The group index method of design of flexible pavement was suggested by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) O.J. Porter",
            "b) California state highway",
            "c) Highway research board",
            "d) North Dakota state highway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The group index method of design of flexible pavement was suggested by Highway research board (1945). California state highway devised the California bearing ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "The California bearing ratio method was originally devised by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) O.J. Porter",
            "b) California state highway",
            "c) Highway research board",
            "d) North Dakota state highway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The California bearing ratio method was originally devised by O.J. Porter and then by California state highway department. It has since been developed by other authorities in the U.S.A., notably by U.S Crops of Engineers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "In CBR test, the cylindrical plunger of ________ diameter is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 cm",
            "b) 10 cm",
            "c) 15 cm",
            "d) 20 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The California bearing ratio test carried out in small scale in which a cylindrical plunger is of 3 in2 or 5 cm in diameter is penetrated in to the soil mass or the sub-grade material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "In CBR test, the rate of penetration of plunger is _______ mm/min.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25",
            "b) 1.25",
            "c) 2.35",
            "d) 3.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The California bearing ratio test carried out in small scale in which a cylindrical plunger is of 3 in2 or 5 cm in diameter is penetrated in to the soil mass or the sub-grade material at the rate of 1.25 mm/min or 0.05 inch per minute.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "In CBR test, the standard load is the penetration resistance of plunger into a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) standard sample of crushed stones",
            "b) clay",
            "c) saturated silt",
            "d) peat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In California bearing ratio test, the standard load is the penetration resistance of plunger into a standard sample of aggregates. The test load is the penetration resistance of the sample that is tested.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "The CBR is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{Test \\,load}{standard \\,load}*100\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{standard \\,load}{test \\,load}*100\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{2*Test\\, load}{standard \\,load}*100\\) ",
            "d) Test load*100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The California bearing ratio (CBR) is defined as the ratio of the test load to the standard load, expressed as percentage of a given penetration of the plunger.\n\\(CBR=\\frac{Test \\,load}{standard \\,load}*100.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "The CBR mould has internal diameter of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200mm",
            "b) 50mm",
            "c) 100mm",
            "d) 150mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The CBR mould has an internal diameter of 150 mm and an effective height of 175 mm. The mould is provided with a detachable collar of 50 mm in height and a detachable perforated base plate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "The CBR values are generally calculated for penetrations of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5mm and 5mm",
            "b) 5mm and 7mm",
            "c) 7mm and 9mm",
            "d) 9mm and 10mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The CBR values are generally calculated for penetrations of 2.5 mm and 5 mm. This can be related from the graph of load and penetration which shows linear variation of penetration with the applied loads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "When load is applied on rigid pavement, it deforms in a _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) bottle shape",
            "b) saucer shape",
            "c) rectangular shape",
            "d) square shape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The base course of the rigid pavement consists of dry mix of cement and granular materials or aggregates which can prevent the seepage of fine grained particles to the rigid pavement surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "The radius of relative stiffness is given by the characteristic equation of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(l=\\{\\frac{eh^3}{12(1-μ^2 ) k_s}\\}^\\frac{1}{4}\\) ",
            "b) \\(l=\\{\\frac{eh^3}{12(1-μ^4 ) k_s}\\}^\\frac{1}{4}\\) ",
            "c) \\(l=\\{\\frac{eh^3}{12(1-μ^2 ) k_s}\\}^\\frac{1}{2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(l=\\{\\frac{eh^3}{12(1-μ^2 ) k_s}\\}^\\frac{1}{3}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When load is applied on rigid pavement, it deforms in a saucer shape. This is due to the fact that the rigid pavements are designed on the basis of the design of slabs and their deflections are in the saucer shape.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "If P is the vertical relation and ρ is the vertical deflection, then the modulus of sub-grade reaction is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(k_s=\\frac{P}{ρ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(k_s=\\frac{1}{P}\\) ",
            "c) \\(k_s=\\frac{ρ}{P}\\) ",
            "d) \\(k_s=\\frac{P}{2ρ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The radius of relative stiffness is given by the characteristic equation of,\n\\(l=\\{\\frac{eh^3}{12(1-μ^2 ) k_s}\\}^\\frac{1}{4},\\) \nwhere, l=radius of relative stiffness\nE=elasticity modulus\nh=thickness of pavement\nμ=Poisson’s ratio\nks=modulus of sub-grade reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "The stresses in rigid pavement are due to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) restrained temperature only",
            "b) external loads only",
            "c) frost action only",
            "d) restrained temperature, external loads and frost action"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The modulus of sub-grade reaction is defined as the intensity of pressure on the horizontal surface of a soil mass required to cause a unit settlement of surface.\n∴ \\(k_s=\\frac{P}{ρ}.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "The temperature in general at the bottom of the slab is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) constant",
            "b) variant",
            "c) constant during the days only",
            "d) constant during the nights only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The base course forms a working surface on clays and silts. Thus, the base course enables the construction to proceed during wet weather on clays and silts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "In a day, the top surface of rigid pavement ______ than the bottom of slab.",
        "Options": [
            "a) expands",
            "b) contracts",
            "c) remains stable",
            "d) shows no changes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors affecting stresses in rigid pavements are broadly placed in four categories:\n\nStresses due to restrained temperature and moisture deformation\n\tStresses due to external loads\n\tStresses due to volume changes of supporting material and frost action\n\tStresses due to continuity of sub-grade support.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "If there is no friction between the slab and the sub-grade, then there are ______ in slab.",
        "Options": [
            "a) no stresses",
            "b) small number of stresses",
            "c) large number of stresses",
            "d) temperature gradients"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The surface of the slab is subjected to a wide range of temperatures during the daily cycle. As far as the bottom surface is considered, the temperature in general is relatively more constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "During expansion the under-side of the slab is subjected to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tensile stress",
            "b) shearing stress",
            "c) compressive stress",
            "d) bulk stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a day, as the temperature in the top of rigid pavement is hot or at least more than that of the bottom, the the top surface of rigid pavement expands more than the bottom of slab.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "During contraction, _________ are induced in the under-side of the slab.",
        "Options": [
            "a) tensile stress",
            "b) shearing stress",
            "c) compressive stress",
            "d) bulk stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stresses are set up in the slab due to uniform temperature changes. If this is absent and the slab is free to move without resistance, then there is no friction between the slab and sub-grade. Thus, if there is no friction between the slab and the sub-grade, then there are no stresses in slab.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "The critical stress condition in slab is when _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) temperature and load stresses are multiplicative",
            "b) temperature and load stresses are additive",
            "c) temperature and load stresses oppose each other",
            "d) critical stress condition does not occur in slab"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During expansion the under-side of the slab is subjected to compression. This can be visualised by the hogging action of the beam where the under-side is in compression.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "The critical stress condition in slab occurs when __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) corners remain unwrapped",
            "b) corners are wrapped upward",
            "c) corners are wrapped downward",
            "d) corners are wrapped laterally"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During contraction, the tensile stresses are induced in the under-side of the slab. This can be visualised by the sagging action of the beam where the under-side is in tension. This is also due to the tensile stresses induced due to the sub-grade friction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "The critical stress condition in slab occurs when __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) load is applied at exterior of the slab",
            "b) load is applied at exterior and interior of the slab",
            "c) no load is applied",
            "d) load is applied at interior of the slab"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The critical stress condition in the slab is the one in which the stresses due to temperature and stresses due to load are additive. This takes place when the slab corners are wrapped down.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "During the clear, cool night followed by a hot sunny day, the edges and corners of slab will ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) wrap downward",
            "b) wrap upward",
            "c) wrap upwards and downwards",
            "d) wrap laterally"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The critical stress condition in slab is when temperature and load stresses are additive. This happens when the road is hot in day and cold in night. When the corners are wrapped downward, the critical stress condition in slab occurs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Stabilisation of soils are most commonly used in __________ engineering works.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air-field pavements",
            "b) Foundations of buildings",
            "c) Pile construction",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most common application of stabilisation is in the construction of roads and air-field pavements."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Method of stabilisation can be grouped under________ main types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) three",
            "b) two",
            "c) one",
            "d) four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Method of stabilisation may be grouped under two main categories: i) modification of soil property of existing soil without any admixture ii) modification of soil property with the help of admixtures."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "Example of modification of soil property with the help of admixtures is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compaction",
            "b) Drainage",
            "c) Mechanical stabilisation",
            "d) Particle size distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Example of modification of soil property with the help of admixtures is: mechanical stabilization, stabilization with cement, lime, bitumen and chemicals etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "The important factors that governs the engineering behavior of soil are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Densification",
            "b) Stabilisation",
            "c) Tensile strength",
            "d) Particle size distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The particle size distribution and composition are the important factors governing the engineering behavior of soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "Mechanical stabilisation of soil involves which of the following operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compaction and Changing the composition of soil",
            "b) Leveling",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mechanical stabilisation involves two operations: i) changing the composition of soil by addition or removal of certain constituents, and ii) densification or compaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "For mechanical stabilized bases, liquid limit should not exceed __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35 %",
            "b) 25 %",
            "c) 50 %",
            "d) 10 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For bases, liquid limit should not exceed 25 % and plasticity index must not exceed 6."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "The properties of a soil under compaction depend upon _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Swelling",
            "b) Placement condition",
            "c) Water content",
            "d) Permeability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The properties of soil under compaction depend upon the water content, amount of compaction, and the type of compaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "The properties of soil that are affected by compaction are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Swelling",
            "b) Water absorption",
            "c) Permeability",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Compaction has a great effect on soil properties, such as strength and stress-strain characteristics, permeability, compression, swelling, and water absorption."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "The soil stabilised with cement is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lime cement",
            "b) Soil cement",
            "c) Cementing soil",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The soil stabilised with cement (Portland cement) is usually known as soil cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "The important factor affecting soil cement is________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Admixtures",
            "b) Swelling",
            "c) Water absorption",
            "d) Permeability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The important factors affecting the soil cement are: nature of soil, cement content, condition s of mixing, compaction and curing and admixtures."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "The binding action of individual particles through cement is possible only in __________ type of soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fine-grained soil",
            "b) Clayey soil",
            "c) Coarse-grained soil",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The binding action of individual particles through cement may be only possible in coarse-grained soil. In fine-grained, cohesive soils, only some of the particles can be expected to have cement bonds, and the rest may be bonded through natural cohesion."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "Which of the following is proved to be useful, ongoing over the site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excavation",
            "b) Escarpments",
            "c) Flood marks",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: On going over the site, a study of the following features may be useful: local topography, excavations, cuttings, escarpments, flood marks and evidence of erosion."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "The methods of site investigation are dependent upon ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Climatic condition",
            "b) Nature of engineering project",
            "c) Local topography",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The methods of site investigation are largely dependent upon the nature of the engineering project and the site."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "The information that should be yielded on site exploration is________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rock formation",
            "b) Depth of ground water",
            "c) Structural loading",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Site exploration should yield precise information about the following: i) the order of occurrence and extent of soil and rock strata ii) the nature and engineering properties of soil, and iii) the location of ground water."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "In site exploration, depth up to which the increase in pressure is likely to cause shear failure is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Failure depth",
            "b) Significant depth",
            "c) Pressure depth",
            "d) Depth of exploration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Exploration in general, should be carried out to a depth up to which the increase in pressure due to structural loading is likely to cause perceptible failure or shear failure. Such a depth is known as the significant depth."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "Depending upon the details, the site exploration may be classified as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) General and Detailed",
            "b) Complex",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Depending upon the details or the precision of the sub-soil data to be obtained, the site exploration may be classified as general (or preliminary) and detailed."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "The general exploration gives information about which of the following features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth of rock",
            "b) Composition of soil strata",
            "c) Ground water level",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The general exploration is able to give information about the following:\ni) Depth, extent and composition of soil strata.\nii) Depth of rock, when necessary\niii) Ground water level\niv) Preliminary selection of foundation type\nv) Compressibility of soil strata."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "For pile foundations, the depth of exploration at the start of the work is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 meters",
            "b) 40 meters",
            "c) 70 meters",
            "d) 200 meters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The depth of exploration at the start of the work or the significant depth, for pile foundation, should be 10 to 30 meters, or more, at least one and a half times the width of the structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "What are the methods used for general exploration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Subsurface penetration",
            "b) Ground water exploration",
            "c) Rock Cuttings",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Exploratory borings, shallow test pits, subsurface penetration, soundings and geophysical methods are used for general exploration."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "The feature that helps to estimate the relative density of coarse-grained soil is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soundings",
            "b) Shallow test pits",
            "c) Exploratory borings",
            "d) Geophysical method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Penetration and soundings help in estimating the relative density and strength properties of coarse-grained soils and also to locate the weaker strata and lenses."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "The number and disposition of bore holes are varied, depending upon _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surroundings",
            "b) Strata",
            "c) Subsoil condition",
            "d) Ground water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Depending upon the subsoil conditions the number and disposition of bore holes are varied, usually in the valley floor, on the abutment etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "In detailed exploration, the field test is conducted to determine ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tensile strength",
            "b) Rigidity",
            "c) Permeability",
            "d) Water content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The field test may be conducted for determining the in-situ values of density, bearing capacity, shearing strength, permeability, and pore pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "The various method of site exploration can be grouped under, which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open excavations and Borings",
            "b) Soil strata",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The various method of exploration may be grouped as follows:\ni) Open excavation\nii) Borings\niii) Sub-surface soundings\niv) Geophysical methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Exploratory borings in general exploration is carried out by using ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auger",
            "b) Bore equipment",
            "c) Well curb",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In general exploration, exploratory borings are carried out by auger, auger and shell and by wash boring."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Hand auger can be used for depths up to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7 m",
            "b) 6 m",
            "c) 2 m",
            "d) 10 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mechanical augers are used for greater depth and Hand augers are used for depth up to 6 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "Auger boring is used in __________ type of soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesion less soil",
            "b) Cohesive soil",
            "c) Coarse-grained soil",
            "d) Pervious soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Augers are used in cohesive and other soft soils above the water table."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "The type of boring, used for making deep excavations is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cylindrical augers",
            "b) Percussion boring",
            "c) Rotary boring",
            "d) Wash boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cylindrical augers and shell with cutting edge on teeth at the lower end can be used for making deep boring."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is adopted for fast boring?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cylindrical augers",
            "b) Percussion boring",
            "c) Rotary boring",
            "d) Wash boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Wash boring is a fast and simple method for advancing holes for all types of soils."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "Rotary boring can also be called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Percussion boring",
            "b) Wash boring",
            "c) Core boring",
            "d) Pit boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rotary borings are used for rotary drilling and simultaneously obtaining the rock cores or samples. The method is then also known as core boring or core drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Auger boring is most suitable for __________ type of work.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air field pavement",
            "b) Highway exploration",
            "c) Dam construction",
            "d) Buildings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Auger boring is fairly satisfactory for highway explorations at shallow depths and for exploring borrow pits."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "Wash boring cannot be used for _________ type of soil strata.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesive soil",
            "b) Cohesion less soil",
            "c) Boulder",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wash boring cannot be used for strata containing boulders and rocks, as they cannot be penetrated by this method."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "Mud rotary drilling belongs to _________ type of boring method.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Percussion boring",
            "b) Rotary boring",
            "c) Wash boring",
            "d) Auger boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A drilling mud is forced downed in rotary boring, hence the method is also known as mud rotary drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "The Instruments used in hand augers are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Post hole auger",
            "b) Sand pump",
            "c) Wash boring apparatus",
            "d) Stationary piston"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Helical auger and Post hole auger are the common types of Hand auger in use."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "The type of boring method that can be used for both rock and soils are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shell boring",
            "b) Wash boring",
            "c) Auger boring",
            "d) Rotary boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rotary boring or rotary drilling is a very fast method of advancing hole in both rocks and soil by drill rod."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "The commonly used geophysical method for site exploration is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravitational method",
            "b) Electrical resistivity",
            "c) Magnetic method",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electrical resistivity and seismic refraction methods are the most commonly used for civil engineering purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Electrical resistivity method is based on measurement of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specific resistance",
            "b) Voltage",
            "c) Potential drop",
            "d) Current"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electrical resistivity method is based on the measurement and recording of changes in the mean resistivity or apparent specific resistance of the various soils."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "The method used for studying of horizontal changes in the sub-soil is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resistive soundings",
            "b) Resistive mapping",
            "c) Mean resistivity",
            "d) Critical distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For knowing the horizontal changes in the sub-soil, the electrodes kept at a constant spacing are moved as a group along the line of test. This method is known as resistive mapping."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "The commonly used penetration test are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS penetration test",
            "b) Cone penetration test",
            "c) Dutch standard test",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Standard penetration test and the cone penetration test is the two commonly used penetration test."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "In the seismic refraction method, the waves sent along the ground surface is picked by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geo satellite instrument",
            "b) Geophone",
            "c) Wave detector",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The radiating shock waves created in to the soil at the ground level are picked up by the vibration detector known as a geophone."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "The depth of exploration for isolated spread footing is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)  the width",
            "b) 2\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) the width",
            "c) \\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) the width",
            "d) \\(\\frac{1}{4}\\)  the width"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The depth of exploration for isolated spread footing is one and a half times the width. While the  depth of exploration is twice the height from stream bed to crest for concrete dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "In hand operated rings in ‘auger and shell boring’ the depth of which it can be used is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 m",
            "b) 30 m",
            "c) 25 m",
            "d) 15 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The hand operated rings in ‘auger and shell boring’ are used for depths up to 25 m and the mechanised rings up to 50 m. In auger boring, hand augers are used for depths up to about 6 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "Auger is suitable for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) soft to stiff clays",
            "b) very stiff clays",
            "c) sandy soils",
            "d) hard clays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Auger boring is suitable for soft to stiff clays as the soil samples can be removed in a less disturbed manner preserving most of the natural structure of sample as compared to the wash boring.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "In rotator boring __________ is forced down the hallow drillrods.",
        "Options": [
            "a) glycerine",
            "b) water solution of bentonite",
            "c) dextrin",
            "d) phenyl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In rotator boring, a drilling mud, usually a water solution of bentonite with or without other admixtures is continuously forced down the hollow drilling rods. The mud returning upwards bring the cuttings to the surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "A ________ sample has preserved natural structure of soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) undisturbed",
            "b) disturbed",
            "c) non-representative",
            "d) remoulded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The undisturbed sample of the soil is the one which has the natural structure in a preserved state which may be obtained by freezing the sand up to the required depth.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "________ sample has the natural structure of soil as modified.",
        "Options": [
            "a) undisturbed",
            "b) disturbed",
            "c) representative",
            "d) non-remoulded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The disturbed sample of the soil has the natural structure of soil as modified due to the disturbance caused while collecting the soil sample. It is usually obtained by pump and shells with trap valve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "The depth up to which the increase in pressure due to structural loading is likely to cause perceptible settlement is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) insignificant depth",
            "b) significant depth",
            "c) trifling depth",
            "d) nugatory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The area ratio of the soil sampler is defined as the ratio of the volume of the soil sample displaced by the sampler tube in proportion to the volume of sample.\n∴ Area ratio=\\(\\frac{D_2^2-D_1^2}{D_1^2}×100.\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "The significant depth is assumed up to a level at which the net increase in vertical pressure becomes _______ of initial overburden pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10% to 20%",
            "b) less than 10%",
            "c) 20% to 30%",
            "d) 50% to 70%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The inside clearance of the sampler is defined as the difference between the outside diameter and the inside diameter of the core part through which the core enters.\n∴ Inside clearance = \\(\\frac{D_3-D_1}{D_1} ×100. \\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Thick wall samplers have area ratio______",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater than 20 -35%",
            "b) greater than 10- 25%",
            "c) lesser than 10 -25%",
            "d) lesser than 15 -35%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thin-wall samplers are the samplers in which the wall thickness of the sampling tube is less than 2.5% of the diam¬eter. Samplers for which the area ratio is greater than 10- 25% are known as thick-wall samplers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "_______ sampler is suitable for soft soils.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open drive sampler",
            "b) Rotary sampler",
            "c) Stationary position",
            "d) No sampler"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stationary position sampler is suitable for soft soils. The stationary position sampler contains a piston or plug attached to a long piston rod extending up to the ground surface through the drill rod.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "For soft sensitive soil, the area ratio of sample ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) should not exceed  20%",
            "b) should not exceed  10%",
            "c) should not exceed  15%",
            "d) should not exceed  40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For soft sensitive soil, the area ratio of sample should preferably not exceed 10%. The thin-wall samplers are those for which the area ratio is less than or equal to 10%. Samplers for which the area ratio is more than 10% are known as thick-wall samplers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "The inside clearance of the sampler should _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) lie between 1 to 3%",
            "b) be less than 1%",
            "c) lie between 2 to 6%",
            "d) lie between 1 to 6%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The inside clearance of the sampler should lie between 1 to 3%. The outside clearance of the sampler should not be much greater than the inside clearance of the sampler.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "For sampling saturated cohesion-less soils _______ is inserted.",
        "Options": [
            "a) inner liner",
            "b) oil",
            "c) trap valve",
            "d) wood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For sampling saturated cohesion-less soils, a trap valve or a spring sample retainer is inserted in the drive shoe or the cutting edge. This helps to retain the sample when the sampler is raised.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "The undistributed samples are obtained by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) thin wall samplers",
            "b) thick wall samplers",
            "c) both thin and thick wall samplers",
            "d) no type of samplers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The undistributed samples are obtained by thin wall samplers in which the wall thickness of the sampling tube is less than 2.5% of the diam¬eter or the area ratio is less than or equal to 10 %.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "To impart cohesion, ______ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) water",
            "b) asphaltic emulsions",
            "c) lime",
            "d) powder soda"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For obtaining undistributed samples of soils, cohesion to the sand is imparted by adding asphaltic emulsions, or to freeze the sand at the sampling depth or near the lower end of the sampler.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "For undistributed samples ______ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) compressed air sampler",
            "b) thick sampler",
            "c) care cutter",
            "d) rotary sampler"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For obtaining undistributed samples, compressed air samplers are used. It enables the sample to be removed from the ground into an air chamber and then lifted to the ground surface without contact with water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "For transport of sample to laboratory, the sample is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) wrapped in wax paper",
            "b) mixed with other samples",
            "c) given disturbance",
            "d) saturated with lime"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sampler should never be over driven so as to compress the sample. When the sampler is over driven, the soil sample gets compressed due to the air locked between the sampler and the sample.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "The measurement of resistance and penetration is done by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) dynamic and static loading",
            "b) dynamic loading only",
            "c) static loading only",
            "d) no loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The penetration and sounding tests involve the measurement of resistance to penetration of a sampling spoon or other tools under dynamic or static loadings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "The standard penetration test is given in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS: 800-2007",
            "b) IS: 2131-1981",
            "c) IS: 456-2000",
            "d) IS: 178- 2008"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The standard penetration test is given in IS: 2131-1981. The IS: 800-2007 is the code book for general construction in steel structures. IS: 456-2000 is the code book for general construction in plain and reinforced concrete.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "The standard penetration test is performed in clear hole of _____________ mm in diameter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 30",
            "b) 30 to 50",
            "c) 55 to 150",
            "d) 150 to 1000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to IS: 2131-1981, the standard penetration test is performed in clear hole of 55 to 150 mm in diameter. A casing or drilling mud is used to support the sides of the hole.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "The sampler in standard penetration test has outer diameter of _________ mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50.8",
            "b) 60.3",
            "c) 70.3",
            "d) 80.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the standard penetration test, thick wall samplers are used which has an outer diameter of 50.8 mm or 2 inches. The thick wall sampler is given an inner lining.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "The sample in standard penetration test has inner diameter of _________ mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50.8",
            "b) 60",
            "c) 35",
            "d) 75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the standard penetration test, thick wall split-tube samplers are used which has an inner diameter of 35 mm or 1.5 inches. The outer diameter of the sampler is 50.8 mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "The sample is driven by a weight of _____________ in sample in standard penetration test.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 65 kg",
            "b) 14 kg",
            "c) 55 kg",
            "d) 100 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In standard penetration test, the thick wall split-tube sampler is driven into the undisturbed soil at the bottom of the hole under the blows of a 65 kg or 140 lb drive weight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "The height of the free fall in sample in standard penetration test is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 cm",
            "b) 75 cm",
            "c) 100 cm",
            "d) 150 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In standard penetration test, the thick wall split-tube sampler is driven into the undisturbed soil at the bottom of the hole under the blows of a 65 kg drive weight with a free fall of 75 cm or 30 inches.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "The sampler is driven through ____________ as seating drive.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 cm",
            "b) 15 cm",
            "c) 100 cm",
            "d) 150 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum open length of the sampler should be 60 cm. When the sampler is driven through depth of first 15 cm, it is known as seating drive. Then the sampler is further driven beyond the 15 cm or the seating drive for the test.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "The penetration resistance is driving the sampler __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 cm beyond seating drive",
            "b) 30 mm beyond seating drive",
            "c) 30 cm beyond seating drive",
            "d) 10 cm beyond seating drive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the sampler is driven through depth of first 15 cm, it is known as seating drive. Then the sampler is further driven beyond the seating drive for another 30 cm or 12 inches or until 100 blows have been applied.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Refusal of standard penetration test occurs when the sampler penetrates ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than 2.5cm under 50 blows",
            "b) less than 2.5cm under 20 blows",
            "c) less than 2.5cm under 10 blows",
            "d) less than 2.5cm under 5 blows"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In standard penetration test, the refusal has is said to have been reached when the sampler penetrates less than 2.5cm under 50 blows. In very fine, silty, saturated sand, an apparent increase in resistance occurs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "The angle of internal friction for fines greater than 5% is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) φ=25+0.15 ID",
            "b) φ=20+0.15 ID",
            "c) φ=15+0.15 ID",
            "d) φ=10+0.15 ID"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Meyerhof in 1956 gave approximate values of φ with respect to density index ID. For fines greater than 5%, the general formula is,\nφ=25+0.15 ID\nwhere, φ=angle of internal friction\n ID= density index.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "The angle of internal friction for fines lesser than 5% is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) φ=25+0.15 ID",
            "b) φ=20+0.15 ID",
            "c) φ=15+0.15 ID",
            "d) φ=10+0.15 ID"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Meyerhof in 1956 gave approximate values of φ with respect to density index ID. For fines lesser than 5%, the general formula is,\nφ=20+0.15 ID\nwhere, φ=angle of internal friction\n ID= density index.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "In Dutch cone test, the base of cone is ____________ cm in diameter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.6",
            "b) 4.6",
            "c) 5.6",
            "d) 6.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Dutch cone test, the base of cone has a cross-sectional area of 10 cm2. The base of cone in Dutch cone test is 3.6 cm in diameter. The cone is carried at the lower end of the steel driving rod.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "In Dutch cone test, the angle of vector of cone is ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30°",
            "b) 60°",
            "c) 20°",
            "d) 45°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Dutch cone test is used for getting a continuous record of resistance of soil by penetrating a cone with an angle of 60° at the vertex. The base of the cone has a diameter of 3.6 cm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "To know the cone resistance, it is first forced down to _________ depth.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8 mm",
            "b) 8 cm",
            "c) 15 cm",
            "d) 30 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cone is carried at the lower end of the steel driving rod which passes through a mantle with external diameter equal to the base of cone. To know the cone resistance, it is first forced down to 8 cm depth.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "In Dutch cone test, the cone along with mantle is further penetrated after 8cm to a depth of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 cm",
            "b) 8 cm",
            "c) 15 cm",
            "d) 30 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Dutch cone test, the cone along with mantle is further penetrated after 8cm to a depth of 20 cm. This is done to know the cone resistance in penetration through the soil layers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "The cone test is very useful in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cohesion-less soils",
            "b) cohesive soils",
            "c) clays",
            "d) silty clay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cone test is considered very useful in determining the bearing capacity of pits or bores in cohesion-less soils. It is particularly useful in fine sands of varying density.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "The cone resistance is approximately equal to ______ times the penetration resistance N.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cone resistance in kg/cm2 is approximately equal to 10 times the penetration resistance N from the standard penetration test. The Dutch cone test is very useful in cohesion-less soils.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "In Seismic refraction method, the radiating shock waves are picked up by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) geophone",
            "b) wave buoy",
            "c) thermometer",
            "d) cohesive soils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Seismic refraction method, the radiating shock waves are picked up by the vibration detector known as geophone or seismometer where the time of travel gets recorded. The wave buoy measures the height of waves.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "The equivalent penetration resistance is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ne=15+\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)(N+15)",
            "b) Ne=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)(N-15)",
            "c) Ne=15+\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)(N-15)",
            "d) Ne=15+\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)(N)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In 1968, Goodman and Karol showed that in a blind zone, the geophone cannot detect the seisdmic refraction. The blind zone occurs when a layer having a velocity lower than that of the upper layer exists.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "If σ’ is the effective overburden pressure, then the effective penetration resistance is given by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ne=\\(N \\frac{50}{1.42σ^{‘}}\\) ",
            "b) Ne=\\(N \\frac{50}{σ^{‘}+10}\\) ",
            "c) Ne=\\(N \\frac{1}{1.42σ^{‘}+10}\\) ",
            "d) Ne=\\(N \\frac{50}{1.42σ^{‘}+10}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The seismic refraction method is fast and a reliable method in establishing profiles of different strata when the deeper layers have increasingly greater density and thus higher velocities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "The essential feature of reinforced earth is that __________ develops between compacted layer of earth and reinforcing elements.",
        "Options": [
            "a) friction",
            "b) tension",
            "c) compression",
            "d) shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reinforced earth consists of a compacted soil mass within which reinforcing elements are embedded. The essential feature of the reinforced earth is that friction develops between compacted layer of earth and reinforcing elements.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "______ is developed in reinforcement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Friction",
            "b) Tension",
            "c) Compression",
            "d) Shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The essential feature of reinforced earth is that friction develops between compacted layer of earth and reinforcing elements. The soil transfers the forces built up in the earth mass to the reinforcement by means of friction. Thus, tension is developed in the reinforcement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "The modern form of application of reinforced earth was first developed by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Darcy",
            "b) Skempton",
            "c) Henry Vidal",
            "d) Marshal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The modern form of application of reinforced earth was first developed by Henry Vidal who first constructed major retaining walls in France in 1968. Darcy has contributions in the field of soil permeability.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "The reinforcement members are used to provide _______ in earth mass where _____ are produced.",
        "Options": [
            "a) tensile strength, compressive stresses",
            "b) tensile strength, shear stresses",
            "c) compressive strength, tensile stresses",
            "d) shear strength, tensile stresses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reinforcement members are used to provide tensile strength in earth mass where shear stresses are produced. The provision of the members leads to the redistribution of the stresses internally within each member.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "In reinforcing elements, galvanised steel strips of _________ width and ____ thickness are used commonly.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 to 100 mm, 9mm",
            "b) 50 to 70 mm, 20mm",
            "c) 110 to 180 mm, 30mm",
            "d) 200 to 310 mm, 40mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In reinforcing elements, galvanised steel strips of 50 to 100 mm width and 9 mm thickness are used commonly. These galvanised steel strips are several meters in length.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "In general from the data on galvanised steel, it has a service life of _____ in soil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 days",
            "b) 120 months",
            "c) 10 years",
            "d) 120 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since the galvanised steel is resistant to corrosion, from the data available on the rate of corrosion of galvanised steel it indicates that, elements if this material are to have a service life of 120 years in soil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "The soil used in the backfill should have particles of not more than _____ passing 63 μm sieve.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 30%",
            "d) 40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The soil used in the backfill should predominantly be coarse-grained and it is proposed that not more than 10% of the particles should pass 63 μm sieve. The first level of the reinforced strips is placed at the ground level.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "The wall facing element is also known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) plaster",
            "b) POP",
            "c) skin",
            "d) coat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wall facing element is provided at the free boundary of a reinforced earth structure. This is done to provide some form of barrier and these elements are known as skin. These elements can be flexible or stiff.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "In general, the reinforced earth structures are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) flexible",
            "b) stiff",
            "c) rigid",
            "d) firm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In general, the reinforced earth structures are quite flexible. Being flexible, they can withstand foundation deformations or the foundation settlements. They can also withstand earthquake force more efficiently.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "By the use of reinforcing elements in earth __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) it restrains lateral deformation",
            "b) it provides lateral deformation",
            "c) it produces shear stress",
            "d) it produces shear failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most of the reinforced earth structures are quite flexible. Being flexible, they can be much easily transported. Since they can be transported easily, these can be constructed speedily.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "The tension T in reinforcement is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ti=γKahs",
            "b) Ti=zi Ka hs",
            "c) Ti=γzi Ka",
            "d) Ti=γzi Ka hs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tension T in reinforcement is given by,\nTi=pi A=γzi Ka hs, where A=h.s=effective area of strip\nKa=coefficient of active earth pressure\nTi=Tension in the reinforcement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "If F is the factor of safety and Fi is the frictional resistance, then the relation between them and tension Ti  in reinforcement is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fi=Ti F",
            "b) Fi=\\(\\frac{T_i}{F} \\) ",
            "c) Fi=Ti+F",
            "d) Fi=Ti-F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frictional resistance of the reinforcement is,\nFi=Ti F, Where, F=factor of safety\nTi=Tension in the reinforcement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "If δ is the angle of surface friction, then frictional resistance Fi is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fi=γzi tanδ*surface area of reinforcement",
            "b) Fi=γzi cosδ",
            "c) Fi=γzi sinδ*surface area of reinforcement",
            "d) Fi=γzi cotδ*surface area of reinforcement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frictional resistance of the reinforcement is,\nFi=Ti F, if δ is the angle of surface friction, then,\nFi=γzi tanδ*surface area of reinforcement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Geotextiles are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) permeable",
            "b) semi-permeable",
            "c) impermeable",
            "d) does not permeability characterises"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Geotextiles are porous fabrics and hence they are permeable. They are made from synthetic materials that are used with geotechnical materials like soils or rocks as an integral part.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "The geostrips are generally produced from ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) glycerine",
            "b) polypropylene",
            "c) dextrin",
            "d) benzene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The geostrips are a type of geotextiles. As per American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM), the geotextiles are permeable sheets of synthetic fibres like polypropylene, polyethylene etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Geotextiles are available in thickness varying from ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 5 mils",
            "b) 5 to 10 mils",
            "c) 10 to 20 mils",
            "d) 10 to 300 mils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The geotextiles are permeable sheets of synthetic fibres that are available in thickness varying from 10 to 300 mils. 1 mil=1/100 inch=0.254 mm. Due to their fine thickness, they are permeable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "If geotextiles are used as reinforcements, then they should have __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) low modulus of deformation",
            "b) high modulus of deformation",
            "c) low coefficient of friction",
            "d) low breaking strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the geotextiles are used as reinforcements in the soil, they should take up some of the tensile stresses and help to distribute them more evenly. Therefore, they must have high modulus of deformation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "The geotextiles are available in rolls of length _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 cm",
            "b) 5m",
            "c) up to 600m",
            "d) 1 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The geotextiles are permeable sheets of synthetic fibres that are available in thickness varying from 10 to 300 mils, widths up to 10 m and in rolls of length up to 600 m. The permeability of geotextile is comparable in range from coarse gravel to fine sand.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "The geocells or geowebs are stitched together at _________ intervals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 cm",
            "b) 200 to 50 mm",
            "c) upto 600 m",
            "d) 1 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The geocells or geowebs are stitched together at 200 to 50 mm intervals. They can even be welded together. The hexagonal or rhomboidal cells can be made of geosynthetic honeycomb design.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "The GCL is a composite of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) geotextiles and bentonite clay",
            "b) silt and gravel",
            "c) gravel and bentonite clay",
            "d) geotextiles and gravels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Bentofix Thermal Lock Geosynthetic clay liner (GCL) is a patented registered trade mark. It is a sandwiched composite of geotextiles and bentonite clay that is used to provide appositive barrier to liquids in containment applications.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "The exposure of the geotextiles to the elements tween lay down and covering should be a maximum of ____ days.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 14",
            "c) 150",
            "d) 365"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the geotextiles are used to provide tensile strength in places where the shear stresses are generated, the use of geotextiles leads to redistribution of the stresses and hence it can withstand differential settlements.\n"
    }
]